Having defined the principal of Maximum
Likelihood Estimation for a single,
parameter, we can now consider the more
complicated scenario where we're
interested in doing Maximum Likelihood
Estimation for the full ensemble of
parameters for a given Bayesian network
structure. So let's look at the more
general case where now we have a general
Bayesian network, not necessarily
binary valued. And our parameters now
consist of a set of parameters theta x for
all possible values of the variable x and
the set of parameters theta y given x for
all values of the parent x and the child y
and that's the parameterization of this
Bayesian network in this general case of
table CPDs. Now let's think about the
likelihood of, the parameters, the set of
parameters, theta, What does the
likelihood function look like? Well, the
likelihood function, remember, is the
probability of the data given the
parameters which decomposes because the
parameters are iid as the product of all
data instances Xm and Ym, relative to
the parameterization theta. Well so
we're going to break that probability up
using the chain rule for Bayesian
networks. And that's going to give me a
decomposition of this joint [inaudible]
probability. As a product of the
probability of, the parent x times, the
conditional probability of y given x,
which is, just again the [inaudible]
application of the chain rule in this very
simple example. And now I'm going to,
Basically break this up first into two
separate products. So I'm going to move
this product here, so I have one product
over just the first set of terms, and then
a second product over the y given x terms.
And then I'm going to observe that the
first set of terms, the probability of x m
only depends on the parameters theta x.
And the probability y m given x m only
depends on theta y given x. And so now
we've broken up the likelihood function
into a product of two, what are called local
likelihoods. Where a local likelihood is a
likelihood of just the variable X or just
the variable Y given its parents in
this case, X. So more generally, I
can do this exact same process in a somewhat
more general case where if we have a set
of variables x one up to x m then we can
once again look at the product over all
theta instances break this up using the
chain rule for Bayesian networks, as for each
instance the product of xi given its
parents where assuming that UI are the
parents, xi. Switch the order of the
products, so that's instead of doing, so I
switch it here, so instead of doing m.
First I do the, first the product over
variables, then the product over data
cases. And that gives me once again. A
product of terms which I'm going to call Li
Of the CPD for XI. And if we're willing
to assume that variables, that the
different CPDs don't share. Any parameter
so each CPD is effectively an
independent entity that can be estimated
separately then I can now, estimate, now
optimize theta of the ith variable
separately from all other variables by
optimizing this local likelihood term. If we
have table CPDs, it turns out we can
further decompose. So remember that we
started out with the probability now we
are looking at the local likelihood for
variable x given its parents U,
and as it depends on the CPD
for x given U. And what we are going to
do now is we are going to break up the
data cases into separate buckets so
for every value little x of X and
every value little u of the parent U,
we're going to multiply separately all the
instances M for which the Mth instance
takes that value little x and that value
little u. And so what I have basically
done is that I have divided all the instances
into these disjoint buckets. Now the
point is we know what this is, the
probability that xm takes the value of
little x. And given that Um takes the
value little u. Is simply the appropriate
CPD entry, theta X given U. And so this
turns into this expression over here. And
so now the question is how many
occurrences. Of theta x given u do I get?
Well, the answer is how many times I
multiply it in. The number of times that
little u, x occurs in the data. And so
this turns out to be simply a product over
all possible values of the child X and the
parent U. Of the appropriate CPD entry,
P of little x given u to the power of the
number of occurrences. Of little x comma
u. And if we now. Consider maximum likelihood
estimation. It's turns out the maximum
likelihood estimate of X of theta X given U, is
simply as one would expect, the fraction.
Of X = x among cases. Where U equals the
little u. So what happens with maximum
likelihood estimation when we have a model with
shared parameters. Let's consider that
question in the context of a hidden Markov
model where initially we are actually just going to look
at a Markov chain, that is a case where we
have just a single state variable. S and
we transition from one state to the other.
So let's look at the likelihood function
in this context before we consider what
maximum likelihood estimation would look like.
So the likelihood function of the
parameter vector theta, which dictates the
transition model, given a set of
observations of the states between time
zero and time T decomposes using the
Markov assumption as a product of t from
one to T of the probability of the state
at time t given the state at time t+1. Now
we can further reformulate this product by
looking at how it decomposes across
specific pairs of states S i and S j so we can first multiply over
all possible pairs of states i and j and
then consider all the time points
in which we transition from s i to s j And
then we have the probability of that
transition of Si to Sj. Now the critical
observation is that this probability is the
same regardless of the time point. This is
indicative of the time invariance assumption
that we have in these models. And so the
parameters specifically that we will be
multiplying in this context is simply the
transition parameter theta Si to Sj. Now
if we look at this expression, which has
all these products in it. The product of
IEJ, and then the product of the time
points, consistent with the transition, or
in which the transition from I to J took
place. We end up with the product over
here, which multiplies, over all IJ of the
parameter associated with that transition,
exponentiated by the sufficient
statistics. Msi to SJ, which is simply the
number of times in which the, in the data
stream that we saw, we had a transition
between those two states. Now if we now
consider what maximum likelihood estimation
would look like for this parameter,
theta.hat, sorry for the parameter theta
Si to Sj. The maximum likelihood estimate
theta.hat Si to Sj would be exactly what
we would expect. The number of transitions
in which, Si transitions to Sj, divided by
the number of total, occurrences, of the
state Si within the time sequenced. Let's
now elaborate this to the context of the
hidden Markov model just to see what
it would look like so here we have in
addition to the first component of the
likelihood function which is the same one
we had before just the transition
probabilities of the state sequence
we also have an additional component that
looks at every state from one to
big T of the probability of the
particular observation O of t given
state s of t. So we can just do the exact
same process of reformulating the
likelihood function. We've already seen
what the first term looks like, it's
exactly the same as the one we had on the
previous slide. Theta SI to SJ
exponentiated with sufficient statistics.
And we have. [inaudible] a very analogous
term that looks for over pairs of
[inaudible] of states i and
observations k the parameter that
corresponds to the kth observation in
state i exponentiated for the
sufficient statistics which is the number
of times that we saw in the same state in
the same time point the observation k and
the state i And so, adding now to our set
of sufficient statistics, in addition to
the counts of going from SI to SJ. We also
have sufficient statistics that count the
number of times, time points in which we
had the state SI and the observation O k.
[sound]. So to summarize maximum likelihood
estimation in the case of discreet. Graph
of Bayesian networks
that has disjoint sets of parameters in
the CPD. That is where each c p d has its
own set of parameters the likelihood
function decomposes as a product of local
likelihood functions and this is important
because we're going to use that later on,
one per variable. So the likelihood
function is a product of small likelihoods
or local likelihoods one per variable Now,
when we have table CPD, we get a further
decomposition. Specifically, even the
local likelihood now decomposes as a
product of. Likelihoods for specific
multinomials one for each combination of
the parents. And so now we get a further
decomposition that is basically going to
allow us to estimate each of those
multinomials separately via the same
maximum likelihood estimation that we had in the
original case estimating parameters for
single multinomials [inaudible] product of
these likelihood functions each of them
can be optimized separately. Finally, in the
very common case of networks that have
shared CPDs so this is the case
unlike the first bullet where we had
dis-joined sets of parameters here we have
shared CPDs we simply accumulate
the sufficient statistics over all
occurrences or uses of that CPD and then
once we do that, maximum likelihood estimation can be done in effectively the same way. Now
one important observation that arises from
the maximum likelihood estimation is worth
remembering and, and thinking about when
one uses this, so let's look at the form of
the, of the maximum likelihood estimate
for, for parameter theta x given u. And as
we have seen that is a ratio between m
between the number of counts of the
instantiation little x and the parent assignment u
divided by the sum of all. M X prime, U
for different values of X prime. Or
written otherwise is MXU divided by MU.
Now what are the consequences of this
expression when the number of parents
grows large. When the number of parents
grows larger, the number of buckets, that
is, the number of different possible
assignments, little U, increases
exponentially with the number of parents.
If you have two parents it's it grows
exponentially with 2 the number of
different buckets u but if you have
fifteen or twenty parents then the number
of buckets into which we need to partition
the data increases very quickly and that
means that most buckets, that is most
assignments little u will have very few
instances assigned to them which means
that effectively most of these estimates
which divide m of x u divided by m of u
will be done with Few or even zero
instances and review, at which point any
estimate is just totally bogus. And
specifically the that means that the
parameter estimate that we're going to get
in most of the multinomial parameters once
U gets large are going to be very poor. So this concept is called
fragmentation of the data. And, it has
following important consequence. If the
amount of data is limited. Relative to the
model dimensionality we can often get
better estimates of the parameters with
simpler structures even when these
structures are actually wrong. That is even
if we make incorrect independence
assumptions, that are Making, that a
removing edges that really ought to be
there. We can sometimes get better
generalization in terms of say log likelihood
of test data. Than when using
the much more complicated correct structure.