So we previously defined the notion of
Bayesian estimation, and showed how it
could be applied in the context of a
single random variable say, a multinomial
random variable. Now we're going to step
back to the world of probabilistic
graphical models and think about the
application of these ideas to the problem
of estimating parameters in a Bayesian
network. So let's draw again the
probabilistic graphical model that
represents Bayesian estimation in a
Bayesian network. So just as before in a
single variable case we're going to inject
into the model explicitly the parameters
that characterize sorry, random variables
that define the parameters. And so here we
have two random variables theta X which
represents the CPD of X. And theta Y given
X, which represents the CPD p of Y given
X. Notice that each of these actually
vector valued because there's gonna be
multiple actual numbers in each of these
CPDs, but we're going to draw them as
single circles. Now, once again, we can
look at this network, and read out certain
important conclusions. So the first
important conclusion is that the
instances, these XY pairs, are
independent, given the parameters. And you
can see that by noticing that if I
condition on both theta X and theta Y,
given X, then the, XY pairs become
conditionally, become [inaudible]
d-separated from each other. And so we have
conditional independence, following as a
consequence of the structure of the
graphical model. We also have, and this is
another explicit property that we can read
from this diagram, is that Theta-X and
Theta-Y given X, are marginally
independent. So a priori we have that
the parameter prior over all of the
parameters, theta, can be written as the
product over I, in this case random I is
being the random variable in the network
of the prior over the CPD for xi and so
the prior is the product of little priors,
one for each CPD. Now, it follows from
this. From by just writing down the, the
graphical model and looking at what the,
the implications of the expressions are
the, the posteriors of the theta are also
independent given complete data. And the
reason for that is that complete data
d-seperates the parameters for the two
CPDs. So if you look at this network over
here and assume that we have all of these
variables condition-, observed, then you
can see that there's no active path
between theta x and theta y given x.
Because, for example, if we look at
potentially this. Trail. We can see that
X2 blocks the trail from theta X to theta
Y, given X. And so, again, following
directly from the structure of this
network, we can see that the posterior
distribution, theta X, theta Y, given X
again. given D decomposes as a product of
the posterior over theta X given D, times
the posterior of theta Y, Y given X given
D. Which means just as in maximum likelihood
estimation where it can break up the
estimation problem into one of estimating
each cpd separately. We can do the same
here only now we can do it using Bayesian
estimation where instead of just picking a
single parameter setting for, for the cpd
we compute these separate posteriors
separately and then put them together into
a single posterior. Now it turns out that
we could do even finer breakdown in the
context of table CPDs. So here we have,
when we're now looking at the binary case
where X is a binary value random variable.
So now we have two multi-nomials in our
CPD, one for Y given X, one corresponding
to the case of Y given X1 and the other to
Y given X0. And it turns out that if;
again in this model we're assuming that
these are independent a priori. Which is
what this diagram says, because you notice
that there's no edges between them, so
they're marginally independent, theta y
given x one and theta y given x zero. If
we're postulating that, that holds, as we
are in this diagram, it turns out that
they are also independent in the
posterior. Now, that is a little bit
trickier to show, because it turns out
that you can't read it directly from the
diagram, because in fact even given
complete data, we have an active trail
that goes from. theta Y. Given X. One
through Y. One. Which since it's observed
it activates a V. Structure. Instance
theta Y given X0. But, it turns out. That
if we go back to some of the examples of
context-specific independence that we had
in the case of specifically multiplexer
CPD we can derive that these are in fact
despite the appearance of an activated V
structure conditionally independent in the
posterior as well. And so once again, we
can compute the posterior as a product of
posteriors of the form p of theta X given
D times the probability of theta Y given
X1 given D. times the probability of theta
one given X0. We can generalize this to a
general Bayesian network and let?s assume
that we have a Bayesian network with table
CPD's that specified in terms of
multinomial parameters of the form theta x
given u where u is some assignment to X's
parents, U. Then if, for each such
multinomial parameter, we have dirichlet
prior with appropriate hyper parameters.
Then we can show using the kind of
analysis that we just did, combined with
the analysis of the posterior for a single
multinomial. That the posterior is now a
dirichlet, with hyperparameters that
represent the. Prior that we had for that
multinomial, plus the sufficient
statistics that represent the count in the
data of particular combinations of the
parent and the child. And so, for example,
for the entry in the multinomial
representing the value little x1 for X,
and little u for the parents U. We have
this. A prior parameter plus the counts
and the data for that combination of X and
U. So. Now we know how to take a set of
priors and use the data to update them to
form posteriors. Now, let's think about
where the priors might come from. And
a priori it might seem very daunting, to
construct a set of priors for all of the
nodes in a Bayesian network. It turns out
however that there is a general purpose
scheme for doing that, that is both easy
and has some good theoretical properties.
And that scheme works as follows. So what
we're going to do is we're going to define
a prior Bayesian network that has some set
of parameters theta zero. And we're going
to define a single equivalent sample size.
Which is going to be applicable or applied
to all of the nodes in the Bayesian
network. And so, in order to specify the
parameter, the hyperparameter alpha X
given U, for m, for an assignment X equals
little x and U equals little u, we're
simply going to compute the probability in
this parameterized network of X and U, and
we're going to multiply it by the
equivalent sample size alpha. Now in many
cases you're just going to use theta zero
to be the uniform parameters and which
makes it all a very easy computation. But
this provides a simple coherent way to
specify all of the hyper-parameters
simultaneously. And so let's look at an
example. Here is a network X Y that, that
has no edge. And, and let's imagine that,
that is our That is our prior network. And
so we're going to in fact assume a uniform
distribution, over the values, XY, and now
let's. So Theta-0 is uniform. And now
let's look at what we would get for
different situations in a network where we
have x being a parent of y. Which is the
network whose parameters we actually want
to estimate. And so what we would get for,
and let's assume they're both binary, x
and y. And so x is going to be distributed
as a parameter with, Dirichlet with
hyperparameters alpha over two, alpha over
two. And Y is going to be distributed.
Remember, so not [inaudible], not X. Theta
of X is going to be distributed this way.
And theta of Y given XO is going to be
distributed in the following way. It's a
dirichlet, with hyperparameters alpha
times the probability of X, Y. Which in
the uniform distribution is a quarter. And
similarly for theta y given x one is going
to have the same Dirichlet distribution.
And if you think about this, this makes
perfect sense because it tells us that
we've seen the same number of examples of
X. As we have of y. It's just that in y we
have to partition the examples of x, of y
over those where we have x equals x0 and
those we have x equals to x1. If on the
other hand, we had say Dirichlet of alpha
over two, alpha over two for the two
except for the two multinomial?s
corresponding to, to the corresponding to
y. This one and this one. It would rep, it
would, imply that we've seen twice as many
Y's as we've seen X's. So let's see what
kind of affect using the Bayesian
estimation has in a pseudo real world
example. So this is actually a real
network. It was developed for monitoring
patients in an ICU. And we call it the ICU
alarm network. And it turns out that the
ICU alarm network has 37 different
variables. They represent things like
whether the patient was [inaudible]. The
patient's blood pressure, heart rate, and
various other medical, events that might
happen. And it turns out that, overall,
the network has 504 parameters. Now there
aren't actually data cases here. This was
a hand constructed network. And so what
we're going to do is we're going to sample
instances from the network and then we're
going to pretend that we don't know the
network parameters and see the extent to
which we can recover the network
parameters via learning from the instances
that we sampled from it. Now I should say
that this is. A pseudo realistic learning
problem. Because the instances that one
samples from a network, are us, are always
cleaner than the instances that one gets
in the context of a real world data
[inaudible], data set. Because it, in a
real world scenario, it is rarely the case
that the network whose structure you, the
network whose, that you're trying to learn
has the exact same structure as the true
underlying distribution, from which the
data were generated. And so, this is a
much cleaner scenario. But still, it's
useful and indicative. So what we see here
are the results of learning as a function
of the x axis, which is the number of
samples. And the y-axis is a distant
function between the true distribution and
the learned distribution. And that distance
function we're not going to talk about
this at the moment it's the notion called
relative entropy. It's also called kale
divergence. But what we need to know about
this for the purpose of the current
discussion, is that when two distributions
are identical it's zero, and otherwise
it's non-negative. So what we see here is
that the blue line Corresponds to maximum
likelihood estimation. And we can see several
things about the blue line. First of all
it's very jagged. There is a lot of bumps
in it. And second, it's consistently
higher than all of the other lines. Which
means that maximum likelihood estimation,
although it does continue to get lower as
we get more data, with as high as 5,000
data points, we still haven't gotten close
to the true underlying distribution.
Conversely, let's see what happens with
the Bayesian estimation and this is all
Bayesian estimation with a uniform prior.
And different equivalent sample size. So
this is using the prior network with a
uniform network and different values of
alpha. And what we see here is that for
alpha equals five, that's the green line.
Alpha equal ten are almost sitting
directly on top of each other. And they're
both considerably lower than all of the
other lines and also the maximum likelihood
estimation. As we increase the prior
strength so that we are, have a firmer
belief in, in. An uniform prior. We can
see that we move a little bit away. And
now the performance becomes a little
worse. But notice that by around 2000 data
points, we're already pretty close to the
case that we were for an equivalent sample
size of five. For 50, which is this dark
blue line, it takes a little bit longer to
converge, and it doesn't quite make it.
But even with a, an equivalent sample size
of 50, which is pretty high you get
convergence to the correct distribution
much faster than you do from maximum
likelihood estimation. So to summarize,
in Bayesian networks if we're doing
Bayesian parameter estimation, if we're
willing to stipulate the parameters are
independent a priori, then they're
also independent in the posterior which
allows us to maintain the posterior as a
product of posteriors over individual
parameters. For multinomial Bayesian
networks, we can go ahead and con, perform
Bayesian estimation using the exact same
sufficient statistics that we use for
maximum likelihood estimation. Which are the counts
corresponding to a value of the variable
and a value of the parents and whereas in
the context of maximum likelihood estimation you
would simply use the formula on the left,
in the case of Bayesian estimation we're
going to use the formula on the right
which has exactly the same form, only it
also accounts for the hyper parameters.
And, in order to do this kind of process,
we need a choice of prior, and we've
shown how that can be effectively elicited
using both a [inaudible] distributions
specified as a Bayesian network, as well as
an equivalent sample size.