So far we talked about a more of and
[inaudible] of learning clearly in the
context of maximum or clear destination.
Where our goal is to optimize likely
dis-function or the congetional
dis-function. But as for Bayesian network
maximum at your destination is not a
particularly good regiment and its very
susceptible to the over fining of the
parameters to the specifics of the
training data. So what we'd like to do, is
we'd like to utilize some ideas that we
exploited also in the context of Bayesian
networks which are ideas such as parameter
priors to smooth out our estimates of the
parameters at least in initial phases
before we have a lot of data to really
drive us into the right region of the
space. So, in the context of [inaudible]
networks, that was all great, because we
could have a conjugate prior on the
parameters, such as a [inaudible] prior
that we could then integrate with the
likelihood to obtain a closed [inaudible]
conjugate posterior, and it was all very
computationally elegant. But in the
context if MRF's and CRF's, even the
likelihood itself is not computationaly
elegant and can?t be maintained in closed
form. And therefore the posterior, is also
on something that's going to become
computationaly elegant. And so the
question is how do we then incorporate
ideas such as priors into MRF and CRF
learning, so as to get some of the benefit
of regularization. So the idea here in
this context, is to use what's called map
estimation. Where we have a prior, but
instead of maintaining a posterior in
closed form, we're computing what's called
the maximum posteriori estimate. The
parameters. And this in fact is same
notion of [inaudible] that we saw when we
did math inferencing [inaudible] when we
were computing single [inaudible]
assignment, here continuing in the
[inaudible] of [inaudible] learning as a
[inaudible] difference, we're computing
inference estimate of the parameters. So
concretely, how is map inference
implemented in the context of MRF or CRF
learning? A very typical solution is to
define a Gaussian distribution over each
parameter theta I separately. And that is
usually a zero mean. Uni-variant Kelsian.
With some variants. Sigma squared. And the
variants of sigma squared dictate how
firmly we believe that the parameter is
close to zero. So for small variances, we
are very confident that the parameter is
close to zero. And are going to be
unlikely to be swayed by a limited amount
of data. Whereas, sigma gets larger, we're
going to be more inclined to belief,
believe the data earlier on, and move the
parameter away from zero. So, we have such
a parameter prior over each data I
sub-routines are multiplied together to
give a joint parameter prior. So, the
parameter prior over each is going to, of
each parameter is going to look like this.
This sigma squared. Is called a
hyper-perameter. And it's exactly the same
kind of beast as we had for [inaudible]
hyper parameters and the context of
learning [inaudible]. An alternative prior
that's also in common use is what's called
the Laplacian parameter prior. And the
Laplacian parameter prior looks kind of
similar to the Gaussian in that it has an
exponential that increases as the
parameter moves away from zero. But in
this case the increase in the parameter
depends on the absolute value of theta I
and not on theta I squared, which is what,
the behavior that we would have with the
Gaussian. And so this. Function looks, l,
looks as we see over here with a much
sharper peak around zero that effectively
corresponds to a discontinuity at theta I
equals, equals zero. And we have again
such a prior, a Laplacian prior theta I
over each of the parameters of theta I
which are multiplied together. Just like
the Gaussian, this distribution has a
hyper parameter, which in this case is
often called beta. And the hyper
parameter, just like the variance. In the
Gaussian distribution, sigma squared
dictates how tight this distribution is
around zero where tighter distributions
correspond to cases where the model is
going to be less inclined to move away
from zero based on limited amounts of
data. So now, let's consider what map
estimation would look like in the context
of these two distributions. So here, we
have these two parameter priors rewritten,
the [inaudible] and the [inaudible]. And
now, map estimation corresponds to the
[inaudible] over theta of the joint
distribution P of B comma theta. So we're
trying to maximize, [inaudible], we're
trying to find the, theta that maximizes
this joint distribution. And by the simple
rules of probability theory, this joint
distribution is the product of the given
data, which is our likelihood. Multiplied
the prior PSA value. And because of the
linearity of the [inaudible] not
linearity, sorry, lognicity of the
logarithm function. We have the, this is
the same as doing our maps of theta, of
our log likelihood function. Which is just
the log of what we're doing. And the log
of the parameter prior. So, now let's look
at what these logarithms look like in the
context of these two priors. And so this
is, I'm actually drawing the negative log
of T of theta. And the negative log of T
of theta for a Gaussian distribution is
simply a quadratic. And so we have a
quadratic penalty that pushes the
parameters towards zero and this is the
same for those of you who have seen this
in the machine learning class for example,
as doing L1 regularization. Over the
parameter thing I the distribution if we
now do the same for the [inaudible]
distribution, we're going to get. The a
penalty that pushes the parameter towards
zero in a way that depends on the absolute
value of the parameter. And this is
equivalent to L1 regularization, which
again, some of you might have seen in a
machine learning class. So this is a
linear penalty. Now these penalties
although hey both push the parameters
towards zero. Am. Are actually quite
different in terms of the behavior. So if
we look at what L2 does, in, when the
parameter is far away from zero, sort of
towards the edges, the quadratic penalty's
actually quite severe, and it pushes the
parameter down dramatically. But as the
parameter gets small, so closer to the
case of theta I equals zero, the pressure
to move down decreases. So, effectively
you, it's quite legitimate for the model
to have a lot of parameters that are close
to zero but not quite zero. And there
isn't a lot of push at that point to get
the parameters to hit zero exactly. And so
that means that models that use L2
regularization are going to be dense. That
is, a lot of the Theta I's are going to be
non-zero. Conversely when you look at the
one regularization you see that there is a
consistent push towards zero regardless of
where in the parameter space we are. And
so it's in the interest of the model to
continue pushing parameters that don't
impact significantly the log likelihood
component and push them towards zero. And
so, for L1 regularization, we're going to
get models that are sparse. And sparsity
has its own value, because the sparser the
model, the easier it is to do inference in
it, in general. Because sparsity
corresponds to in principle, removing
edges or removing features from the
graphical model, which in turn, can remove
edges and make inference more efficient.
And so, L1 regularization, or the
corresponding Laplacian penalty, is often
used to make the model both more
comprehensible, as well as computationally
more efficient. So to summarize, when
we're doing learning in undirected models.
The parameter coupling that we have in the
likelihood function prevents us from dong
Bayesian estimations efficiency that is
maintaining a posture distribution over
parameters. However we can still use the
parameter in [inaudible] parameter priors
to avoid the over fitting that we would
get with maximum likely destination and
specifically we're going to use map as a
substitute for MLE. The most typical
priors used in this context are L1 and L2,
or Gaussian and McClaussian, and both of
these drive the parameters toward zero,
which has the effect of preventing the
models from going wild and using very.
Drastic parameter values that allow us to
over fit the specific training data that
we've seen. Now, while this behavior is
shared among these two models, there's
also a significant difference between them
in that the L1 or [inaudible] distribution
can be shown both empirically and provably
to induce par solutions, and therefore it
perform for us as forms of feature
selection or equivalently structure
learning in the context of MRF's and
CRF's.