We previously talked about maximum
likelihood estimation for Markov random
fields. Then when we first defined Markov
random fields, we also defined a, an
extension on MRFs called conditional
random fields, or CRFs. So, now let's
think about how the ideas that we
developed in the context of MRFs, can be
utilized for the maximum likelihood
destination of a conditional random field.
So as a reminder, the point of the CRF was
to compute the probability of a particular
set of target variables, Y, given in a set
of observed variables, X. And the. Idea
behind this was that although, the
unnormalize density, P-tilda of x, y was
defined in exactly the same kind of
parameterization whether it's a product of
factors, or as logginer model. As in the
MRF case, the difference here, is that we
have a, an X specific partition function
that guarantees that what we have is a
normalize distribution over the Y
variables given a particular x. So, this
partition function is the sum of over all
y's of the. A normalized measure
[inaudible] theta of x, y. So it
normalizes only over they y's and not the
x's. When learning [inaudible], our data
is now a set of pairs. It's a set of input
variables or observed features x and a set
of target variables y. And in the training
data both these are observed. And we like
to use these to learn conditional
distribution of y given x. So the right
objective function that we're going to
apply in this context, is the, what's
often called the conditional log
likelihood, but really should be called
the log conditional likelihood, because
the conditioning is inside the log. And
what we have in terms of this of this
objective is the sum over all data
instances and of the log of the
conditional probability of Y and X. So if
we look at the conditional [inaudible] we
basically open it up. We end up with a, an
expression that looks very similar to what
we saw in the case of MRF's. We have a sum
over I of. And this is for the case of a
log linear model. We have a sum over I of
the parameter theta I, multiplied by the
value of the feature FI. This is for a
particular instance XY. So it's theta I,
FI of XM, YM. And over here, we have a
negative minus a log of the partition
function for X of M. And this uses the
exact same derivation that we had for the
case of an MRF. And so now we can, sum up
over multiple data instances M, and
compute the derivative relative to a
particular parameter, theta I of the, one
over M of the log conditional likelihood,
or, And then, what we end up with is a,
again, an average of, in this case, the
sum over two expectations. So what we have
in the, we have a summation over M, and
the first term is the value of the feature
function, FI, XM, YM. And the second term
is the expected. Expectation of that
feature phi relative to XM and why? Now
its important to look carefully at this
second expression over here, E theta of
fI, XM, Y, and note that here the XM is
fixed and the expectation is taken only
over the variables Y, and this is in
contrast to the case of MRF when we were
taking the expectation relative to the
entire set of variable. Let's see how this
pans out in the context of a particular
example. So we're going to look a really
brain dead notion, model for image
segmentation, where we just have two
features, F one and F2. The first feature,
F1, is a single tone feature. And it.
Takes the value of, the average green
value for pixels and the super pixels S.
This is my super pixel S. We average out
all of the green super pixels but we only
put them into that feature in cases where
that pixel is labeled with G for graph.
So, and notice that this feature is
repeated across all super pixels S in the
image. So this is a model with shared
parameters. The second feature, F2, is a
pairwise feature. And here we get a one,
four cases where two adjacent super
pixels, S and T, are labeled the same
values. Say, both grass or both cow. And
this allows the model to learn how likely
it is for super pixels that are adjacent
to each other to have the same class
label. Notice that this model too
[inaudible], this feature too is shared
both across pairs of super pixels, but
also across different classes. That is, we
have the same parameter for cow, cow, as
we do for grass, grass, or sky, sky. So
let's plug in these two features into the,
a model for the gradient that we had on
the previous slide. So this is the general
equation, and let's see what happens for
theta one. So the partial derivative,
relative to the parameter, theta one, has
the difference of two expectations. Again,
an empirical expectation and a, And a
model expectation. So, this is for a
particular, instance M. So we're not
currently averaging across multiple
training images. We have a single image,
M, that we're working over. So here,
because the model has shared parameters,
we're selling over all possible super
pixels S in the image. And the empirical
expectation sums up the product of this
indicator function for the super pixel S,
multiplied by the, this average greenness
of the super pixel. And that's the
empirical expectation. The model-based
expectation has exactly the same form.
We're also summing up over all super
pixels S. And we similarly have a product
of two terms, only here, because we don't
know whether, in, because in this model
based expectation, we don't have the Y
labels. We're computing the probability
over the Y label taking the value
[inaudible]. That is, for each super pixel
S, we can compute the probability that YS
takes the value green, given, But we know
about the image, that is, the v, values x
sub m, and that gets multiplied with the
average greenness again. So that's the
gradient for the first parameter. The
gradient for the second parameter is very
similar in spirit. So here, we're looking
at the sum over all pairs of adjacent
super pixels S and T. And the empirical
expectation just sums back over all of
those pairs, with an indicator function of
YS is equal to YT. So we get one if YS is
the same as YT. Say they're both labeled
grass or they're both labeled cow, and
zero otherwise. And in the, in the
model-based expectation term, we have the
probability of that event, that is the
probability that YS is equal to YT given
the image, and once again that sums up
overall pairs of adjacent super-pixels S
and T. So again, a difference of two
expectations in both cases, an empirical
expectation and a model-based expectation.
Taking that and thinking about this, let's
compare the computational cost of two of
two models, of two training [inaudible].
One is the MRF training, and the second is
the CRF training. So in the MRF training,
remember that our gradient relative to a
parameter theta I, was the difference of
two expectations. And we've already
pointed out that the computation of the
second expectation, the model based
expectation, requires that we run
inference at each gradient step. And we
thought that was pretty expensive, or it
could be. But now, let's see what happens
for CRFs. Let's look at that gradient one
more time, for the case of CRFs. And here,
notice that we don't really have, That,
that we have summation over m. That is the
summation over all the data instances of
the difference of two terms. The second is
the feature value in that particular
instance and the second is the expected
feature value in that particular instance,
x of m. So. The important observation to
come out of this, is that this
expectation, this second expectation,
relative to theta, is an expectation that
is different for each of our input
instances. So that means that we need to
rerun this inference for each and every
one of our XM's at each gradient step. So
whereas, MRS requires one inference. At
each radiance step. This requires M in for
instance at each radiance step, where M is
the number of training instances. And so
here the inference required to do learning
is considerably more extensive. However
one needs to weigh the balance all over
the factors that contribute to
computational cost. So when we're doing
inference of the conditional probability P
of Y given X, we only need to worry about
the Y variables, so the Xs are all fixed,
their values are instantiated and so our
factors in the resulting model are factors
only over the variables one. If we were to
once use mrf training because say we
decided that crf training is too expensive
because of the additional cost of
imprints. We would need to compute the
joint probability p of y x which. Might be
much more complicated. And that might be
much more complicated not only because of
the fact that we have more variables now
in the model. Both the Y's and the X's.
But, also because in many cases where we
would like to apply a CRF, the
distribution that we might have over the
X's, becomes quite unmanageable if we want
to actually compute a distribution over
them. So, to understand that, let's go
back to the previous example, and consider
this a very simple image segmentation
model. And, here notice that the X. But
the variable X. And S. Implies this, This
average [inaudible] of the super pixel,
now in the context of [inaudible] we don't
need to compute the distribution over
average [inaudible] because we're
[inaudible] of the X on S and so G of S is
now fix that's instantiating and we're
only competing the probability
distribution over the Y's but if we wanted
to train this model as MRF, we would need
to somehow maintain a distribution over
this average [inaudible] and since that's
a continuous quantity it actually requires
that we think about parametric forms and
[inaudible] or, or mixture of. Celsius and
it becomes quite hairy to manage. And so.
Although, they're, the CRF based training
in this case, might have additional costs,
it can also reduce the cost in terms of
any particular inference. Stop, as well as
avoid a bunch of phony issues regarding
parameterization of the distribution over
the various features. [sound]. So to
summarize, serious learning, in terms of
the mathematical formulation is very
similar to [inaudible] learning. The
likelihood function has the same form.
It's called cave. It's similarly optimized
using gradient [inaudible] usually the
same lbsgs algorithm. However the gradient
computation is now much more expensive
because it requires inference, not only
once per gradient stuff, but also once per
gradient stuff and beta instance. And as a
comparison, once per gradient step in the
context of MRFs. But as we already, as we
just said, the conditional model is often
much simpler. So the inference calls for a
CRF, and the MRF is not the same. So we're
not really comparing apples and oranges.
And so in the context of any given
[inaudible], one really needs to think
about which of these models is more
appropriate. And not only based on the
computational costs of training, but also
in terms of the overall performance and
generalization. [sound]. [sound].