We previously discussed the notion of
maximum likely destination, and showed how
it can be applied in the context of
directed networks, daisy networks. And
everything was really cool. You could do
maximum likely destination in enclosed
form and, and it could all be really
efficient and really elegant. Now we're
going to. Look at the other class of
networks, which is mark up networks and
we're going to see how maximum likely
destination pans out in the context of
mark up networks and specifically when we
use the log linear model representation
because it's a lot easier to think about a
parameter destination in that study. So
let?s look at what a [inaudible]
destination would look like a markup
network. So first let?s go back and remind
ourselves that, we use [inaudible] as an
objection. So what would the [inaudible]
look like? So first of all let?s remind
ourselves that provability of relative to,
for a distribution by a set of factors
over this network. For data instance A.,
B., and C., is going to have the form,
five, one. Of AB times phi two of BC
multiplied by normalizing constant which
is the [inaudible] function. And so if we
now take that and put it through the log,
in order to define the log likelihood and
then summing that out for multiple data
instances, we see that we have the
following expressions. We have a summation
over instances M, of the log off. The Pi
one of a. B for that instance plus log of
pi two of BC for that instance minus log
of Z. And here importantly notice that
I've included the parameters of the model
theta as an argument to the partition
function which now explains why it's a
partition function rather than a partition
constant. It is a function of the
parameters and as we change the parameters
the partition function changes and, and
that's going to turn out to be very
important. So, now let's continue
[inaudible] deriving this expression, and
We can see that just like in the context
of daisy network we can gather like term
and consider for example how many times a
particular entry on a factor five, one of
A, B is used and its used in every
instance where the variable A takes the
value little A and the variable B takes
the value little B. And so we can, again,
accumulate like terms and we end up with a
summation over here, over all possible
value combinations, little a, little b, of
the log of that factor [inaudible],
multiplied by the counts. A baby. And
similarly we have exactly the same form
for the second factor BC, where for every,
for every entry in the factor phi two of
BC, we have a number of occurrences of
that which is simply the counts, of BC in
our data set. And finally we have, this
partition function hanging off the end,
which is accumulated once for every
[inaudible]. So this looks great so far.
Because we have, as in the context of
Bayesian networks, we've decomposed the
likelihood function, or, in this case, the
[inaudible] function, rather, into a bunch
of these terms, each of which involve one
parameter, and a count of how many times
the parameter is used. So, beautiful
decomposition, and maybe we can just go
ahead and optimize each parameter
separately. Except that we have that nasty
partition function hanging off the M. And
if we look at the form of the partition
function, that form is a sum over all
possible values of A, B, and C of the
product, the FI1-AD, FI2-BC. And one
important observation is that when you
stick the summation into a log, the log
doesn't flow through the summation. And
so, you don't get any decomposition of the
parameters nicely into isolated pieces.
And that is the killer, because the
partition function is a term that couples
the parameters and so there's no
decomposition of the likelihood into
separate independent pieces. There's part
if it that decompose but the partition
function, kills that decomposition. And as
a consequence, it turns out that there is
no closed form solution for this
optimization problem. Unlike in the case
of Bayesian networks where we had maximal
likelihood estimation having a closed form
that you could derive directly from the
sufficient statistics which are the data
counts. So to see this in action, here's a
picture of, of a projection of a pro, of
this of this probability distribution. So
here we have written the probability
distribution, distribution of the function
of two. [inaudible] features. These are
the indicator functions of A. One, B. One.
And the indicator functions of b0 c1. And
so, one of them is an entry in the first
potential, in this potential, and the
other one is an entry in this potential.
And obviously you could have other
features than that but I could only rather
two dimensional features space. So, so we
focus on just two parameters. And so that
you see here, for the two axis one axis is
one of these parameters on the second axis
and the second of this parameters. So,
the. Say that these are the coefficient of
the indicator function and what you see
here is the log likelihood. So, this is
the surface of the log likelihood. And
there's several things that can be seen
from looking at the surface. First, it
seems, and we'll show this in a moment,
that there is a single global optimum of
this function that happens right here in
the middle of this contour. But we can
also see the coupling between the
parameters coming up, that it doesn't
decompose nicely as the product of or in
this case a summation of a function over
one of the dimensions. A plus a functional
in the second dimension. So, now let?s
delve into the mass a little bit more and
consider what the log-linear of function
looks like in general cases of a
log-linear model. So, just as a reminder,
here is the definition of a log-linear
model and it's defined as the sum of a set
of coefficients which are a parameters
beta i. Multiplied by a set of features.
Which could be indicator features as we
had in the previous slide but we also
talked about other forms of features for
log linear model in a previous modules.
So, we're not going to go back there. But
any function here would work. We add up
all of the log linear functions and
exponentiate that, and then we have the
partition function that makes sure. That
we have in distribution. So plugging this
into the form of the log likelihood we.
Take this and apply it to every single
data instance, and so we end up with the
following expression which is what we get
after we do this manipulation of
accumulating terms all of which involves a
particular parameter theta i. And so now
for each theta I, we have a summation over
theta instances m of the value of the
feature f I, so this is the feature of i.
Applied. To the [inaudible] and stuff. Now
notice that I've changed arguments on you
in that. Here the future I has a limited
scope; a certain subset of the variables.
For example, the pair AB and here I've
given it the entire assignment as an
argument. This is a shorthand that we use
where we allow the function, FI, to forget
arguments that it doesn't care about. So
if we give the function, say the first
indicator feature all three arguments, A,
B and C it's just going to forget about C
and look at AB alone. And so this is just
a convenient shorthand that allows us to
sort of use a consistent. And simpler
notation without as many indices. So this
is the first term, of the log likelihood,
and just as before we have a second term,
where we accumulate a log partition
function, for every instance in our data
set. And just as a reminder, the log
partition function has the following form;
it is a log, of unfortunately a summation
over an exponentially large space. Of
this, this exponential function. So it has
the form log sum X, which is a term that
you might hear. In various context. But
now we can do an analysis on what the log
partition function looks like. And in
order to do that we're going to State what
the first and second derivatives of this
log partition function are, relative to
our parameters theta i. And let's first
understand what, what we're doing here.
So, this, the partition function, as we
said, is a function of a parameter's
theta. And what we have here is a vector
of first derivates. One relative to every
parameter theta i. And this is a matrix.
Known as the Hessian. Of second
derivatives relative to pairs of
coefficients theta I, theta J. What the
first line says in the theorem is that the
first derivative of the log partition
function is an expectation of the feature
phi relative, so it's an expectation,
that's what the e stands for. Of the
feature FI relative to the distribution P
sub theta. That is relative to the
distribution that we get by parameterizing
a graphical model using the parameters
theta that defines the probability
distribution, and now I can go ahead and
compute the expectation. So, this is equal
to sum over X, P theta of X, FI of X. And
that is an expectation. In the same way
that we treat FI as a random variable over
the space X we can now consider the
covariance of two random variables FI of X
and FJ of X and what this second line
tells me is that the matrix of second
derivatives is really the covariance
matrix of these of these random variables,
that are define by a [inaudible] FI and a
[inaudible] FJ. Well, let's go ahead and
prove the first of these, statements. The
second is more complicated, but really is,
in terms of a lot more lines in the
derivation, that the intuitions aren't
considerably different, and there is no
point going through the details. So, let's
go ahead and plug through the, the
derivative. And so we have a partial
derivative of Z theta relative to theta I.
And, and sorry, this is a partial
derivative of log theta, log theta
relative to theta I, and derivative of a
log, is one over, of a log z, is one over
z times the derivative of the expression
in the middle. And so, that gives us this
expression over here, where we have one
over z times, and we've pushed in the
derivative into the summation, because the
derivative of the summation is the sum of
the derivatives. And so, that gives us
this next line of the expression. We can
now continue and recall that the
derivative of exponential is the
exponential itself times the derivative of
whatever is in the exponent of the
exponential. And so that is going to give
us. Here, the exponential itself, times
the derivative of this summation relative
to theta i. And now it's very simple. We
have the summation over j, j as j, and we
are taking the derivative relative to
particular state I, and that derivative is
either zero. So, the derivative relative
to data I data I, state to j as j is equal
to zero, if I is not equal to j, and is
equal to. Beta. I, sorry is equal to one,
or actually is equal to fj, fi if I is
equal to j. Because the derivative of beta
I itself, is one. And so that gives me fi
is x over here. And now we just rearrange
the expression just a little bit. Moving
the FI to. This sign. And, what we have
here, in this box down at the bottom, is
really just the definition of the log
linear model. It's one over the proficient
function times the exponential of the sum
of the weighted features. And so what we
end up with is a form that looks like sum
over X, [inaudible] of theta of X, times
FI of X. Which is exactly what we wrote
over here. A similar procedure will get us
the formula in the second expression. Just
with a lot more algebraic manipulation. So
now let's, that was the log of the
partition function. Now let's think about
the implications regarding the log
likelihood. So if you remember, the log
likelihood had this term over here which
was linear in the theta I's, and this
additional term which was m times the log
partition function. And, and now let's
think about what are some of the
implications. The log partition function
because it's Hessian. Has this form. It
turns out that, that means that it's a
convex function. What does a convex
function mean? It means that it's bowl
shaped. It's nice bowl. Or, formally,
there is a definition of convexity that
says that if you have a function g of
alpha x plus one minus alpha y, then.
That's greater than or equal to alpha
finds, sorry that's less than equal to,
alpha times [inaudible] plus one minus
alpha [inaudible] y and so that means if
you draw a line from here is. X. Y. G of
X. G of Y. Any point, along this line, is
greater than or equal to the G value of
the point in the middle. So that's the
formal definition of convexity. And
because the, [inaudible] is convex, sorry
because the. Well's partition function is
correct. It's negation, which is what we
have here, is concave. Which means it's an
inverted goal. And this function is
linear. [inaudible]. So, we have a linear
function plus a concave function. So, all
together L of sayna is a concave function.
Which means it has this nice cave shaped
form. What are the implications of that?
It means that there are no local optima to
this function, and therefore it's going to
be easy to optimize using techniques such
as hill climbing, which climb up this
inverted bowl, until they hit an optimum,
which in that case has to be a global
optimum, because the function has no local
optimum. So let's think about how to
actually perform this [inaudible]
destination. So, let's go back to the log
likelihood function. Now we're going to
add this we're going to multiply by one
over m so that we don't have a scaling
issue with a log likelihood continues to
grow with a number of data instances
growth, and so that gives us. This
expression over here, where note that the
M has disappeared as a multiplier from the
log partition function and now we have the
one over M term in the linear component as
well. And now if we go back and plug in
the derivatives of theta I, we take the
derivative of this expression relative to
a particular parameter theta I, we have
two cases. We've already said that the
derivative of the log partition function
relative to a parameter theta I is the
expectation. Of theta I, of FI, which is
the col, which is the feature that theta I
most applies in [inaudible] theta. On the
other hand, if we look here at the
derivative relative to theta I, we can see
that what we have here is also an
expectation. It's an empirical
expectation. It is the expectation or
average. Of fi. In the data distribution.
And so the derivative of the log
likelihood relative to theta I, is a
difference of two expectations. An
empirical expectation and an expectation
in the parametric distribution defined by
my current set of parameters theta. The
one immediate consequence from this is
that a parameter studying theta hat, if
there's a, the maximum likelihood estimate
if and only if we have an equality of
expectations. That is, if the expectation.
Relative to the model. [inaudible] is
equal to the expectation. In the day to
day. And so the expectation in the model.
Has to be equal to the expectation in the
data. And that has to hold for every one
of the features. In my log linear model.
[inaudible]. Now that we've computed the
gradient, let's think about how one might
use it to actually do the optimization. So
it turns out that a very commonly used
approach to do this kind of likelihood
optimization in the context of crs is the
variance of gradient ascent. So here we
have a likelihood surface, which is in as
in this case a fairly nice. Function. And
what we're going to do is we're going to,
use a gradient process where at each point
we compute the gradient we take a certain
step in that direction and continue to
climb up and the gradient that we've
computed on the previous slide is what
we're using. Now it turns out that plain
vanilla gradient ascent is not actually
the most efficient way to go. Typically,
one uses a variant of gradient ascent
called LBFGS, which is a quasi mutant
method. So, very briefly, a mutant method
is something that constructs a second
order approximation to the function, at
each point, as opposed to just a linear
approximation, which looks only at the
gradient. But since we don't want to spend
the computational cost, in general, to
compute a second order, or quadratic
approximation to the function, a quasi
mutant method. That kind of makes an
approximate guess at what the step would
be if we were to compute a second order of
approximation. And we are not going to go
into the details of LDFGS here but there
is plenty of literature on that, that,
that you can find. Now. In either case,
for computing the gradient. In this
context. The critical computational cost
is the fact that we need the expected
feature counts. And the expected feature
counts come up in two places: in the data,
that is when we compute this empirical
expectation E of, E relative to D of the
feature F I; but also in the second term
in this derivative, relative to the
current model. So E relative to the
parameter vector theta in the current
model of the feature F i. Now this second
piece is really the rate limiting step,
because it requires that at each point in
the process we conduct inference on the
model in order to compute the gradient,
and so this is inexpensive competition
because it requires that we run inference
in a graphical model, which we know to be
not an expensive step depending on the
complexity of a graphical model. So to
make this concrete, let's look at an
actual example. Let's return to our
example of the [inaudible] model, where
the energy function of a set of random
variables, X1 up to XN, is a, is the
product of a bunch of pair wise term, is a
sum of a bunch of pair wise terms,
WIJXIXJ. And a, and a bunch of singleton
terms, UI, XI and it's an energy function
so it's negated. And so. Plugging in to
the equation that we had before, the
gradient equation relative to a particular
parameter vector. Theta I, [inaudible]
let's know look at what this looks like
for the two types of parameters that we
have here. The singleton parameter is UI,
and the pair wise parameter is WIJ. So for
the [inaudible] parameters ui, if we just
go ahead and plug into this expression
here, we're going to have where the
empirical expectation simply the average
of the beta xi of m over them all, over
the beta instances m. So, assuming that
each variable xi has its own parameter ui.
We're going to sum up over all data
instances and the value of the variable xi
of m. And that is going to be our
[inaudible] expectations once we average
it overall of the beta instances. Now what
about the, The model expectation,
expectation relative to [inaudible]. Well,
here we have. Two, two cases. I, we need
to consider the probability that XI equals
to one and the probability that XI is
equals to -one and the case where XI equal
to one makes a contribution of +one to the
expectation and the case where XI equal to
-one makes a contribution of -one to the
expectation, so altogether we have p theta
XI equals one, -p theta XI equals -one and
that's because these two have, these two
different coefficient +one and -one. A
slightly more complicated version of this
comes up when we have the peer wise
derivative the derivative relative to the
parameter wij. And here, once again, the
empirical explanation is simply the
average of XI of M, XJ of M, over the data
instances M. And the probability term has
four different probabilities corresponding
to the four cases. Xi and XJ are both one,
both, negative one, or one takes the value
one and the other, negative one, and vice
versa. And the two cases of +one+1, and
-1-1, have a coefficient of one. Because
of the product XI, XJ, is one in those
cases. And the other two have a
coefficient of negative one. And so we end
up with this expression, P sub theta of
XI=1, XJ=1. Plus, P theta of XY=-1XJ=-1.
Minus the probability of the other two
cases. So to summarize. We've seen that
the partition function in undirected
graphical models couples all of the
parameters in our likelihood function. And
that introduces complexities into this
setting that we did not see in the context
of Bayesian network. Specifically, we've
seen that this that there's no close form
solution for optimizing. The likelihood
for this under active graphical models. On
the other hand, we have also seen that the
problem is a convex optimization problem.
Which allows it to be solved using
gradient ascent usually in lbfts
algorithm. And because of the convexity of
the function we're guaranteed that this is
going to give us the global. Optimum,
regardless of the initialization. The bad
news, the further piece of bad news other
than the fact that it has no close form of
optimization is that in order to perform
this gradient computation, we need to
perform probabilistic inference and we
need to do that at each gradient step in
order to compute the expected [inaudible].
And we've already seen that inferences are
a costly thing. And this really
dramatically increases the cost of
parameter estimation in Markov networks
say in comparison to Bayesian networks. On
the other hand the features that we are
computing, the expectation, are always
within clusters. In a cluster graph or in
a clique tree because of the family
preservation property. And, and that
implies that a single calibration step
suffices for all of the feature
expectations it wants, and so a single
calibration, say, of the clique tree is
going to be enough for us to compute all
of the expected feature counts and, and
then we can go from there and compute the