Hello and welcome to the class in
Probabilistic Graphical Models.
Probabilistic Graphical Models are a bit
of a mouthful, so before we define them,
let's first figure out what they might be
used for. So, one example application,
which in fact is the one with
Probabilistic Graphical Models, or PGMs
as they're called, first made its way into
computer science and artificial
intelligence, is that of medical
diagnosis. Consider a doctor who is faced
with a patient. The doctor has a fair
amount of information at her disposal when
she looks at the patient. Predisposing
factors, symptoms, the results of various
tests. And, from that, she's supposed to
figure out what diseases the patient
might have, and what the response to
different treatment might be. A very
different application where PGMs have
also been used is that of image
segmentation. Here, we might have an
image, such as this, that has thousands,
or even hundreds of thousands, of pixels.
And, what we'd like to do is, we'd like to
figure out what each pixel corresponds to.
For example, if we break up the image into
these, fairly larger regions that have
less stuff to reason about, we want to,
figure out which of these corresponds to
grass, sky, cow, or horse. What do these
two problems have in common? First, they
have a very large number of variables,
that we have to reason about. In the context
of the doctor it's all these predisposing
factors, test results, possible diseases
and so on. And in the context of the image
segmentation, it's the labels for different
pixels or these larger regions called
superpixels. The second thing these applications have in
common is that fundamentally there is going to be
significant uncertainty about the right
answer, no matter how clever the
algorithms that we design. So
Probabilistic Graphical Models are a
framework for dealing with this kind of
application. So let's first
understand what each of these words mean
in the context of this framework. So,
first, let's consider the word "models". So,
what is a model? A model is a declarative
representation of our understanding of the
world. So, it is a representation, within
the computer, that captures our
understanding of what these variables are,
and how they interact with each other.
And the fact that it's declarative means
that the representation stands on its own,
which means that we can look into it and
make sense of it, aside from any algorithm
that we might choose to apply on it. So
why is that important? It's important
because that same representation, that
same model, can then be used in the
context of one algorithm that answers
maybe one kind of question, or other
algorithms that might answer different
kinds of questions, or the same question
in more efficient ways, or that make
different trade-offs between accuracy and
computational costs. The other advantage
of having a stand-alone model is that we
can separate out the construction of the
model from the algorithms that are used to
reason over it. So, we can construct
methodologies that elicit these models
from a human expert, or ones that learn it
from historical data using statistical
machine-learning techniques, or a
combination of the two. And once again,
the separation between the algorithm
and the model, and the learning and the
model, allows us to tackle each of these
problems separately. So that was the word
"model". What about "probabilistic"? The word
"probabilistic" is in there because these
models are designed to help us deal with
large amounts of uncertainty. So,
uncertainty comes in many forms and
for many different reasons. So
first it comes because we just have
partial knowledge of the thing below. For
example, the doctor doesn't get to measure
every symptom or every test result, and
she's certainly uncertain about the diseases
that the patient has. Uncertainty comes
because of noisy observation. So, even
when we get to observe certain things,
like blood pressure, those observations
are often subject to significant amounts
of noise. Their uncertainty also comes in
because of modeling limitations. So we're
going to have phenomena that are just not
covered by our model. All sorts of
different, obscure diseases, for example,
that might cause the same set of symptoms.
It's impossible for us to write down the
model that is so detailed that it includes
every possible contingency and every
possible factor. And so you're going to
have uncertainty and variability that is
simply due to modeling limitations. And
finally, some people would argue that the
world is inherently stochastic. Certainly,
if you go down to the quantum level,
that's true. But even at a higher level,
the modeling limitations of complicated
systems are such that, one might as well
view the world as inherently stochastic.
Probability theory is a framework that
allows us to deal with uncertainty in ways
that are principled and that bring to
bear important and valuable tools. So,
first, probabilistic models provide us,
again, this word "declarative". A
declarative representation that is
stand-alone, where you could look at a
probability distribution, and it has clear
semantics, that represent our uncertainty
about different states that the world
might be in. It also provides us, with a,
a toolbox comprising powerful reasoning
patterns that include, for example,
conditioning on new forms of evidence. Or
decision making under uncertainty.
And because of the intricate connection
between probability theory and statistics,
we can bring to bear a range of
powerful learning methodologies from
statistical learning to allow us to learn
these models effectively from historical
data. Avoiding the need for a human to
elicit, to, to specify every single aspect
of the model by hand. Finally the word
"graphical". The word "graphical" is here from
the perspective of computer science,
because Probabilistic Graphical Models are a
synthesis between ideas from probability
theory and statistics and ideas from computer
science. And the idea here is to use techniques
from computer science, specifically
that of graphs. To allow us to represent
systems that are very complicated, that
involve large numbers of variables. And
we've already seen those large number of
variables in both of the applications that
we used as driving examples. Both in
the medical example as well as in the
image segmentation example. And so, in order to
capture probability distributions over
spaces involving such a large number of
factors, we need to have probability
distributions over what are called random
variables. And so the focus of this
class, and what we'll do for most of
it, is to think about the world as
represented by a set of random variables,
X1 up to Xn, each of which captures some
facet of the world. So, one symptom that
may be present or absent. Or a test
result that might have a continuous set of
possible values. Or a pixel that might
have one of several labels. So each of
these is a random variable and our goal is
to capture our uncertainty about the
possible states of the world in terms of
the probability distribution or what's
called a joint distribution over the
possible assignments to the set of random
variables. Now the important thing to
realize when looking at this is that,
even in the simplest case where each of
these is a binary value, which is not
often the case, but say, just for the sake
of argument, if you have n binary-valued
variables, then this is a distribution
over 2 to the n possible states of the
world, one for each possible assignment
of the n variables. And so we have to deal with
objects that are intrinsically
exponentially large. And our only way to do
that is by exploiting data structures that
encode, that use ideas from computer
science in this case, to exploit the
structure in distribution and
represent and manipulate it in an effective
way. So what are graphical models? Let's
look at a couple of very simple examples. So
here's a toy Bayesian network, one that will
accompany us through much of the first
part of this course. A Bayesian network
is one of the two main classes of
probabilistic graphical models, and it
uses a directed graph as the intrinsic
representation here. In this case,
remember we had a set of random variables
X1 up to Xn. The random
variables are represented by nodes in
the graph. So to take a look at this
very simple example which we'll discuss
again later, here we have a situation
where we have a student who takes a course
and gets a grade in the course. And, so
that's one of our random variables. We
have other random variables that are also
related to that. For example, the
intelligence of the students in the
course, the difficulty of the course, and
others that might also be of
interest. For example, the quality of the
recommendation letter that the student
gets in the course, which is dependent on
perhaps the student's grade, and the
score that the student might have received
at the, on the SAT. So, this is a
representation of a probability
distribution, in this case over these five
random variables. And the edges in this
graph represent the probabilistic
connections between those random variables
in a way that is very formal, as we'll
define later on. The other main class of
probabilistic graphical models is what's called a
Markov network, and that uses an
undirected graph. And in this case, we
have an undirected graph over four random
variables A, B, C, and D. And we'll give
an example of this type of network maybe a
little bit later on. So these were toy
examples. Here are some real examples of
the same type of framework. So, this is a
real Bayesian network. It's a network
that's actually called CPCS. It's a real
medical diagnosis network. It was designed
at Stanford University for the purpose of
diagnosis of internal diseases. And it
has 480-some nodes, and a little bit over
900 edges. And it was used for diagnosing
internal diseases by physicians here.
Another real graphical model, in this
case on the Markov network side, is
one that's used for the image segmentation
task that we talked about before. Here, the
random variables represent the labels of
pixels or superpixels. So one per each
superpixel, say. And the edges
represent again probabilistic
relationships between the label of a pixel
and the label of an adjacent pixel,
since these are likely to be related to
each other. So to summarize: the graphical
representation gives us an intuitive and
compact data structure for capturing these
high-dimensional probability distributions. It
provides us at the same time, as we'll see
later in the course, a suite of methods
for efficient reasoning using general
purpose algorithms that exploit the
graphical structure. And because of the
way in which the graph structure encodes
the parametrization of the probability
distribution, we can represent these
high-dimensional probability
distributions efficiently using a very
small number of parameters, which allows
us both feasible elicitation by hand from
an expert, as well as automatically
learning from data. And, in both
cases, a reduction in the number of
parameters is very valuable. This
framework is a very general one and has
been applied to a very broad range of
applications. And I'm not going to list
all of the ones on this slide, and
there is many others that I could have put
on the slide had there been more space.
Let me just very briefly mention a few of
them on subsequent slides. So, we've
already discussed the image segmentation.
So, just to, motivate the benefits of a,
of the PGM framework in this context,
let's look at these two images as an
example. Here is the original images. This
is the division of these images into what
I mentioned were called superpixels,
which are these sort of slightly larger
coherent regions. And this is what you
get if you apply a state-of-the-art
machine-learning framework to individual
superpixels separately. So just trying
to classify each superpixel separately.
And you can see that you get, especially
in the case of the cow, a total mess, with
different superpixels having drastically
different labels. You can't even see the
cow in this segmented image. Whereas, if
you construct a probabilistic graphical
model that captures the global structure of
the scene and the correlations, the probabilistic
relationships between these superpixels,
you end up with a much more coherent
segmentation that captures the structure
of the scene beautifully. We've already
discussed medical diagnosis as an example.
So, here is a real-world application. This
was something that was fielded on the
Microsoft network for helping parents
figure out what was wrong with a sick
child. The site was called
"On Parenting", and, parents could enter the
primary complaint, and then were led
through a series of questions that allowed
the system to provide a probability
distribution over the most likely
diagnosis of what was ailing the child.
A very different application is one of textual
information extraction where we might have
an article from say, a newspaper, and we'd
like to take this unstructured data and
convert it into a structured form where we
have some representation of the people,
and the sentences, locations,
organizations, and perhaps relationships.
So one such task might be to take this
kind of sentence and recognize that these
two words together form a person. Which
might not be that hard, given the presence
of the word "Mrs." But this is a little
bit harder because "Green" is also a word
and yet, we want to identify it as a person.
We might want to, then, infer that
this is a location. And perhaps, that
this is an organization. It turns out
that the state-of-the-art methodology
for solving this problem is as a
probabilistic graphical model, where we
have a variable for each word that encodes
the label for that word. For example, here
we have the beginning of a person unit,
and an intermediate label for the person
unit. And here is another person unit.
Whereas here, in this variable, we
would like to label it as a location, but
we would like to capture importantly the
correlations between both adjacent words
as well as between nonadjacent words. By
using this occurrence of the word "Green" to
infer that this occurrence of the word
"Green" is also a name. A very different
example altogether is one that
integrates data from multiple sensors.
This occurs in many applications. One such
is for integrating data related to traffic
from both sensors that we might have in
the road, or on the top of bridges, or
weather information, incident reports that
we might get in some form, we'd like to
take all this together and use a model
that, as it happens, was learned from
data. And that model is then used to
predict both current and future road
speed, including not only on roads where
we have sensors that measure traffic, but
even more interestingly, on roads where
traffic wasn't measured. And it turns out
that this was a very successful
application that was fielded on, in
several large cities, and with very good
results. From a totally different
application domain, probabilistic
graphical models have been used very
successfully for discovering new knowledge
that we didn't have before. In this case,
the application was biological network
reconstruction, where a biologist
measured protein levels of a diverse set
of proteins in different conditions,
under different perturbations, and from
that, they learned the relationships
between those proteins and discovered
interactions between those proteins
where one was controlling another
including the ones that were not known
before. So, let's conclude this
introduction with an overview of what
we'll learn in the class. So we'll cover
three main pieces related to probabilistic
graphical models.  We'll cover
representations of PGMs including both
directed and undirected representations.
We'll also talk about higher level
structures that allow us to encode more
complicated scenarios including ones that
involve temporal structure as well as
ones that involve repeated or relational
structure, specifically a class of models
called plate models. We'll talk
about inference or reasoning using these
models, covering both exact reasoning where
exact probabilities are the output, as well as
approximate methods that provide a
different tradeoff regarding accuracy in
computation, and we'll also talk about how
this class of models can be used for
decision making under uncertainty. And
finally, we'll talk about how you might
learn these models from historical
statistical data.  We'll talk about learning
both parameters as well as structure of
these models automatically, and dealing
with both the somewhat simpler scenario
where we have complete data, that is, all
the variables are always observed, as well as
the more difficult case where some of the
variables might not be observed all the
time, or perhaps not at all. And that
introduces an interesting set of
complications, but also a wealth of
very exciting applications, as we'll see.