A critical building block in a lot of what
we'll do, both in terms of the finding
probability distributions and in terms of
manipulating them for inference, is the
notion of a factor. So let's define what a
factor is and the kinds of operations that
you can do on factors. So a factor really
is a function or a table. It takes a bunch
of arguments, in this case, a set of
random variables X1 up to Xk. And just like
any function, it gives us a value for
every assignment to those random
variables. So it takes all possible
assignments in the cross-product space of
X1 up to Xk, that is all possible
combinations of assignments, and in this
case it gives me a real value for each
such combination. And the set of
variables X1 up to XK is called the scope
of the factor, that is, it's a set of
arguments that the factor takes.
Let's look at some examples of factors.
We've already seen a joint distribution.
A joint distribution is a factor. For every
combination, for example here of the
variables I, D and G, it gives me a number.
As it happens this number is a
probability, and it happens it sums to one.
But that doesn't matter, what's
important is that for every value of I, D
and G, a combination of values, I get a
number. That's why it's a factor. Here is
a different factor: an unnormalized
measure is a factor also. In this case, we
have a factor such as the probability of
I, D comma g1, and notice that in this case, the
scope of a factor is actually I and D, because
there is no dependence of the factor on
the value of the variable G, because the
variable G in this case is constant. So
this is a factor whose scope is I and D.
Finally: a type of factor that we will use
extensively is what's called a Conditional
Probability Distribution, typically
abbreviated CPD. This, as it happens, is a
CPD that's written as a table, although
that's not necessarily the case, and this
is a CPD that gives us the conditional
probability of the variable G given I
and D. So what does that mean? It means
that for every combination of values to
the variables I and D, we have a
probability distribution over G. So, for
example, if I have an intelligent
student in a difficult class, which is
this last line over here, this tells us
that the probability of getting an A is
0.5, a B, 0.3, and a C is 0.2. And as we
can see, these numbers sum to one, as they
should, because this is a probability
distribution over G for this particular
conditioning context. And you can easily
verify that this is this is true for all
of the other lines in this table. So this
is again a particular type of factor: one
that satisfies certain constraints, in this
case, that each row sums to one. Now
this is--, these are--, the factors that we're
dealing with will not always correspond to
probability. So here is an example of a
general factor that really doesn't
map in any way to probability. Because the
numbers aren't even in the range 0...1. As
we'll see, these kinds of
factors are nonetheless useful. This is a
factor whose scope is the set of variables
A comma B, and it's probably using a real-valued
number for each of those, for each
assignment to A and B. Some operations that
we're going to do on factors: One of
the most common operations is what's
called factor product. It's taking two
factors, say phi1 and phi2, and
multiplying them together. So, let's think
what that means. Here we have a factor phi1.
It has a scope of A, B. phi2 has a
scope of B, C. And what we're doing is, we're
kind of like multiplying a function.
f of x y times g of y z: you're going to get a
function that is of all three arguments
x, y, z. So in this case we have a factor
whose scope is A, B and C. And if we want
to figure out, (oops, that didn't come out
good). If we wanna figure out, for example,
value of the row a1, b1, c1, it's going to
come by taking the a1, b1 row from here,
the b1, c1 row from here, and multiplying
them together. So we're gonna get 0.25. So
this is effectively taking the functions
or the tables, and just multiplying them
together. Another important operation is
factor marginalization. Factor
marginalization is, is oh, is very similar
to, in fact identical to the
marginalization of probability
distributions. So here we have, except
that it doesn't have to be a probability
distribution, so for example, if we have a
factor here who's scope is A, B, and C.
And we want to marginalize out B, to get a
factor whose scope is A, C: what we're going
to be doing is, again, taking both possible
values of B, in this case there's on-
because B is binary there's only two
values, and we add them up, in order to get
the entry for a1, c1: so 0.25 plus 0.08.
And the same all the other rows in
this table are acquired, are computed in
exactly the same way from the
corresponding rows in the original larger
factor. Finally, factor reduction. Again
very similar to the context of probability
distributions. You want to reduce, for
example, to the context c1. So we're
going to only focus on the rows that have
the value C=c1. And that's going to give
us the reduced factor which only has C1.
And once again, the scope of this factor is
A, B, because there is no longer any
dependence on C. So that's basically the
final operation. Now, why factors? It
turns out that factors are the fundamental
building block in defining these
distributions in high-dimensional spaces.
That is, the way in which we're going to
define an exponentially large probability
distribution over n random variables,
is by taking a bunch of little pieces and
putting them together by multiplying
factors, in order to define this
high-dimensional probability distribution.
It turns out, also, that the same set of
basic operations that we use to define the
probability distributions in these
high-dimensional spaces are also what we use
for manipulating them, in order to give us
a set of basic inference algorithms.