One of the most elegant properties of
problems to graphical models is the
intricate connection between the
factorization of distribution as a product
of factors, and the independence
properties that it needs to satisfy. Now
we're going to talk about how that
connection manifests in the context of
directed graphical models or Bayesian
networks. So let's first remind ourselves
about why independence and factorization
are related to each other. So, for
example, the independence definition, that
P of X comma Y is the, is the product of
two factors. P of X and P of Y is the
definition of independence. At the same
time it's a factorization of the joint
distribution of the product of the two
factors. Similarily, one of the
definitions that we gave for conditional
independence, which is the joint
distribution over X, Y, and Z is a factor
over X and Z times a factor over Y and Z
is the definition of conditional
independence. So, once again, independence
and factorization. So we see that
factorization of the distribution
corresponds to independencies that hold in
that distribution and the question is if
we have this, so if we know now that if a
distribution P factorizes over G, the
question is can we know something about
the independencies that the distribution P
must satisfy just by looking at the
structure of the graph G. [sound] [cough]
So what are independencies that need, that
might hold in a probabilistic graphical
model? So we talked about the notion of
flow of influence in a probabilistic
graphical model where we have, for
example, the notion of an active trail
that goes through S, up through I, down
through G, and up through D. If, for
example, we have the G is observed, that
is, in Z. And that gave us an
intuition about which -- when probabilistic
influence might flow. We can now turn this
notion on its head and ask the question
well, what happens when we tell you that
there are no active trails in the graph,
that is, influence can't flow. So we're going
to make that notion formal using the
notion of d-separation. And we're going
to say that X and Y are d-separated in a
graph G, given a set of observations Z, if
there is no an active trail between them. And
the intuition that we'd like to
demonstrate in this context, is that this
notion of influence can't flow,
corresponds much more formally to the
rigorous notion of conditional
independence in the graph. So let's
actually prove that that's in fact the
case so the theorem that we'd like to
state that if P factorizes over the graph - if P factorizes over G -  and we have
a d-separation property that holds on the graph
so X and Y are d-separated in the graph
there's no active trails between them, then
P satisfies the conditional independence
statement: X is independent of Y given Z.
So d-separation implies independence - if
the probability distribution factorizes
over G. So we're now going to prove the
theorem in its full glory. We're going to
prove it by example, because that example
really just ill-, really does illustrate
the main points of the derivation. So, the
assumption, so here is our graph G, and
here is the factorization of the
distribution. So, according to the chain
rule of Bayesian networks. And this is the
factorization that we have seen before.
And so now we'd like to prove that a
d-separation statement follows from this,
from this assumption. And, and the
d-separation statement that we'll like to
prove follows as an independents is one
that says that the D is independent of S.
First [inaudible] D and S are in fact de
separated in this graph and so we see
there's only one possible trail between D
and S in this graph. It goes. Like that
and since G's not observed in this case
and neither is L, we have the, the trail
is not activated and so they, the, the two
are, who knows? Are they separated? And
we'd like to prove if this independence
holds. So what is the prob- the joint
probability distribution of D and S. Well,
it's the sum over this joint distribution
over here. Marginalizing out, the three
variables that are not D and  S. So G, L, and
I. So we have the sum over G, L, and I of
this, big product that's assigned by the
chain rule. And as we've previously seen
when we have a summation like that, one of
the things that we can do is we can push
in summations into the product so long as
we don't push them thru, terms that
involve a variable. So here for example we
have, we might have a summation over L.
And we can push in that summation because
the only term that involves L is
probability of L given G. So if we push in
summations in this way we end up with the
following expression, and we see that we
have this summation over L here a
summation over G and then finally the
summation over I at the very beginning. So
what do we know about the summation over L
of the P of L given G we know that this,
that this is a probability distribution
given over L and therefore. It's
necessarily sums to one because we're
summing up over all the possible values of
zero. Once this term is one, we can look
at the next term, which is this one, and
we can ask ourselves well, one is I'll
cancel that and so probability what is the
one over g, and the probability
[inaudible] which is this one and that two
is one and by the time we're done we end
up with the following expression and the
important thing to notice about this
expression is that this is Phi one of d
and this is Phi two. Woops. Y2 of S and
therefore because we partition this joint
distribution as a product of two factors
we end up with something that corresponds
directly to the definition of marginal
dependence therefore proving that P
satisfies this independent statement. So
having convinced ourselves that D
separation is an interesting notion let's
look at some other D separation statements
that might hold in a graph, so one of the
general statements that we can show, is
that any node in the graph is
d-separated. From its non-descendants
given its parents, so let's look at the
variable letter. And let's see what non
descend [sound] non, non descendants this
has that are not its parents. It only has
two descendants let's mark those in blue
that's this one and that one. And what are
the non-descendants, so these are the
descendants. What about the non
descendants. Well, here's one non
descendant, here's another, another, and
another. So those are the four non
descendants in the graph that are not parents.
Now let's convince ourselves that
Letter is d-separated from all of
its non descendants given its parents, and
lets take just an arbitrary one of those,
let's take SAT, for example, and let's see
if we can find and active trail from
SAT to Letter that is active given
parents, which in this case is just a
variable grade. Way. What are, what's one
potential trail? So we can go on this way.
Up. And then back down through letter but
is that trail active? No, it's not active,
because grade, is observed and so blocks,
it blocks the trail. As in fact, it will
block any trail that comes in from the
top. So, any trail inth the letter that
comes in through it's parent grade, is
going to be blocked by the fact the grade
is observed. So that means we have to come
in through the bottom. So let's look at
that. Let's look at the trail through SAT
through job. And up. Again through Letter.
Well is that [inaudible] active? No. The
reason it's not active is because only
[inaudible] is observed and job since it's
not, it can't be [inaudible] letter
because it's [inaudible], is necessarily
not observed so neither job nor
[inaudible] observed so we, we cannot
activate this [inaudible] over here cannot
be activated. And so, so coming from the
[inaudible] don't work either. And so we,
if again this is approved by
demonstration, but it shows again that,
that. It shows the general property in a
very simple way. So, that tells us, by the
theorem that we proved on the previous
slide, that if p factorizes. Over G, then
we know that any variable is independent.
Of its non-descendants, given its parents.
Which is kind of a nice intuition when you
think about it. Because when we motivated
the structure of bayesian networks, we
basically said that, what makes us pick
the parents for a node is the set of
variables that are the only ones that this
variable depends on. So the parents of X
are the variables on which X depends
directly. And this gives a formal semantic
to that intuition. That is, we now have
that the variable is depending only on its
parents. So now that we've defined a set
of independencies that holds for any
distribution that factorizes over a graph
we're now going to find a general motion
which is just a term for this, So we
define these separation in a graph G and
we show that when you have these
separations property that satisfies the
corresponding independent statement. And
so now we can basically look at the
independent C that are implied by the
graph G. So I N G which is the set of
independencies that are implicit in a
graph key are all of the independence
statements, X is independent of Y given Z
correspond to B separation statements in
the graph so this is the set of all
independencies that are derived from these
separation statements and those are the
ones that the graph implies hold for
distribution P as we just showed in a
previous demo. So now we can give this a
name. We're going to say that P if P
satisfies all of the independencies in G
then G is an imap of P and imap stands for
independency map. And the reason it's in
the [inaudible] is by looking at G it's
the map of in-dependency that holding T
that is it masks in-dependencies that we
know to be true. So it's a good example an
Eye Map so let's look at two, two
distributions here's one distribution, T1.
And here's a second distribution P2. Let's
look at two possible graphs. One is G1
that has V and I being separate variables
and the other is G2 that has an edge
between D and I, so what independencies
does G1 imply, what's an I of G1? Well I
of G1. Is, the independence it says D is
independence of I because there's no edges
between them. With the I of G two. Well I
see two [inaudible] independencies because
there are no, because D and I are
connected by an edge and there's no other
dependencies that can be implied and so
[inaudible]. So what does that tell us?
Let's look at the connection between these
graphs and these two distributions. Is G1
an I-Map of P1? Well if you look at P1 you
can convince yourselves that P1 satisfies
these independence of I. Z1 is an I-map.
Of P1 what about G is [inaudible] an eye
map of P2 well if we look at P2 we can
again convince ourselves by examination
that P2 doesn't satisfy. D is independant
of I so the answer is no this G1 is not an
imap for P2. What about the other
direction? What about G2? Well G2 has no
independence assumptions and so it
satisfies and so both P1 and P2 satisfy
the empty set of the independence
assumptions, as it happens P1 also
satisfies additional independence
assumptions but the definition of I-Map
doesn't require that, that G the graph
exactly represents the independencies in,
in a distribution only that any
independence that's applied by the graph
holds further distribution, and so we
have. The G2 is actually an imap for both
P1 and P2. So, now we can restate the
theorem that we stated before. Before we
talked about these separation properties.
So now we can just give it, one concise
statement. Because if P factorizes over G,
that is, if it's re presentable as a
[inaudible] network over G, then G is an
[inaudible] for P, which means I can read
from G. Independencies that's holding P.
Regardless of the perimeters. Just by
knowing that P factorizes over G.
Interestingly, the converse of this
theorem holds also. So this version of
this theorem says that if G is an
[inaudible] for P, then P [inaudible]
rises over G. So what does that mean? It
means that if the graph, if the
distribution satisfies the independence
assumptions that are implicit in the
graph, then we can take that distribution,
and represent it as a [inaudible] network
over that graph. So once again, let's do
proof by example. So now, here we have the
little graph that we're going to use. And,
and so now, what do we know? We're going
to run down the probability of the joint
distribution over these, these five random
variables, using this expression, which is
the chain rule for probabilities. Not the
chain rule for [inaudible] networks,
because. We don't know yet that this is
representable as a bayesian network. We're
going to write the [inaudible] of
probabilities, and that has us, writing it
as P of V times P of I given D. Which, if
you multiply the two together using the
definition of conditional probability,
these two together give us probability of
I [inaudible]. If you multiply that by g,
given I and V, then we end up with the
probability of g, I, V. And so long as we
can construct this telescoping product,
and, all together, we, by multiplying all
these conditional probabilities, we have a
we have the, we can construct the joint
probability distribution. Great, now what?
So we haven't used any notions of
independence yet, so where do we use that?
Well, we're going to look at each one of
these terms, and we're going to see how we
can simplify it. [inaudible] is already as
simple as it gets. So now let's look at,
the next term, which is the probability of
I given D. And, let's look at this graph,
and we can see that I and D are non
[inaudible]. And we're not conditioning on
any parents. And so we have put in this
graph, as we've already shown this, that
I's independent of d. And so we can using
one of the definitions that we have on the
conditions of the parents, we can erase
this from the right hand side of the
conditioning bar, and just get p f i. The
next term is actually already in the form
that we want it so we don't need to do
anything with it. But now let's look at
the probability of S given D I and G. So
here we have the probability of a variable
S given one of it's parent I and two non
descendants D and G and we know that S is
independent of it's non descendant given a
non descendant given it's parent I and so
we can erase both D and G and just, end up
with probability of S given I. Finally, we
have the last term probability of L given
D, I, G, and S and here again we have the
probabilty of a variable L given its
parent G and a bunch of non-descendants.
So we can again erase the non-descendants.
And so, altogether, that gives us exactly
the expression that we wanted. And so now,
again, by example, we prove this, we prove
this independent. We prove that some of
these independent statements, we can,
derive the fact that p factorizes using
the product rule for [inaudible] that
works. To summarize, we've provided two
equivalent views of the graph structure.
The first is the graph as the
factorization as a data structure, that
tells us how the distribution p can be
broken up into pieces. So in this case,
the fact that g allows p to be represented
as a set of factors or c p ds over the
network. The second is in imat view, the
fact that the definition, the, the, the,
the structure of g encoded in the
[inaudible] doesn't necessarily hold in p.
And what we've shown is that each of these
actually implies the other. Which means
if, that if we have a distribution P that
we know is represented as a bayesian
network over a certain graph, we can just
look at the graph without even delving
into the parameters. No certain
independencies that have to hold in the
distribution key. And independencies is a
really valuable thing, because it'll, it
tells you something about what influences
what. And if I observe something, what
else might change? And that helps a lot in
understanding the structure of the
distribution, and consequences of
different types of observations.