So far, we've designed graphical models
primarily as a data structure for encoding
probability distribution. So, we talked
about how you can take a probability
distribution and, using a set of parameters
that are somehow tied to the graph's structure
one can go ahead and represent
a probability distribution over a high
dimensional space in a factored form. It
turns out that one can view the graph
structure in a graphical model using a
completely complementary viewpoint, which
is as a representation of the set of
independencies that the probability
distribution must satisfy.
That view turns out to be really
enlightening and thought provoking and so
let's talk about that, and we're going to
begin by just defining the notion of independencies that we're going to utilize
in subsequent presentations. So let's start
by just defining the very basic notion of
independence within a probability
distribution. And initially we're just
going to talk about the probability in the
sorry the independence of events
alpha and beta within a probability
distribution. And let me just go ahead and
introduce this notation, this says P, this
symbol is the logical symbol for
"satisfies". And this perpendicular symbol
is a standard notation for independence.
So this says: "P satisfies 'alpha is
independent of beta.'" That's how one should
read that statement. And there's actually
three entirely equivalent
definitions of the concept of
independence. The first one says that the
probability of the conjunction of the two
events -- there's several
different ways to denote
conjunction, some people denote it as
intersection, we typically denote it using
a comma. So here is: the probability of
alpha and beta holding both is simply the
probability of alpha times the probability
of beta, that's the first definition. The
second definition is a definition about
flow of influence. And this says: If you tell
me beta, it doesn't effect my probability
in alpha. So the probability of alpha
given the information about beta is the
same as the probability of alpha if you
don't give me that information. And
because probabilistic influence is
symmetrical, we also have the exact
converse of that. That is, the probability
of beta given alpha is the same of the
probability of beta. This is
independence of events. You can take that
exact same definition and generalize it to independence
of random variables. Here we are going to
read this the same way. This says:
"P satisfies 'X is independent of Y'" for two
random variables X and Y. Once again we
have the exact same set of definitions. So
the first one says that P of X comma Y is equal
to P of X times P of Y. The second says P of
X given Y is equal to P of X and P of Y
given X is equal to P of Y. You can make
these three statements in two different
but equivalent forms: The first is
a universal statement. So for example you
could read the first statement as saying:
For every assignment x and y
to the variables X and Y we have the P of
the event X comma Y is equal to P of X
times P of Y. So you can think of it as a
conjunction of lots and lots of
independent statements of the form over
here. That's the first interpretation. The
second interpretation is as an expression
over factors. That is, this one tells me
that the factor over here, which is the
joint distribution over X and Y, is
actually a product of two
lower-dimensional factors, one of which is a factor
whose scope is X and one is a factor
whose scope is Y. These are all equivalent
definitions, but each of them has a
slightly different intuition, so it's useful to
recognize all of them. So let's look at an
example of independence. Here is a
fragment of our students network. It has
three random variables: intelligence,
difficulty and course grade. And this is a
probability distribution that
has a scope over three variables, and we can
go ahead and marginalize that to get a
probability distribution over the scope,
which is a factor over the scope ID. As it
happens, this is a marginal distribution
which you can confirm for yourselves by
just adding up the appropriate entries so,
just as a reminder, to get i zero and d zero,
we're going to add up this one, this one and that one.
And that's going to give us this factor.
And it's not difficult to test that if we then
go ahead and marginalize P of I comma D to
get P of I and P of D that P of I comma D
is the product of these two factors. Here
is an example of a distribution that
satisifies an independence property. And
here's the graphical model, and when you
look at it, you can see that there's no
direct connections between I and D, and
we'll talk later about how that tells us
that there is no -- that the two are actually
independent in this distribution. Now,
independence by itself is not a
particularly powerful notion, because it
happens only very rarely. That is, only in
very few cases are you going to have
random variables that are truly
independent of each other. At least
few interesting cases, you can always
construct examples. So now we're going to
define a much broader notion of much
greater usefulness, which is the notion of
conditional independence. Conditional
independence, which applies equally well
to random variables or to a set of random
variable that is written like this. So
here we have once again that P
satisfies -- here we have again the
independent sign, and here we have a
conditioning sign. And this is read as:
"P satisfies 'X is independent of Y given Z'".
And once again we have three
identical -- not identical, sorry, three
equivalent definitions of this, of this
property. The first says that "probability
of X comma Y given Z is equal to the products
of P of X given Z, times the probability
of Y given Z". Once again, you can view
this as a universally quantified statement
over all possible values of X, Y, and Z;
or as a product of factors. Definition
number two is a definition of information
flow: "Given Z, Y gives me no additional
information that changes my probability
of X" or "Given Z, X gives me no additional
information that changes my probability in
Y". Once again you can
view this as an expression involving
factors. Notice that this is very
analogous to the definitions that we
have for just plain old independence. Z
effectively never moves, it always sits
there on the right hand side of the
conditioning bar and never moves, and so
if you find yourself having a hard time
remembering conditional independence, just
remember that the thing you're
conditioning on, just sits there on the
right hand side of the conditioning bar
all the time. Let me introduce one final
definition, which is going to serve us
quite well in an interesting
derivation. It's very similar to the first
definition, but it says that the
probability of X comma Y comma Z -- the joined
distribution -- is proportional, to... So
we're going to forget the potential need
to add normalizing constants. It's
proportional to a product of two factors.
Oops. One factor over X and Z and one
factor over Y and Z. This turns out
to be yet again another definition of
conditional independence. Let's look at an
example of conditional independence. Imagine
that you have, that I give you two coins,
and I'm telling you that one of those
coins is fair, and the other one is biased,
since it's going to come up heads 90
percent of the time, but they look the
same. So now you have a process by which
you first pick a coin out of my hand, and
then you toss it twice. So this is which
coin you pick. And this is the two tosses.
Now let's think about dependence and
independence in this example. If I don't--
if you don't know which coin you picked,
and you toss the coin, and it comes out
heads: what happens to the probability of
heads in the second toss? It'll be higher, right?
Because, if it came up heads the first time,
that is more likely to happen. I mean, it
happens 50/50 with a fair coin,
but it happens with greater
probability with a biased coin, and so the
probability of having heads in the second
toss is going to be higher now. On the
other hand, if I now tell you, "No, no,
you've picked the fair coin",
you don't really care what the
outcome of the first toss is. It doesn't
tell you anything about the probability of
the second toss. Similarly, if I tell you
that it's the biased coin, it also
doesn't tell you anything at that point.
The first toss and the second toss are no
longer correlated. And so what we have is
that X1 and X2 are not independent, so P
does not satisfy "X1 is independent of X2",
but we have that P does satisfy "X1 is
independent of X2 given C". So here's a
very simple and intuitive example of
conditional independence. Let's go back to
another example of conditional
independence. One in the distribution that
we've seen before. This is actually a very
analagous model. Because it also has, in
this case, one common cause, which, in
this case, is the student's intelligence.
This is in the students example that
we've seen before. We had two things that
emanate from that. The student's grade in
the course, and their SAT scores. And
once again, it's, you can generate the
joint distribution of I, S, G which is this,
and now you can look at the probability of
S and G given for example, i zero, and ask
yourselves: "How does that
decompose, and is that independent given--
when we look at the probability of S given
i zero and the probability of G given
i zero?" And convince yourselves that in
this case conditional independence applies.
Now one somewhat counterintuitive
property of independence that you kind of
don't think about when you hear about
conditional independencies the first time,
is that conditioning on something doesn't
just gain you independency as it did in
the case of the coin or the case of the
intelligence. But rather conditioning can
also lose independency. So this is the
other fragment of our students network,
where we had the intelligence and the
difficulty both influencing the grade. And
we have already seen that although I and D
are independent in the original
distribution, they're not independent when
we condition on grade. So this is a
case where you can just convince
yourselves of this by examining this
distribution over here that I and D are
not independent in this conditional
distribution, even though they were in the
marginal distribution.