So now we're getting into Bayesian
land. And we're finally going to start
talking about the actual representations
that are going to be the bread and butter
of what we're going to describe in this
class. And so, we're going to start by
defining the basic semantics of a Bayesian
network, and how it's constructed
from a set of factors. So let's
start by looking at a running example
that will see us throughout a large part
of, at least, the first part of this course
and this is what we call the student
example. So in the student example we have
a student who's taking the class for a
grade and we're going to use the first
letter of, of the word to denote the name
of the random variable, just like we did in
previous examples. So here, the random
variable is going to be G. Now the grade
of the student obviously depends on how
difficult the course that he or she is
taking and the intelligence of the
student. So that gives us, in addition to
G. We also have D and I, and we're going
to add just a couple of extra random
variables just to make things a little bit
more interesting. So we're going to assume
that the student has taken the SAT. So he
may, may or may not have scored well on
the SAT's. So that's another random
variable S. And then finally we have this
case of the disappearing line. We also
have the recommendation letter L that the
student gets from the instructor of the
class. Okay? And we're going to grossly
oversimplify this problem by, basically,
binarizing everything except for grades.
So, everything has only two values except
for grades that has three. And then,
only so that I can write things
compactly. This is not a limitation of the
framework, it's just so the
probability distribution won't become
unmanageable. Okay, so now let's think
about how we can construct the
dependencies of this in this
probability distribution. Okay, so let's
start with the random variable grade. I am
gonna put it in the middle and ask ourselves
what the grade of the student depends on
and it seems just, you know, from a completely
intuitive perspective it seems
clear that the grade of the student
depends on the difficulty of the course and on the intelligence of the students.
So, we already have a little baby Bayesian
network with three random variables, let's
now take the other random variables and
introduce them into the mix, so for example
the SAT score of the student doesn't seem
to depend on the difficulty of the course
or on the grade the student gets in the
course, the only thing it's likely to
depend on, in the context of this model, is
the intelligence of the student. And
finally, caricaturing the way in which
instructors write recommendation letters,
we're going to assume that the quality of
a letter depends only on the student's
grades. The professor's teaching, you
know, 600 students or maybe 100,000 online
students. And so, the only thing that one
can say about the student is by looking
as their actual grade record. And so, regardless of anything else, the quality of the letter depends only on the grade.
So, this a model for the dependencies. It's only one model that one
can construct for these dependencies. So,
for example, I could easily imagine other
models. For instance, ones that have the
students who are brighter taking harder
courses. In which case, there might be
potentially an edge between I and D but
we're not going to use that model (so let's
erase that), because we are going to stick
with the simpler model for the time being.
But this is only to highlight the fact
that a model is not set in stone. It's a
representation of how we believe the world
works. So here is a model drawn out a
little bit more nicely than in the
picture before. And now, lets think about
what we need to do in order to turn this
into our representation of probability
distribution, because right now all it is,
is a bunch of you know, of nodes stuck
together with edges, so how do we actually
get this to represent the probability
distribution? And the way in which we're
going to do that, is we're going to
annotate each of the nodes in the network
with what's called, with CPDs. So we
previously defined CPDs. CPDs - just as a
reminder - is a Conditional Probability
Distribution, I'm using the abreviation
here. And each of these is a CPD, so we
have five nodes, we have five CPDs. Now if
you look at some of these CPDs, they're
kind of degenerate. So, for example, the
difficulty CPD isn't actually conditioned
on anything. It's just an unconditional
probability distribution that tell us, for
example, that courses are only 40% likely
to be difficult and 60 % likely to be
easy. Here is a similar unconditional
probability distribution for intelligence.
Now this gets more interesting when you
look at the actual conditional probability
distributions. So here, for example, is a
CPD that we've seen before. This is the
CPD of the grades A, B, and C. So, here is
the conditional probability
distribution that we've already seen
before for the probability of grade given
intelligence and difficulty. And we've
already discussed how each of these rows
necessarily sums to one because of the
probability distribution over the variable
grade. And we have two other CPDs here in
this case the probability of SAT scores given
intelligence and the probability of a recommendation
letter given a grade. So, just to write
this out completely, we have P(D) . P(I)
I, P(G given I,D), P (L given G) and P (S given I)
And that now, is a
fully parameterized Bayesian network and
what we'll show next is how this
Bayesian network produces a
joint-probability distribution over these
five variables. So here are my CPD's and
what we are going to define now is the
chain rule for Bayesian networks, and
that chain rule basically takes these
CPDS, all these little CPDS, and basically
multiplies them together, like that. Now,
before we think of what that means, let us
first note that this is actually a factor
product in exactly the same way that we
just defined. So here, we have five
factors, they have overlapping scopes. And
what we end up with is a factor product
that gives us a big, big factor,
whose scope is five variables. What
does that translate into when we apply the
chain rule for Bayesian network in the
context of this particular example? So, let's
look us at this particular assignment and, remember,
there's going to be a bunch of these
different assignments, and I'm just going
to compute this other probability of this
one. So the probability of d0, i1, g3, s1
and l1. Well, so the first thing you need
is the probability of d0, and the
probability of d0 is 0.6. The next thing,
from the next factor, is the probability of
i1, which is 0.3. What about the next one?
The next now is a conditional factor
and for that, we need the probability of g3,
because we have g3 here. So we want from
this column over here, and which row do we
want? We want to pick the row
that corresponds to d0 and i1, which is this
row, so 0.02. Continuing on, we know now
that wenow have g3. So we want from
this row. And we want the probability of
l1, so we want this entry. 0.01... And
finally, here we have probability of s1
given, given i1. So, that would be this one
over here, 0.8. And in this exact
same fashion, we're going to end up
defining all of the entries in this joint
probability distribution. Great, so, what
does that give us as a definition? A Bayesian network is a directed, acyclic graph.
Acyclic means it has no cycles, that is you can't traverse the edges and
get back to where you started. This is
typically abbreviated as a DAG, and we're
going to use the letter G to denote directed acyclic graphs. And the
nodes of this directed acyclic graph
represent the random variables that we're
interested in reasoning about, X1 up to
Xn. And for each node in the graph,
Xi, we have a CPD that denotes the
dependence of Xi on its parent in the
graph G. Okay? So, this is a set of
variables. So, this would be like the
probability of G -grade- given I -intelligence- and D -difficulty-. So, this
would be G, the Xi would be G and the
parents of G, ofXi, would be I and D. And
the BN, the Bayesian network, represents a
joint probability distribution, via the
chain rule for Bayesian networks, which is
the rule that's written over here and this
is just a generalization of the rule that
we wrote on the previous slide, where we
multiplied one CPD for each variable, here
we have again, we're
multiplying over all the variables I and
multiplying the CPD for each of the Xis
and this is once again, a factor product.
So, that's great and I just defined the
joint probability distribution. Now, whose
to say that, that joint probability
distribution is even a joint probability distribution?
So, what you have to show in
order to demonstrate that something's a
joint probability distribution? The first
thing you have to show is that it is
greater or equal to zero, because
probability distributions are always non-negative.
As so, in order to do that,
we need to show that, for this distribution P
and the way in, and this, as it happens,
is quite trivial, because P is a product of factors
Actually, the products of CPDs
and CPDs are non-negative, and if you
multiply a bunch of non-negative factors,
you get a non-negative factor.
That's fairly straightforward. Next one's
a little bit trickier. The other thing we
have to show or to demonstrate so that,
something's a legal distribution, is to
prove that it sums to one. So how
do we prove that something's sums
to one, that this probability distribution
sums up to one? So, lets, actually
work through this, and one of the reasons
for working through this is not just to
convince you that I'm not lying to you.
But more importantly, the techniques that
we're going to use for this simple
argument are going to accompany us
throughout much of the first part of the
course. And so, it's worth going through
this in a little bit of detail, but I'm
going to show that in the context of the
example of the distribution that we just
showed, we just end up cluttered with
notation, but the, but the idea is still
exactly the same. So, to sum up, over
all possible assigments, D, I, G, S, L of
this, hopefully,
probability distribution that I just
defined. The P of D, I, G, S, and L, okay? So
we're gonna break this up using the chain
rule for Bayesian networks.
Because that's how we define this distribution P.
Okay, now here is the magic trick that we
use whenever we deal with distributions
like that. It's to notice that when we
have the summation over several random
variables here, and here, inside the
summation we have a bunch of functions
inside here. Only some of the...
... each factor only involves a small
subset of the variables. And, when you
do, when you have a situation like that,
you can push in the summations. So,
specifically, we're going to start out by
pushing in the summation over L. And,
which factors involve L? Only the last
one, so we can move in the summation over
L to this position, ending up with the
following expression, so notice there's now
the summation over here, that's the first
trick.
A second trick is using definition of CPDs and we observe here
that the summation over L is summing up
over all possible mutually exclusive and
exhaustive values of the variable L in
its conditional probability distribution
P of L given G, and that means, basically,
we're summing up over a row of the CPD, and
that means that the sum has to be one. And
so this term effectively cancels out,
which gives us this. And now, we do exactly
the same thing. We can take S, and move it
over here, and that gives us that. And
this too, is a sum over a row of a CPD.
So, this too, is canceled and can be written
as 1. And we can do the same with G, and
again. This has to be equal to one so we
can cancel this and so on, and so forth,
and so, by the end of this, you're going to
have have canceled all of
the variables in this summation, and what
remains is 1. Now, this is a very simple
proof, but these tools of pushing
information and removing variables that
are not relevant are going to turn out to
be very important. Okay, so now thi is just
the final little bit of terminology that
will again accompany us later on, we are
going to say that the distribution P
factorizes over G means that we can represent
it over the graph G, if we can and call it
using the chain rule for Bayesian
networks. So, a distribution factorizes
over a graph G, if I can represent
it in this way, as a product of these
conditional probabilities. Well, let me
just conclude this with a little
example, which is, arguably, the very
first example of a Bayesian network ever.
It was an example of Bayesian networks
before anybody even called them Bayesian
networks. And it was defined, actually, by
statistical geneticists who were trying to
mull the notion of genetic inheritance
in a population. And so, here is an
example of genetic inheritance of blood
type. So, let me just give a little bit of a
background on the genetics of this. So, in
this very simple, oversimplified example,
a person's genotype is defined by two
values, because we have two copies
of each of those
chromosomes in this case. And so,
for each chromosome, we have three possible
values, so we have, either the A value,
the B value, or the O value. These are
familiar to many of you from blood types,
which is what we're modeling here. And so
the total number of genotypes that we have
is listed over here. We have the AA
genotype. AB, AO, BO, BB, and OO. So, we have
a total of six distinct genotypes.
However, we have fewer phenotypes, because
it turns out that AA and AO manifest
exactly the same way as a blood type A.
And BO and BB manifests as blood type B,
and so we have only four phenotypes. So,
how do we model genetic inheritance in a
Bayesian network? Here is a little
Bayesian network for genetic inheritance.
We can see that for each individual, say
Marge, we have a genotype variable which
takes on six values, and one of the six
values, which we saw before, and the
phenotype, in this case, the blood type,
depends only on the person's genotype. We
also see that a person's genotype depends
on the genotype of her parents. Because,
after all, she inherits one chromosome
from her mother, and one chromosome from
her father. And so, a person's
individual genotype just depends on those
two variables. And so, this is very nice
and very compelling Bayesian network,
because everything just fits in
beautifully in terms of, things really do
depend  only on the variables
that we stipulate, and the models
they depend on.