One very common kind of repeated structure
occurs when we have multiple objects of
the same type. So. That, where we want to
have all these different copies of the
objects. It's not copies of the objects,
but objects of the same type all have a
similar, or in fact, the same probablistic
model. For reasons that we'll talk about
momentarily, the most, one of the most
common type of, such models is called the
plate model. Let's start by modeling
repetition so in this case imagine that
we're repeatedly tossing the same coin
again and again so we have an outcome
variable. And what we'd like to model is
the repetition of multiple tosses and so
we're going to put a little box around
that outcome variable and this box which
is called a plate. Is a way of denoting
that the outcome variable is indexed,
which we usually don't denote explicitly
by the notion, by different tosses of the
coin T. And the reason for calling it a
plate is because the intuition is that
this is a stack of identical plates.
That's kind of where the idea comes from
for a plate model. And looking at what
that model denotes is, if we have a set of
coins, the coin tosses T1 up to Tk. It
basically says that we have a set of
random variables, outcome of t1 up to
outcome of tk. So we've just reproduced to
the outcome variable in its mulitple
copies. Now what does that explicitly
correspond to? I'm now going to do
something that we're gonna do a lot of
times later on in the course when we talk
about learning, which is I'm going to put
the parameters off the CPD explicitly into
the model. So this random variable theta
is the actual CPD parameterization and I'm
puting it explicilty so that I can show
how different variables depend on that.
And so if we have this, the parameters
here we can see that theta is outside of
the plate. Which means that it's not
indexed, by t. Which means it's the
same for all values of t. So what that
means is that we have this cop-, this
parameters theta over here. And we have all
of these outcomes depend on the exact same
parameterization. And the CPD of the
outcome of T1 is copied from this parameterization theta. Let's look at a slightly more
interesting example. Going back to our
university with multiple students, we now
have a two variable model, where we have
intelligence and grade. And we now index
that by different students s. Which again
indicates that we have a repetition, a
copying of this template model. In this
case, I only made two copies for, one for
student one, and the other one for student
two. And, once again, if we wanted to
encode dependence on the parameters. So we
might have theta I, which represents the
CPD for I. So we might have theta G, which
represents the CPD for G. And we would
have exactly the same idea of thetai and
theta G, where theta I influences the two
I variables and thetas influences the two s
variables. And, again, they're out of the
plate. Sometimes
in many models we will include those
parameters explicitly within the model,
but often when you have a parameter that's
outside of all plates, we won't denote it
explicitly. So we just omit it as we did
in this original diagram before I
annotated it. Now, just repeating the
exact same model multiple times is not
particularly interesting. So now let's
talk about how you can overlap different
plates or in, in, in different words,
think about how different types of objects
in the model overlap with each other. So
in this case we have two kinds of objects
that are universe of discourse
We have courses, and we have
students. And courses we're gonna call
little c and students we're gonna call
little s. And so now, let's think about
how you might replicate variables that
correspond to properties of courses and
variables that correspond to properties of
students. So the difficulty variable,
belongs in the course plate, because it's
a property of a course. So it's going to
be the difficulty of the course. And now
let's think about how we're going to put
students in. One possibility is we're
going to nest. The students plate inside
the course plate. Now, what that means is
that the student of each variable here,
both of these variables are indexed by
both s and c, because when a variable is
nested in a plate, it means that it has
the indicies of all plates that it's
nested in. So, if, if the in, intelligence
variable is both, is in both the S plate
and the C plate, it's going to be indexed
by both. So let's build that model, and
see what it looks like when we, sort of,
unravel the courses and unravel the
students. It's gonna look like that. So
we're going to have the difficulty of,
let's say this is a two course model, and
a two student model. So we have a
difficulty of course one and a difficulty
of course two. And now we have the
variables in the nested plate, I and
G, and we can see that they're both
parameterized by both student and course.
Let's think about the implications of this
model. The implications are that the
intelligence is now a property of both
the student's intelligence of student in course. And that, the intelligence of the
student in a particular course, influences
the grade of the student in that course.
And you can see that by having
this dependency model, over here. Now what
in fact, let's think about the
implications of this. This tells us that
there is a core specific intelligence for
every student. For every student in every
course and they may or may not be what we
want. If you're taking radically different
courses and one is an art class and one is
a math class and you can say that there's
and art intelligence, their representing
skill if you will in art and you have a
math skill that represents math
intelligence then you might want to have
two different kinds of intelligence and
not necessarily assume that they're the
same thing. Of course that kind of
complicates the model, and if you have a
bunch of courses that are, in some ways
similar to each other, and take a similar
set of skills, you might not want to have
a bunch of independent – look –
independent random variables. Sorry.
This is, these ones. We're assuming that
the student has two independent
intelligences representing their, the
intelligence in the two different courses.
And in that case, you don't want the
intelligence variable to be part of the
course plate. And so that gives us
an alternative representation, which is
what's called, plates that are not the
same, but that overlap. That are not
nested that overlap with each other.
So, in this case, we have the course
plate, which is this plate over here and
we have the student plate. Which is this
one over here, and the assumption is, that
this difficulty is the property
only of the course. So, this is the
difficulty. The intelligence is the
property of the student and only the grade
is the property, that depends on both. And when we unravel this one, what
we end up with is a model that looks like this. So
we have, in this case, the, we only have a
single, we have a difficulty for the
course. We have an intelligence for the
student. And over here, let's denote
things in the intersection in green. We
have the grade of the student in the
course depends on the difficulty of the
course, and on the intelligence of the
student. And so now we only have a single
intelligence per student. And that is an alternative
modeling. It's not that one of these is
right and the other is wrong. They're just
different. And once again, just to
demonstrate a explicit parameter sharing,
I just wanted to highlight again that the notion of parameter also applies to models
such as this. So here we have a parameter
thetaD. We have a parameter, thetaI
and we have a parameter,
thetaG and which influences
the grade and that's shared
among all the all of the different grade
variables. So why are these kinds
of plate models useful? So let's look at
an example to convince ourselves that by
building these richly structured models
that involve multiple entities, you can
actually get much more interesting
conclusions. So let's look at this example
over here. Imagine that we have this,
first quarter freshman came into our
university. And we'd like to figure out,
what we can determine about him. So let's
say that, in this particular university,
a priori we believe that most students
have high intelligence, and so this is the
intelligence distribution. And 80 percent
are high. Now this student that we're
going to call George took two classes. He
took Geology 101 and got an A. So,
the probability that he is intelligent goes up. He took
CS101, didn't do so well, got a C. Well,
the probability goes down, but it doesn't
go down to a very lower number, and that's
because we know from the CPD for grade
that we've seen previously, that we have,
you know, there may be other, may be
multiple reasons why a student might not
do well in a class. For example, maybe it
was a really hard class. And so maybe
everybody did badly. And some of you
shouldn't take this too seriously. If
these are the only two courses that George
took, we're kinda stuck. But now lets
think about this in a more holistic
context, or collective inference where
we're going to think about, a number of
students taking a number of classes and
let's imagine that we have a bunch of
grades for all of those students. So what
we see here are the green ones are A's...
The, yellow ones are Bs, and the red ones
are Cs. And what you see here is shorthand
for a bunch of observed grade variables.
So I didn't put in all the little dots
that represent, all the little ovals that
represent the grade variables. I just put
in this lines to indicate what they are.
So you can think of this as a, as the
induced Markov network, if you will. Okay.
So now, so now, let's think about what
kind of conclusions we can reach from this
network. And what seems, even by looking.
Even looking at this by eye, we can see
that a bunch of people took CS101, and
they all aced it except for our friend
George. And furthermore, even if you look
at this guy over here who got a C in every
other class that he took, he still managed
to ace CS101. So if we do the probablistic
inference over this holistic model, what
we're going to get is that we are pretty
sure that CS101 is an easy class and if
we're pretty sure about that, we are also
pretty sure in this case where the
intelligence is low. And so we can reach
much more form conclusion in this setting,
than we can by reasoning about
individuals and isolation. Now this is a
toy example. But we'll see later on
examples of collective inference that
where we have multiple interrelated
entities, it could be related pixels in an
image, it can be related web pages in
a website that web pages
point to each other. That if we try and
label each entity in isolation we just
don't get a very informed conclusion, but by
thinking about how they all relate to each
other we get much stronger results, that
are much more informed. So, just to
summarize the plate dependency model. The
plate dependency model has the following
characteristics. It defines a dependency
model for a template variable that is
indexed by a bunch of object, types. So for
example students and courses, or, or
anything else. And we have for each of
those template variables we have a set of
template parents. And what we have
[inaudible] is that each of these has to
be a subset off this. So what does that
mean? It means for example, that for the
template variable g of s, c. So this
is, g corresponds to variable a. S and c
corresponds to the indicies, in this
case u one and u two. And what we have is
we have two template parentswe have
I of s and D of c. And the, stipulation that u
i is a subset
of the variable of U1 up to Uk.  How is this for example that
we cannot have, an index in the parent  that doesn't appear in the child, so for
example, we cannot have in this, in this
model, for this reason and I'll describe
in a minute and this for example honors.
For student s depending on the grade, of
the student in multiple courses. And the
reason for that is that this is not a
CPD. You have, the honors variable
depending on a potentially unbounded,
number of parents which are all of, the
grades in which the students
participated, and, it's not to say, that
one can one define, such a dependency
model, in fact, there are richer languages
than plates, for which people have
defined this notion of an aggregate,
aggregator CPD. But it's not within the
standard paradigm of what are
traditionally called plate models. So by
preventing that, we now have, effectively,
a traditional model, where, you know, you
have a random variable with a finite fixed
set of parents. And so we can define a
template CPD which we can then reuse
in a model, for any copy of this template
variable, where a copy is, is obtained for
different instantiations of these indicies U
So for example, so
specifically, if we have this model if we
have this variable A of U1 up to UK then
for any instantiation little U1 up to UK
which are concrete instantiations of the
indicies we would have, the following
model we would have the variable A of
u on up to uk depending on
the specific. Which is potentially
confusing notation, because the sets
are a little bit hard to understand. But
this really, just think concretely of the
example. This exactly says that the
intellig-, that the grade of a particular
student in a particular course depends on
the difficulty of that course, and on the
intelligence of that student, that's all
it says, okay? So it's just a general way
of saying that. And, this
is just the formal version of the
statement that I made earlier that
requires the parents not to have variables
that are not explicitly instantiated in
the child. So that we don't have a free
floating variable that can be instantiated
in, arbitrarily many ways. So to
summarize, plate models
are a language which allows us to define a
template for an infinite set of Bayesian
networks. Why infinite? Because you can
have three students, ten students, 1,000
students, a million students, an unbounded
number of students. So there is an
infinite set of Bayesian networks that we
can use this language to encode and each
of them induced by a different combination
of the way many objects in our example,
for instance students of courses. The
parameters and the structure are reused.
In, those, within, the Bayes net, and,
across, the different Bayes nets, so, for
example, within, our university example, we
reuse the same parameter, and, if we have
a different university, with the different
set of student and courses, we could still
use the same parameters. These models by
allowing us to represent an intricate
network of dependencies allow us to
capture very richly correlated structures
in a concise way, which allows us to do
this kind of collective inference. Which
is potentially a very powerful source for
informed conclusions. Now I've presented
plate models, which are the, perhaps
earliest and one of the simplest of these
languages. Which allow us to represent
template structures. This is a simple one
for example, it has this restriction on
the parents not, having variables that are
not instantiated in the child, and so for
example you can't represent temporal
models here, because x of t-1 is not
instantiated in the variable xt, so
you can't have xt-1 as a parent of xt
not in a plate model, I mean
obviously we have languages that can do
that, but not this one. Similarly, you
can't have the genotype [of the mother] and the genotype
of the father affect the genotype of the
child because once again the child doesn't
instantiate the mother and the father.
These are separate indices. And so this is
a limited language but there's many other
languages that expand on it in different
ways and they each have different trade
offs in terms of what they express easily
and what they don't. And there's an entire
literature on this that we're not going to
go into but has provided a number of very
useful languages representing these claims
of richly structured models.