So, today's topic is an important
extention on the language of graphical
models. And it's intended to deal with the
very, large class of cases, where what
we'd like to do is not just write down one
kind of graphical model for a particular
application. But rather, come up with
something that is a general purpose,
representation that allows us to solve
multiple problems using the same exact
model. So, to understand what that means
in a somewhat more concrete setting, let's
go back. Now for genetic inheratince that
we have discussed previously it's arguably
the earliest example of Bayesian network
reasoning before Bayesian networks were
invented and here we have as input a
pedigree. Which is a family tree. And
we're interested in reasoning about a
particular trait. And for each pedigree
and each trait we can construct a Bayesian
network and the Bayesian network might
look like this. But clearly if you had a
somewhat different family tree, so
suddenly you had another three cousins and
a great grandfather join the family tree,
or if you had a different family
altogether, you would still want to use
the same sort of ideas, the same pieces of
what we used in the first network to
construct this other network because there
is clearly a lot of commonality between
them. So we have, what you might call,
sharing. Between models. But in addition
to that. You also have in this example as
a fairly obvious sharing within the model
so for example, this CPD that tells us how
Selma's genotype affects Selma's blood
type presumably is the same process by
which Marge's genotype affects Marge's
blood type and the same for Maggie and
Lisa and Bart and Homer and everybody. So,
so we have this tremendous amount of
sharing of both dependency models and
parameters. Similarly, you might argue,
you might, looking at this realize that
the genetic inheritance model by which
Bart's genotype is determined by the
genotype of his two parents as the same
inheritance model that applies to Lisa. To
Maggie, to Marge, to Selma, and so on. So
once again we have a lot of parameters
that are shared not just between but also
within the model. So we'd like to have
some way of constructing models that have
this, large amounts of shared structure
that allows us to both construct large
models from sparse parametrization and
also to construct entire family of models
from a single concise representation. This
is not the only such application. This is
probably the most commonly used type of
graphical models are those that have
shared structure and shared parameters.
So, here is another example that we've
seen previously, this is for natural
language processing, a sequence model, for
in this case trying to identify named
entity recognition, a very common task
for which graphical models have been used.
And here, also, we have a sequence model,
and we have, again, shared, shared pieces,
for example. The parameters that relate
the latent variable, in this case, what
type of, what type of variable, what type of entity it is.
Is it a person, is it a location, and so
on. There is a set of parameters here, and
they're going to be independent of the
place and the sequence. In which we find
the word because not because it's
necessarily an exactly correct model I
mean one could clearly imagine cases where
the position in the sequence might make
the difference but because it's often a
very useful simplifying assumption,
specifically because it allows us to A use
parameters, reuse parameters and B allow
us to apply the same model to sequences of
varying length without having to worry
about what is my fifteen word model versus
what's my eighth word model and so this is
a, another case where you have We have a
tremendous amount of reuse of
parameters. We've already seen similarly
the examples in this segmentation clearly
we don't want to have a separate model for
every super pixel in the image there's
hundreds of super pixels so we have
sharing across superpixels
So for example, the model here
that, that relates the class label of the
superpixel to the image features of that
superpixel is generally one to be shared
as are the parameters that involve
adjacent superpixels. So these edge
potentials are also going to shared across
in this case, pairs of superpixels.
And once again we
have sharing across models as well because
we are going to have one such model for
image A and obviously we don't want to
construct a separate model for every image
so once again we have sharing between and within
a model. So let's look at one
example a little bit more concretely
because it's an example that we're gonna
use in some of the later analysis. So now,
let's return to our university example
where we have a student who takes a class
and gets a grade and that the grade
depends on the student's difficulty oh I
am sorry difficulty of the course not
intelligence of the student. Now this is
all fine if we're interested in using just
about an individual student, but now let's
imagine that we want to think about an
entire university. So now we have a
difficulty variable. So these are all.
Difficulty variables. For different
courses in this case C1 up to CN are
different courses that exist in our
university and conversely on the other
side we have multiple students and this is
a set of intelligence variables that are
indexed by different students so we have
the intelligence of student one up to the
intelligence of student m. Now note that
these are different random variables they
can and generally will take different
values from each other but they all share
a probabilistic model and that's sort of
the kind of sharing that we have in mind.
And what we see here, is that the grade of
a student within a course, which are these
variables down here, depend on the
difficulty of the relevant course and the
intelligence of the relevant student. So
for example, the grade of student one in
course one, depends on the difficulty of
course one and on the intelligence. Of
student one and once again we have sharing
of the both the structure and the
parameters across these different grade
variables so that they all have the same
kind of dependency structure in the same
CPD. Another example is that of robot
localization and this is another example
of, in this case, the time series where
the robot moves through time from one
position to the other. And although the
position at time T is different.
Changes over time. We expect that the
dynamics of the robot. Are fixed. We'll
talk more about that later. So that gives
us a graphical model that again, looks a
little bit, this is one example of such a
graphical model where we see that the
position to the robot pose, over here,
these X variables depend on for example
the previous pose and on whatever control
action the robot took. And we're assuming
that once again we have sharing. Of these
parameters for each instantiation of this
variable. So what that gives rise to is a
class of models that are represented in
terms of template variables. Where a
template variable is something that we end
replicating, in many cases, again and
again, within a single model as well as
across models. And so the replication is
indexed by the, by the fact that the
variable. You can think of it as a
function that takes arguments. And the
arguments, for example, might be time
points, as in this example over here. So
here we have a location variable that's
indexed by time point or sonar reading
indexed by time point. We have, in this
case, a genotype variable and a phenotype
variable that's indexed by a particular
person. A class label that's indexed by
pixel. And similarly the difficultly of
the intelligence and the grades that are
indexed, in this case, by different
combinations of indexees, course student
or course student pairs. And a template
model is a language that tells us how
template variables can be the dependency
models for template variables and how
concrete instantiations of variables what
are called ground variables. Like the ones
that are actually indexed by a particular
timepoint or person how they inherit the
dependency molecule [inaudible]. And
their's a whole range of such languages
that have been developed in a special
purpose way for different applications. So
dynamic Bayesian networks are intended for
dealing with temporal processes for
example. Where we have replication over
time we have a whole range of [inaudible]
for object relational models both directed
models and undirected models where you
have multiple objects such as people or
students and courses or pixels so people.
courses, pixels, and lots of other things
which can be related to each other in
different ways and how you represent the
dependency model over that ensemble in a
coherent way.