We talked about Bayes net structure
learning as the task of optimizing a score
over a space of network structures. And,
one of the big design choices that we have
to make in this context is which scoring
function to use. Our first attempt at that
was to use the likelihood score. But as
we've already seen, the likelihood score
is very susceptible to over fitting, and
will invariably learn the most complicated
network that it can, given the constraints
that we impose on our space. We now
consider a different approach in which,
rather than constraining the space, or
maybe in addition to constraining the
space, we're also going. And to impose a
penalty on the complexity of the
structure that we learned so as to force
the model to trade [inaudible] force the
learning algorithm to trade off model
complexity with the fit to the data. And
specifically the model the, the,
specifically the score that we're going to
look at right now is something called the
BIC score. So, let's look at one way of
penalizing complexity which is the one
that the B-I-C score uses. The B-I-C score
has two terms in it, the first is just the
likelihood of the Graph and its maximum
likelihood parameters, relative to the
data. This is a familiar term, this is the
term that represents the, the same thing
as the likelihood score. So this term is
just score L, of G relative to D. And were
we to use this in isolation we would get
the same over fitting behavior. But we add
to this a penalty term, this is the second
term here on the right. And that term is,
is. Subtract log of M over two, times the
dimension of G. So, let's understand what
these different pieces are. M is the
number of training instances. And the
dimension of G is the number of
independent parameters. In the network. So
we talked about the concept of independent
parameters in the context of multinomial
networks and as a reminder, a multinomial
distribution has one fewer independent
parameters than the number of entries in
the multinomial. And from that, we can
compute the number of independent
parameters for any multinomial network. So
this basically counts the number of, of
degrees of freedom that we have in the
network in terms of estimating independent
parameters in it. And so these two terms
balance each other out. We've already seen
that the term on the left, the log
likelihood, tries to push towards a better
fit to the training data. Whereas the term
on the right, the law, the, the penalty
term is going to try and keep the number
of independent parameters. And therefore,
the network complexity down. And, so, this
score provides us with some kind of
tradeoff between fit to data and model
complexity. Now this is one choice in
terms of this tradeoff. And in fact there
are other scores that use a different
tradeoff between those two terms, but this
one is one that is very commonly used in
practice and has several distinct
motivations, some, one, some of which
we'll talk about and others and others
not. One comment that's worth making,
though, is the negation of this, of this
course, is we negate this entire term.
That is often called. The MDL criterion
where MDL stands for minimum. Description.
[sound], length. And so in fact this
notion of minimum description length is an
information theoretic justification for
this and the other justification for this
is one that's derived from a more Bayesian
criterion which is why BIC actually stands
for Bayesian. Information criterion. Let's
look at the asymptotic behavior of this
penalized score. We've already seen that
in the context of the likelihood score, it
really doesn't matter how much training
data we have, we will almost always pick
the most densely connected network that
our assumptions allow. But. This is no
longer the case when we have this
penalized score. So let's, to understand
that, let's break down the first of these
two terms, which is the likelihood score,
and remind ourselves that at least in the
context of multinomial networks, the
likelihood score Can be, re-written as in
the following way, so this is the
breakdown of the likelihood score and it
has, these two terms. The first is, the
number of data instances M, times the sum
over the variables X-I, of the mutual
information between X-I and its parents,
in, the network. And that mutual
information is relative to the empirical
distribution, P hat. The second term in
the likelihood score is a term, which is
also M times the sum over the variables of
the entropy of the variable, again, in the
empirical distribution. And as we've
already discussed before, this term is
independent of G. And so, doesn't affect
the choice of which structure is selected
because it's the same for all structures.
And so, we have these two terms that are
playing off against each other. We have,
the term over here. The, the true, which
is m times the sum of a mutual
information. And we have the second term,
the blue term which is the log of M over
two times the number of independent
parameters in G. Now, if we consider these
two terms, we see that, the mutual
information term grows linearly with m,
whereas the complexity term grows
logarithmically with m. And so as we get
more and more data instances, we put more
emphasis, on the fit to data and less
emphasis on the model complexity, so
intuitively we would infer that we would,
as we have more data instances, we would
be more amenable to learning more
complicated structures So that property
gives rise to a very important result that
we can state regarding the BIC score and
that is the result called consistency.
Consistency tells us what behavior we
would get, what network we would learn as
the number of samples grows to infinity.
And so here we're going to assume that the
data is actually generated from a
particular true structure G star, so there
is a G star because otherwise result
doesn't really make can't really be
stated. And what the consistency property
says is that as M grows to infinity, the
true structure G star  is going to be
the one that maximizes the score. Now that
by itself is not quite right as, as we can
see because the true structure g star
might have several other structures that
are I-equivalent to it and we have already
seen that the likelihood score and, and in
fact it also turns out to be case that
the, The penalty term are the same for I
equivalent networks. And so, it's not just
the true structure alone that will
maximize the score. It's the true
structure or any other structure which is
I equivalent to it. But as far as we're
concerned that's fine because we've
effectively learned the correct
representation of the probability
distribution. So to understand why this
result is true, we're going to give just a
very high level intuitive argument. We're
not going to prove theorem, it's a little
bit tricky to prove completely formally.
So let's first consider the case of why
this is not going to over fit. That is why
we're not going to have spurious edges
learned in maximizing the score as the
number of instances grows to infinity. So
here we go, we go back to un, we go back
and look at this formula over here and we
see that as M grows into infinity P hat is
going to approach P star, where P star is
my true underlying distribution. And so
what were going to have in this first term
over here is effectively the mutual
information relative to P star between X-I
and its parents. And in that P star, the
mutual information between Xi and its
parents is you don't get any benefit from
adding additional parents, spurious
parents. That is the mutual information in
P star for a spurious parent is not
going to grow because in the true
underlying distribution P star the, their,
the There is no Additional independence.
There's no additional correlation that we
have. And so at that point we're going to
have that, the more complicated structure
is about the same as G in terms of this
first term, but the spurious edges are
going to cost us. In terms of the number
of parameters in the blue term. And so,
these spurious edges will not contribute
to the late, to the data likelihood term,
but will be penalized more, and so we will
choose the sparser network that
corresponds with G star. Conversely,
why do we not under fit, that is, why do
we eventually learn all correct edges? And
that is because the data likelihood term,
tells us the edges that are required. That
is, edges, that, are in G, for example,
or in the I equivalent network. Will, if
we don't have them there, this mutual
information term will be lower than it
could be. And so we will have a higher
score by including those, terms in the
model. And because this mutual information
term. Grows with m linearly versus the
penalty term which grows logarithmically.
Then eventually the first term will
dominate and we'll have a and it will
beneficial for the learning algorithm to
add that edge. The, the required
edge in G star. So this is a high-level,
very hand-wavy argument, but at least it
gives an intuition as to why consistency
holds. So to summarize, the BIC score is a
very simple score that trades off, model
complexity with, the fit to data. And
therefore, has the important property of
asymptotic consistency. Which means that
if the data were actually generated by a
network G, for, which is a perfect map
for the distribution. Then either G or
networks I equivalent will have the high
score as M goes to infinity.