We talked about how the problem of
learning a general base net structure can
be viewed as a common coil optimization
problem in which we are trying to find a
high scoring network structure. And how
that's problem, that problem is usually
solved by some kind of heuristic search
over a space of base net structures. Let's
talk now about the computational cost of
this algorithm and how we can use the
property of decomposability, which we also
previously used in the context of tree
learning to considerably reduce the
computational cost of this of this
algorithm. So as a reminder, the
[inaudible] search procedure that we
discussed, iteratively moves over the
space of networks. And so if this is the
network that we're currently at, we need
to evaluate several different moves away
from that network. That's [inaudible]
usually local ways by adding the leading
or reversing an arc. We then score each of
these subsequent networks. And see which
of those has the highest score. And take
that move. And one can also have other
algorithms that evaluate the, the, the
[inaudible] that make the greedy move at
each point. But the basic idea is the
same. So what is the computational cost of
this algorithm? Let's do the naive
computational analysis. What we would get
if we were to do the naive implementation
of this. So, how many operators are there
in each search step that we need to
evaluate? So, in a Bayesian network with,
N nodes, we have, N times N - one,
different possible edges. One now each of
those edges is either present in the
graph, or not present in the graph. If the
edge is present in the graph, we can
either delete it. Or reverse it. And if
it's absent. We can add it. Which means
that effectively we have either two or one
possibilities for each of those N times N
-one possible edges and so we have O of N
squared possible operators that we need to
evaluate at each point in this step. Each,
each step in the algorithm. What is the
cost of evaluating each of the candidate
successors that we would get by taking one
of these operators? So reminding ourselves
that there are multiple components in this
score, one for each variable in the
network because of the decomposability
property, so we have n. Different
components. And for each of those we have
to look at this efficient statistics and
compute the resulting entry in the score
corresponding to a variable. Computing
efficient statistics requires a traversal
over the training data. And so that
something would takes o of m time, where m
is the number training existence. So
altogether, this stat requires o and times
m. Now, we haven't talked about this, but
one also needs to make sure that the
resulting graph from this operator is in
fact acyclic. And, so we need to do an
acyclicity check. This is something that
in general requires O of little M time
where M is the number of edges in the
graph. So altogether, if we sum up all of
these different pieces of the cost, we end
up with, a computational cost, which is O
of N squared times MN+little m. Where, by
and large, little m is usually dwarfed by,
M, by big M times N. And that is the cost
per [inaudible] up. Now if you think of
that work, it?s not even the [inaudible]
that large something that has fifty or
hundred variables so that ends fifty to
hundred and the number of training
instances is ten thousand this can get
really-really large and generally
impractical to do in a lot of situations.
So how to improve on this. Let's see how
we can exploit the decomposability
property to get a significant
computational savings in the search
process. Let's first look at a single
small operator, such as the one where we
have an edge between B and D. To this
network where such an edge did not exist
before. And let's consider the score that
we had for the original network which, in
this case is because of decomposability
property, is the sum of family scores for
the individual variables. So we have a
component that lists a score of A relative
to its empty set of parents, the score of
B relative to the empty set, C relative to
its parents A and B and D relative to its
parents C. Let's compare that to the score
of the network following the move. And we
can see that this score for the new
network is actually very similar to the
score of the original network, because.
For the same decomposability property, we
can break up the score into these little
components. And since most families
haven't changed that component, then the
score's going to be the same.
Specifically, we're going to have the
exact same score for A, relative to its
empty parent set. The same score for B,
the same score for C. And only this, only
this last score for D is now going to be
different, because of. The fact that we've
modified the family for D. But that
immediately suggest that we don't really
need to recompute these earlier components
of the score because they haven't changed.
We only need to compute the last component
corresponding to D. In fact we can do
better than that by, instead of
considering the absolute square. Instead
we are going to compute what's called the
delta square, which is the difference
between the square of the network
following the change, this network, and
the square of the original network. And
we're going to compute the difference
between those two squares, which as we can
see, is just the difference between the
squares of the two families for D the BC
family in the following, in the new
network versus the C family in the
original network. And that delta score is
going to be something that we can compute
just looking at a single family. It can
ruin the rest of the network. The same
thing happens for other local operators.
So, for example, if we consider now, the
deletion operator, that deletes an edge
between B and C. The, and we look at the
delta score, that delta score only cares
about the, the family C, because that's
the only family to have changed. And
that's going to be, again the difference
between the score of C with a single, with
a single edge A, minus the score of C,
with a family AD. So again, only one
family gets affected by this change. For
an edge reversal, the situation's a little
bit more complicated because we can see
that by flipping the edge from B to C and
making it go from C to B, there's actually
two families that are affected, the B
family and the C family. But that's still
just two as opposed to the entire network.
And so, we can see that, that delta score
is going to have two components. One is
the delta score for the C family, and the
second is the delta score for the B
family. But in either case, we only end up
affecting either one. Family, in the case
of edge addition, or in that case, a case
of edge deletion, or utmost, two families
in the case of edge reversal. And so that
means that we only have to consider a much
smaller fraction of the net worth when
computing the delta square. A second use
of this possibility property comes up when
we consider multiple consecutive steps of
the search algorithm. So let's imagine
that in the previous step, we decided to
take that steps that added the edge for
[inaudible] and now we have to consider
the next step in the search. But what are
the operators that are conceivable in this
next step of the search. For example, one
such operator is to delete the edge from
[inaudible]. This one, and notice that,
that edge deletion operation is in fact
operator that we considered in previous
step of the search before we decided to
add the edge from B to D. Now not only is
this operator the same. Notice that the
family of C hasn't changed between those,
between those two cases. And both of
these, cases, when we're considering the
move, C has the parents of A and B. And so
the delta score for that particular move
is not going to change either.
Specifically, if in this case, the delta
score was, the score of C, given family A,
minus the score of C, given the family AV.
We have exactly that same score. The same
delta score in, in the previous step. That
is, these two delta scores in the previous
step and the new step are exactly the
same. And so there's really no point to
recompute it. So which scores do we need
to recompute? The only scores that we need
to recompute are the ones that were
affected by the step that we currently,
that we just took. So specifically if we
took a step that modified the family of D,
then any step that involves an additional
change to the family of D will have a
different delta score because the family
is now different in doing the comparison.
However, families that were not affected
by the move don't need to be recomputed.
So to summarize, we only need to re-score
Delta moves, Delta scores, for families
that changed in the last move. So let's
summarizes the computational cost of this
procedure. What's the cost per move?
Having decided to take a move we have only
one or two families that were affected by
that move. That means that. Only O and
delta scores need to be computed because
for a given family there is only N
possible edges that impends on that
family. So only O and delta scores need to
be computed and for each of those we need
to compute sufficient statistics, which
takes OM time. So all together we have O
of little m times m as the cost of doing
this stuff which is actually two orders of
magnitude better than old n cube times m
that we had for the original naive
computation. Now this tells us the cost
after we pick a move. What about the cost
of picking the [inaudible]? Now, naively
we might say that there's N squared
possible operators that we can consider
any given move so we need to evaluate each
of them and pick the best one, or consider
each of them and pick the best one, but in
fact we can do considerably better by the
use of clever data structure, specifically
we can maintain a priority queue of
operators sorted by their delta scores.
Now when we re-score those O-event
operators. In this step over here. We need
to modify the score of those operators,
and reinsert them into the priority cue in
their appropriate place. But that's a
computation that requires [inaudible] and
login time, because there's only N of
them. And once we have done that, the best
operator will be at the top of the list.
Which we can then, take, identify and take
in constant time. And so this priority
queue saves us complexity by taking us
from old S square time for picking this
for traversing the set of operators to
something that requires [inaudible] log
in. And so altogether we've actually saved
a considerable cost in both of these
steps. It turns out that one can, get an
even higher level of computational
efficiency, based on a different
observation. So, it's a fact that, in most
network learning algorithms, the plausible
families, the ones that have some chance
of being selected, are variations on a
theme. That is, for a given variable A,
there might be some number of variables.
You know, B1, B2. Up to DK for a very
small K. That are reasonable parents to be
selected as parents for A. And so. How do
we exploit that property in computational,
to get computational savings? Turns out
there's two different, ways that one can
utilize this. The first is the fact that,
because we have the same set of variables
being constantly considered as being
candidate families. It means that we can
use sufficient statistics that we computed
in one step, and reuse them in a different
step if we cache them. Because the,
because we're likely to encounter the same
family more than once. We might encounter
B as a parent of A. And A as a pair, as a
possible pairing for B and for both of
these we have the sufficient statistics. A
B that are going to be utilized for both
of them. And so, if we compute this once
and then cache it, these sufficient
statistics we don't have to recompute them
again. That turns out to be a huge
difference in terms of the computational
cost of this algorithm. The second way
which this could be used is that if we can
identify in advance the set of B1 up to BK
that are reasonable parents to consider
for A. We can restrict in advance. That
set, and not consider other parents at
all, which reduces our complexity from o
of n to o of k, where k is some bound on
the number of plausible parents that we're
willing to consider. Now this, now is a
heuristic in the sense that this is a
restriction that could actually change the
outcome of our algorithm. It's not just a
way of reducing the cost, but it turns out
to be a very good approximation and
practice. To summarize, it turns out that
even the fairly simple heuristic structure
search that we employ in, in, such as
greedy hill climbing, can get expensive
when N is large. Because the, naive
implementation has the cubic dependence on
N. But we can exploit the decomposability
property, that we also exploit in the
context of tree learning, to get several
orders of magnitude reduction in the cost
of this search. We can also exploit the
recurrence of plausible families at
multiple steps in the search algorithm to
get further computational savings and also
restrict the search space to, to get
better, better computational property