So over the course of the last few
lectures we've talked about a number about
different inference strategies and how
they might be applied to a range of different
graphical models. One question that comes
up is whether the same strategies can be
used for the kinds of template based
models that we defined earlier in the
course. Models that are defined by a, say,
dynamic Bayesian networks, or via plate
models, or one of the other
representations that uses repeated
structure. So as we'll see, the answer to
that is both yes and no. That is, the same
strategies can be applied, but they're
also some interestingly new challenges
that arise from this. So, first let's
remind ourselves of how for example a
dynamic Bayes net is specified, so
as a reminder, dynamic Bayes net is
specified using a, initial time. Zero
distribution, which is usually a Bayesian
network, as well as the 2TBN that tells us
the transition model. And it's certainly
the case that one can take those two
pieces, and construct an unrolled or
ground Bayesian network. And once we've
done that, that ground Bayesian network is
a Bayesian network, just like any other.
And so whatever inference techniques we
have developed for answering queries for
any Bayesian network, can be used in this
context as well. So specifically, once we
unroll the DBN for a given trajectory
length, we can run your favorite
inference algorithm over the ground
network to answer questions such as what
is the location of the car at time two
given whatever evidence we might be
willing to give it. So. Observations, up
to time two or observations for the entire
duration of the sequence. The same thing
happens when we look at plate models. If
this is the simple plate model that we
have done for our university example,
where we have students and courses and
grades, then we can unroll that network to
produce a ground network over a subset of
students, in this case, this very simple
example, two courses and two
students. And that unrolled network is
once again a Bayesian networks just like
any other, and so we can run inference
over that network to answer questions
about what is our predicted distribution
over the intelligence of the given
student. >> Given some information about
grades for example. >> Mm-hm. What are
some of the challenges though. So, part of
the, Difficulty or new dimensions that are
offered by some of these models, is the
fact that they establish new problems,
which is particularly true in the context
of temporal models, where we might often
be interested in what you might call
belief state tracking. That is, keeping
track over the state of the system as it
evolves. Now, in some ways, this is just a
traditional probabilistic inference task,
because it corresponds to asking, what is
our probability distribution over the
state of time T, given. The observations
that the agent has had access to, up. To
time t. So this is, over here, what we see
is 01: t is just a shorthand for 01.
Comma, O two up to O T. And so this is an
inference task that can be answered using
standard, probabilistic inference
techniques over the unrolled network.
But there is a challenge that needs to be
addressed, if we want to keep track of this
probability distribution over the course
of a long trajectory, without having a
potentially unboundedly large network that
we have to keep running inference over. So
it turns out, fortunately, that one can do
this in a dynamic way, without. Keeping
track of the huge unrolled network at
all points in time. And this comes
directly out of the consequence of the
Markov properties of the graphical model.
So specifically we're going to do this as
a two stage process, where the first thing
we're going to compute is this Sigma dot
T+1 and the position of the dot indicates
that, although it's a distribution over
the state at T+1, it's a distribution that
doesn't take into account the T+1
observation. And so this is defined to be,
as written here, the probability of this
state at time T+1, given the observations up
to time T. And so now we can do fairly
straightforward manipulations of this
probabilistic expression. So the first
thing is, we inject S of T into the right
hand side of the conditioning bar, and sum
out over it. So this is now a probability
of ST+1, given ST and observations up to
time T times the probability of ST, given
the observations up to time T. And now we
can apply independencies that arise
from the structure of the graphical model
and specifically the fact that the state
at time T plus one. Is independent of
everything that occurred before, given the
state at time T, which is going to allow us
to use conditional independence to
basically simplify the expression as
follows, just the probability of ST plus
one, given SFT which is just our
transition model. [sound]. And
ahe second term which is probability of s
of t given o one to t. This is just a
previously computed belief state as
it's called, the sigma t that we are
trying to keep track of. And so this
allows us to keep sigma t and produce
sigma dot t plus one. The second step is
now to account for the observation model, at
time t+1. So lets look at what that
would involve. So now we have sigma dot of
T+1 which we defined on the previous slide
and so now we want to condition that on
the new piece of observation or the
observation of time t+1 and this is defined so
just and from that to derive the belief
state sigma T+1 and so here we are just
going to take that definition probability
of S(t+1) give it all of the observation the
ones the one with T and the new one. And
we're going to apply Bayes' rule to define
this and to, to reformulate this and that
gives us probability of OT+1 given ST+1
and the previous observations times the
probability of ST+1 given zero of one
through T divided by the probability of
OT+1 given OT. This is a straightforward
application of, of Bayes' rule and, once
again, we can now examine each of the
terms in this expression and see what it
corresponds to and looking first at this.
The first term on, in the, in the
numerator, we can see that this is the
probability of the observation at time t
given the state at time t and a bunch of
things that happened in the past. And once
again conditional independence tells us
that the stuff that happened in the past
is not aff-, is, is irrelevant and can be
removed because of condition
independencies. The second term. Which is
this one is the we just computed. Its
[inaudible]. And that gives us this
expression over here which is they're easy
to, to deal with because each term in
numerators either something that is part
of our model, the observation model. In
this case or. Something that we've
computed here, sigma dot equals one. Now
you might wonder about how we get this
somewhat scary looking denominator. But
the important thing to remember is, as in
previous examples that we've seen, this
denominator is simply a normalizing
constant. [sound]. [sound] Which can be
derived by computing the numerator. And
then normalizing. And so it's not really
scary at all. So going back to an example
that we've seen before, let's look at the
example of robot localization. This is a
model that we've already discussed, so
we're not going to talk about it anymore.
But now let's see how we might, how this
might manifest in the context of an actual
belief state tracking problem. So here is a
situation where this model might be
applied. So let's first, explain what
we're seeing before we see a demo. What
you see is the green circle is the robot
true position which is not known. To the
robot because, the robot's trying to
localize itself. These blue lines are the
observed. Sonar readings but the robot.
Gets at each point in the, in the process.
So, you can see that the returned length
of the sonar readings correspond roughly
to the distance of the robot from the
wall, that there is some noise here. So
for example, sometimes for whatever reason
the sonar appears to go through the wall,
even though it should have been giving,
giving us a reading that is considerably
closer because it should have been
reflected from the surface. So this is,
sonars are quite noisy and the
visualization that we see reflects that.
The red dots that you see is a
visualization of the robots beliefs over
where it is and the initial stage this is
a uniformed probability distribution and,
and because the robot doesn't know where
it is. And, as we'll see, this gets
clumpier and clumpier over time as the
robot's belief state over where it's
likely to be becomes more and more
definitive. So let's look at. This and
what this looks like overtime. So what we
are gonna see is the Robot Lewis as it
gets more modulations. We can see, that
the distribution becomes clumpier and
clumpier, and pretty sure the robot's sure
that it?s in the hallway, but because of
symmetries its not sure which side of the
hallway it is, so we have these two
clumps. Representing these two modes of
the distribution. But now the robot's
going to walk into this room and notice
that this room over here is different from
the room at the bottom. So right now the
robot has localized itself with certainty
or close to certainty because only one
position is consistent with it?s with the
observations that it's received over the
course of its trajectory. The second
challenge associated with these complete
base models are computational issues. Sure
we can produce and unroll Bayesian network
and compute a posterior over any subset of
the variables using standard inference
techniques. But one of the consequence of
being able to produce these very large
probabilistic graphical models from a
fairly small template is that we can
produce very large probabilistic graphical
models from a very small template. And
probabil-, large probabilistic graphical
models can pose new inference challenges
in terms of the s-, the ability to scale
inference to models of that size. So
specifically if we look at the unrolled
model that arises from an unrolled DBN and
thinking back to some of the analysis that
we did regarding the complexity of
probabilistic inference for a particular
probabilistic graphical model. We
remember, for example, that if we want to
run inference, say the exact inference,
say a click tree, over this unrolled
network, then For example if we want to
s-, to have a clique tree where say the
time zero variables are in one part of the
model and the time t variables for some
future t are on some other in some other
clique in the model so they're not all together in
one big clique, then the minimal subset
needs to separate these variables over
here, let's say the blue variables, the
time zero variables from. The green
variable. So the subset must separate
them. And if you think about what
separation imposes on us in this setting
we can see that the only way to separate.
The For example these variables, the blue
variables over here from the green
variables over here, is to put in the
subset at least the persistent variables.
That is, the ones where. There is an edge
from the variable of time T to its
incarnation of time T plus one. And so the
minimum subset in this context, the
smallest subset that we can construct that
would allow us to have different cleats
for say, time zero and time two, is
something that involves all of these
variables in the middle. And so. That can
potentially involve a significant
computational cost for exact inference,
especially when we have a large number of
persistent variables. A different way of
understanding this is via the concept of
entanglement if we're thinking of belief
state tracking. So [sound] if our goal is
to maintain a belief state over say the
variables time three and we are trying to
think about how can we maintain this
probability distribution the sigma of time
three in a way that doesn't involve of
maintaining a full explicit joint
distribution over the variables time
three, we quickly realize that really we
have no choice because there are no
conditional dependencies within time
three. Now you might say, how's that, this
is a nicely structured model, why wouldn't
there be conditional independencies. Well
look at what's going on here, can we say
that weather is a times three
conditionally independent of failure times
three. Well, in locally, they're not
connected to each other within the time
slice, but there's certainly an active
trail between them, that goes for example,
like this From weather time three, weather
time two, weather time one, failure time
two, to failure time three. And so this is
an active trail between these two
variables, which means that they are, when
you consider only the variables at times
three, not conditionally independent of
each other, given any of the other
variables at times three. And so this
entanglement process occurs very rapidly
over the course of, tracking a belief
state in a dynamic daisy network, which
eventually means that the belief state, if
you want to maintain the exact belief
state is just. [sound]. Fully correlated,
in most cases. And so this is a
computational consequence of the fact that
we have a very large Bayesian network. And
if you wanna think about just how large it
can get, we can go back to the real,
Vehicle tracking example that we talked
about in a previous lecture and note that
all of these variables over here. All
persistent variables and so [inaudible]
say tracking will have to maintain if we
were to be done exactly. If full joint
distribution over all these variables
which is why could be intractable.
Certainly if you want real time
performance and problem not even [sound]
without that constraint. And so, there has
been a lot of work on approximate method
in the context of a temporal models
because of the computational issues that
they raise. Computational issues like that
also occur in plate models so here is the
plate model unrolled for our student
example with the difficulty over here. And
the intelligence. Alright and the grades
in the middle are all observed, have not
put in the actual variables to, because of
which [inaudible] things up. And we have
talked about computational complexity of
this bipartite. Mrf, which is what we
really have here where you have the
variables on the left are connected to the
variables on the right. And, in general,
seeming that the grades are fairly dense,
we mentioned before that the. For exact
inference the lowest, cost that we can
expect is, if you have M variables on the
left and N variables on the right, its the
minimum, of M and N. So the minimum of the
number of courses and the number of
students, and again this is you, you could
come up, cases where this is going to be
lower than that, but in general, for a
bipartite MRF like this that?s what you're
what?s, that?s what you're going to get
and assuming that the University has a
reasonably high number of courses and
presumably even more students, this can
become intractable very quickly, giving
rise to the need for approximate inference
methods. That said, approximate inference
methods can be very successful. So, let's
just conclude this with one more example.
So, here is an example from, in this case,
an undirected, template model, where we
have repeated structure. So here the task
is to classify web pages into categories
where you want to categorize web pages.
This is a project called, web KB, That was
[sound] constructed by Tom Mitchell and
his group at Carnegie Mellon University.
And what we see hers is that you like to
categorize web pages as corresponding to
students faculty courses and so on. And
while one can use standard machine
learning techniques to categorize web
pages individually, say by the words that
they contain, it turns out one can get
significant improvement in performance by.
Considering the connections between the
web pages, so specifically by considering
edges. Between in this case, undirected
edges between the category of pages that
are linked to each other. So for example,
we see and this is a model that was
learned from data that students are quite
likely to point to faculty and faculty are
somewhat less likely to point to students.
And faculty are even less likely to point
to other faculty. And so that gives us
some information about the correlations
between labels of web pages that are
linked to each other and gives rise to.
Improvement in performance that one gets
better actually quite, quite considerable.
So for example a reduction in error from
eighteen percent to a little bit over
twelve%. To summarize. Our inference in
template of, on template models. Can be
done in principal [inaudible] by using
standard inference methods. However,
template models specifically weighs new
inference tasks. Such as real [inaudible]
tracking which requires certain adaptation
in our methods. And. Furthermore, a second
source of complexity here is that the
[inaudible] that we get by unrolling these
models is often very large and sometimes
quite densely connected, requiring careful
design of algorithmic methods and use of
approximate methods that can allow us to
deal with the increase in [inaudible]