We showed how influence diagrams can allow
an agent to make decisions regarding what
course of action the agent should take,
given a set of observations. But often, we
want to answer a different type of
question. Which is, what observations
should I even make before making the
decision? For example, a doctor
encountering a particular patient might
have to decide which set of tests to
perform on that patient. Tests are not
free, they cause pain to the patient, they
come with a risk, and they cost money. So
which ones are worthwhile, and which ones
are not? The same kind of question comes
up in many other scenarios. So, for
example, if you're running a sensor
network, which sensor should I
measure? The sensor might require energy
in order to transmit the information, and
that might be something that we want to
consider carefully. And there is many
other examples of that. It turns out that
the same framework of influence diagrams
can also be used to answer that question
using rigorous formal foundations.
So how do we provide a formal semantics for
the notion of the value of getting
information or the value of making an
observation? So, the, the, formal
definition that one can provide for this
is the value of perfect information, so
this stands for value...of
perfect information. About a variable X is
the value that we have by observing X
before choosing an action at A and perfect
means that we observe X would perfectly
without, without any noise. How do we
give that a formal
value? Well, if D was our original
influence diagram before I had the
opportunity to observe x. We can compare
the value of d to the value of a different
influence diagram which is the one where I
introduce an edge from x to a. Because
that tells me what the value of the
situation would be, if, if I had that, the
ability to make that observation. So we
can now define the value of perfect
information to be simply a difference
between the maximum expected utility that
I have in the situation where I have this
observation. Minus the value of the
expected utility to the agent in a
scenario where I don't. So in this example
that we presented before, we saw that we
compared two decision situations, one
where the agent has found the company
without any kind of additional information
about the value of the market and the
other is where the agent gets to make an
observation regarding the survey variable
prior to making the decision whether to
found the company. So we can compare the
value of the decision making situation
with a variable from S to F minus the
assuming the agent makes optimal decisions
of the original decision making situation
D. And we can compare that and see how
much the agent's gained by this and if you
recall, we computed this to be 3.25 and
this was two so the value of perfect
information was 1.25. Which means that the
agent should be willing to pay anything up
to 1.25 utility points before, in order to
conduct the survey because doing that will
increase his expected utility. So let's
look at some properties of the value of
perfect information. So the first
important property of the value of perfect
information, is assuming that there is no
cost to the information. So not counting
in how much it might cost to conduct a
survey. One can show that the value of
perfection information is always greater
than or equal to zero. So let's first go
ahead and convince ourselves that this is
true. So, let's look at this expression
over here which compares the maximum
expected utility between two different
influence diagrams. And remember, that
each of these is obtained by optimizing
over a decision rule. This one is,
optimizes the, the MU of the original
decision, D, is optimizing a decision rule
delta, which is a CPD of A given its
current set of parents Z. And this one,
the new influence diagram, is optimizing a
decision rule delta, where A has Z as a,
all the original parents Z. Plus an
additional parent X. And the point that
one, that becomes on this when you think
of it this way is that this is strictly
larger class of CPDs than this. That is
any CPD. Of the form delta of A given Z,
is also a CPD. Of the form delta of A
given Z and X. Which means, any decision
rule that I could have implemented in my
original influence diagram, I can also
implement in the context of my current
influence diagram. And if it had a
particular value there, it would still
have that same expected utility varia-,
value, in the original diagram. But to go
back to our example for, for instance, if
the agent. Has a decision rule that found,
[inaudible] to found the company
regardless of the value of the survey.
That is still legitimate decision rule
even when they get to observe the survey,
and it would have exactly the same
expected utility. And so that means that
the set of decisions that I get to
consider is just larger in the context of
the richer, of the richer influence
diagram. And therefore one cannot possibly
lose by exploring a larger, a larger space
over which to optimize. Okay. So now let's
think about the second property which is
when this value of perfect information is
equal to zero. And this follows from very
similar reason to the one that we just
talked about. So if the optimal decision
rule for D. For my original influence
diagram B is still optimal for the
extended influence diagram. Then I've
gained nothing from the information. That
is I, any, any decision that I could, any
decision move that I could of applied
before I could still apply. And therefore,
there I gained nothing from this initial
observation. And so this gives us a very
clear notion of when information is
useful. Information is useful precisely
when it changes my decision. In the police
one case. >> Which, thinking about this
from the other perspective. If there is no
ability for an observation to change my
decision, there really is no point in
making it. Let?s see how this intuition
manifests in an actual decision making
scenario. So let?s imagine that our
entrepreneur has decided against founding
a widget company, and is now starting to
pick between two companies that he can
choose to join. For each company, there is
the state that the company is in, so S1 is
that the company is not, doesn't have that
great of a management, things are not
necessarily going so well, so that's S1.
S2 is medium and S3 is the company's doing
great. And the same thing holds for both
companies. We are assuming that the
company funders have access to some of the
information, to this information about the
company state because they can do some
very in depth [inaudible] diligence and so
the chances of the company to get funding.
Depends on the state of the company. So
you can see that if the company's state is
poor, S one, then the chances of getting
funding are 0.1, whereas if the company's
doing great, the f, chances of getting
funding are 0.9. And we're assuming that
the agent's utility is one if the company
that he cho, that he joins. It's funded
and zero otherwise. But now let's think
about the two strategies that the agent
can take without information. And so, if
the agent chooses to join company one. One
can see company one is That the expected
utility now is 0.72 and the expected
utility of company two which is not doing
as great is only 0.33 which's you know, if
you look at the state of the company, that
makes perfect sense. Now what happen if
the agents now get to make an observation?
And specifically we're going to let the
agent make the observation. Of S two,
regarding S two. Which is, in this case
the weaker of the two companies. So, the
agent has a little mole inside the company
and can get access to that information
before making his decision. What happens
then? Well. The, if you look at the
utilities values, you can see that if
company one is in state, sorry if company
two is in state one. Then, which is a not
unlikely scenario, it happen with
probability 40%, the chances of getting
funding are 0.1. And so the agents
expected utility in this case. So the
expected utility if. The agent chooses C2
and S, and the state of the second company
is S1 is 0.1. The expected utility if the
agent chooses the second company and it?s
doing moderately well is 0.4. Both of
these are lower than 0.72 that the agent
can guarantee on expectation if he chooses
for company one; even without any
additional information from company one.
And so in both of these cases the agent is
going to prefer to stick with his original
Choice Of going with company one. It is
only in the one scenario that, that we
have where. S, where the second company is
doing really great. Then, his expected
utility from going with that company is
0.9 because that's the chances of getting
funding in this case. And in that case, he
would prefer. The changes in opinion and
go with C two. But that happens with very
low probability, that only happens if
probability is at 0.1. And so that means
that the value of information here is
going to be very low because although
there is a situation in which the agent
changes his mind, it?s a very unlikely
scenario. And sure enough if you look at
the expected utility in the influence
diagram with that edge I just added, it
only goes up from 0.7 to 0.743, which
means that the agent shouldn't be willing
to pay his mall and company too much money
in order to get that information about
company two. Okay. Now let's look at a
slightly different situation. Where now,
neither company is doing so great. So, you
can see that now company one is also kind
of this sort of rocky start up without a
very good benefit structure and, and
unclear business model. In this case what
happens? So once again we can complete the
expected utility of the two actions and
now we can see that the expected utility
of choosing company one is 0.35 as
compared to the expected utility of
company two which is 0.33. Now the
decisions are much more balanced relate to
each other and so you would think that
there would be a much high value of
information and the chances that the agent
would change his mind are considerably
larger. So let's work our way through that
and see that once again if we consider
adding this edge from the mole and company
too, we can now see that the agent is
going to want to change his mind either
when he observes S2 or when he observes S3
because both of these, both 0.4 and 0.9
are larger than, than the expected utility
that he gets from sticking company one.
And now indeed the expected utility rate
goes up in the case where we have the
influence diagram and it goes up to 0.43
which is a much more significant increase
in the expected utility relative to what
we have before because now there is more
value to the information. We change, the
agent changes their opinion in two out of
three scenarios and that happens with
probability 0.6. Now let's look at. Yea,
the third scenario, where now we've
changed the probability that the company
gets funded. Now we're back in the bubble
days of the internet womb and basically,
pretty much every company gets funded with
a pretty high probability. Even if their
business model is totally dubious. And in
this case, what happens so now we can once
again compute the expected [inaudible] of
C-1. Which is 0.788. The expected
[inaudible] of C-2. Which is 0.779. And we
can see that again these expect
[inaudible] are really close to each
other. And intuitively what that's going
to mean is that even if the agent changes
their mind. It doesn't make much of the
difference in terms of their expected
[inaudible]. So here we see that because
of, in this case we can see that 0.8 which
is their expected utility in the case of
the observed s2. This value S2 is bigger
than 0.788 and so they're going to pick.
They're going to the sight to change their
mind. And go from C1 to C2 and similarly
for S3. But the actual utility games in
this case are fairly small. And so now the
utility, the expected utility that we have
in this scenario, where the agent gets to
observe this variable without, before
making a decision is zero. Eight one four
two which is only a fairly small increase
over the 0.788 that they could have
guaranteed themselves without making that
observation. So once again, this is a case
where as a promo in company two doesn't
get that much money. But to summarize,
influence diagrams provide a very clear
and eloquent interpretation for what it
means to make an observation as simply the
vow, the difference in the expected
utility value or the NU values rather
between two influence diagrams. And this
allows us to provide an intuition about
when information is valuable and that is
only when it is induces a change in the
action in at least one context. And now
quantitatively it means that the extent
which information is valuable depends both
on how much my utility improves based on
that change and on how likely the context
or in which I changed the decision.
We showed how influence diagrams can allow an agent to make decisions regarding what course of action
the agent should take given a set of observations but often we want to answer a different type of question
which is observations should I even make before making the decision?  For example a doctor encountering
a particular patient might have to decide what kind of test to perform on that patient.  Tests are not
they cause pain to the patient, they come with a risk and they cost money.  So which ones are worthwhile
and which ones are not.  The same type of decisions comes up in many other scenarios.  So for example,
if you're running a sensor network, which sensor should I measure? The sensor might require energy in
order to transmit the information, and that might be something we want to consider carefully, and there
are many other examples of that.  It turns out that the same framework of influence diagrams can also
be used to answer that question using rigorous formal foundations.  So how do we provide formal semantics
for the notion of the value of getting information?  Or the value of making an observation?  So the,
the, formal definition that one can provide for this is the value of perfect of information.  So this
stands for value of perfect information...  about a variable x is the value that we have by observing
x before choosing an action at A.  And perfect means we observe x with, um, perfectly, without any noise.
So how do we give that a formal value?  Well, if D was our original influence diagram before I had the
opportunity to observe x, we can observe that value of D to the value of a different influence diagram
which is the one where I introduce an edge from X to A, because that tells me what the value of the situation
would be if I had the ability to make that observation.  SO we can define the value of perfect information
to simply be the difference between the maximum expected utility I have in the situation where I have
this observation, minus the value of the expected utility to the agent in the scenario where I don't.f
So in this example that we have presented before, we compared two decision situations, one where the