We've already said that there is many
different algorithms for inferencing
graphical models. But the simplest and
most fundamental is an algorithm typically
known as variable elimination. Let's
consider the variable elimination
algorithm in the context of the simple
example of a graphical model structured as
a chain. Here we have we're interested,
maybe, in computing the distribution over
variable E. So we're interested in P of E.
And as we've already said, that
probability is proportional to the
unnormalized measure, P tilde over
A, B, C, D, and E, summing up. All of the
variables except for E. So now let's see
how we can do this more efficiently than
simply constructing the joint distribution
and then summing things out. So, the first
thing we do is we write up this
unnormalized measure as a product of the
constituent factors. And for the moment,
we're going to assume that we only have
pairwise factors for the edges in this graph. So,
we have a factor for AB, a factor for BC,
CD, and DE. So those are the factors phi 1
up to phi 4. Now what is the first
observation that we have when we see the
summation over A, B, C, and D of a product
of factors? Well, we've already done this
exercise previously, when we were doing
some proofs related to graphical models.
That, if you have a factor that doesn't
mention a particular variable in it's
scope, we can move it out of the scope of
the summation. So specifically, phi 2
of BC can be moved out of the summation
over A, as can phi 3 of CD, and phi 4
of DE. Which leaves us only with the
summation over A, of phi 1 AB. So that
gives us the expression over here. Now
this is. Now this is a summation over a
pair wise factor, and the result of this
is a factor over a single variable B,
which we're going to call tau 1 of B. So we end
up with an expression that looks like this.
So now let's continue this expression,
developing this expression further.
Knowing that we now have an expression
that doesn't involve A only the variables
B, C, D and E so that effectively we have
eliminated E from the graph A we have
eliminated A from the graphical model. So
let's go back to this expression. We now
have this product of four factors and once
again we can look at what factors involve
the variable B and which ones don't. And
the ones that don't can be moved out of
the summation, just as before, giving us
this. For now we have an expression which
is a product of these two factors, summed
out over B. And this is going to give us
an expression tau 2 whose scope is C. And so
we now have an expression that does not
involve the variable B, and so now we've
eliminated B from this graphical model.
And we can similarly continue to eliminate
C and D so that ultimately we end up with
an expression that involves only the
variable E. And that expression is going
to be proportional to the probably of the,
to the marginal probability of E. Now is
through this algorithm in the context of
some of more complicated example which is,
our enhanced student network that we played
around with before. So lets imagine that
our goal is to compute the probability of
the variable J, this one. And in order to
do that we are going to have to eliminate from
the joint distribution all of the other
variable except for J. So this is our, our
expression. And note that we have this
product of factors I've taken already in
this expression the factors that we're,
the CPDs and turned them into factors so
that we can have a consistent notation.
And now we need to eliminate every one of
the variables except for J. So we're going
to start with eliminating the variable C
first. And, and so once again we're going
to take the summation over C and we're
going to push it in, leaving in the
summation only the factors that involve
C. And those are phi D and phi C. Multiplying
them together and eliminating C is going
to give us a factor which we are going to
call tau 1 whose scope is D. Mm-hm. And by
putting tau 1 into this expression and
removing the ones that we've just
multiplied together, we end up with this
expression. Over here. Having eliminated
C, we now go ahead and eliminate D. So,
here we have the variable D, and which
factor is involved D, well, tau 1 of D
and phi G of G, I, and D. And, so, everything
else is taken out of the summation and we
just have this expression over here. And,
that's going to give us, tau 2 whose
scope is G and I, after having eliminated
the variable D from this product, whose
scope is G, I and D. And tau 2 gets put
back into the bucket. Together, with
everything else, [sound]. Moving forward
we're now interested in eliminating I
[sound]. And so the factors that involve I
are tau 2 of G and I, and phi S
of S and I, and phi I of I. And so we go
ahead and multiply them together. To give us
a factor, whose scope is G, I, S and
eliminating I gives us a factor, tau 3
whose scope is S and G. And so the
process continues. And let's just finish
it, all the way to the end. Now, our goal
is to eliminate H. Well, H is a little bit
of an interesting case. The only factor
that mentions H is this factor, phi of H. And,
if we think about what phi of H is, phi H, as it
happens. Is P of H given G and J. And so
for summing that up over H, we're actually
summing up what is, in fact the
conditional distribution. And since we
know that a conditional distribution, when
you sum up on the, the values on the left
hand side, the summation is necessarily is
equal to one. So in principal, we could
have taken this entire expression. Erased
it, and written one instead. And that
would have given us something that is a
factor that doesn't depend on anything
would have just been, would have just
disappeared. But for purposes of
demonstration, we're not actually going to
do that because in fact, not every
algorithm is clever enough to notice these
kinds of coincidences. It depends on
whether they were designed to look for
that. And so we're going to do this in the
same way, in the same sort of naive way
that we've done before, which is just.
[inaudible]. Turn this in to a factor
which is going to be Tau-4 of G comma J. So,
so now we have that factor, which really
is one, but we're not going to pay
attention to that particular aspect for
the purposes of demonstrating how the
algorithm would work. Okay? Next is
eliminating G, and we have this
expression, which we inherited from the
previous slide. And G is one of the big ones,
because it appears in, phi L,
tau 3 and tau 4. So when we
think about the variables here in this
scope, we see that this one actually has
this product over here, actually has a
scope of L, G, S, J which is the largest
factor, the one with the largest scope
that we've encountered so far. Summing out
G, we end up with a factor whose scope is
L, S, and J, so we're missing an S. And,
and now we put that into. This expression,
and out comes a now, product of two
factors. And, really, at this point, we
might as well just multiply them and end
up with a factor over J and. Hold on. So
that gives us variable elimination in
its, naive form. What about variable
elimination with evidence? Well, we've
already basically established how to deal
with evidence. If we're interested in,
[inaudible] in, for example, solving the
query probability of J, I= little i.
Comma H equals little h, the way in which
we do that is by, is by computing the
probability of the joint event J, I
equals little I, H equals little h and the
way in which we do that is by reducing the
factors to correspond to this scope. And
so if these were, if, so we take each of
the factors that involves I, and we
basically instantiated to take the
particular value for that I, the value
little I, and similarly for H. And so we
see here, for example, that, where as phi I
initially depended on I, now it doesn't
depend on anything. Because this is simply
the value phi I of little I, which is a
constant. And, whereas, for example, G
depended on D and I, as we can see in the
original example diagram. Here, phi G in
the reduced factor doesn't depend on I,
and is really probability of G, given
little I and D. And the same reduction
occurs for H=h, and so we end up with the
following set of reduced factors. And now,
once we have that set of reduced factors,
we do elimination as, exactly as before.
No changes whatsoever to the algorithm.
The only aspect that's a little bit
different is notice that we don't
eliminate. No H and no I because there's
no point in eliminating vat, a variable
that has a single value. There's no need
to sum up over it when it only has a
single value. So, with, this gives us a
unified framework for dealing with, with
queries whether they involve evidence or
not. And then how do we get the
probability of J, given the evidence?
Well, this is straight forward, we simply
re-normalize. Because we, because we can
take this. And simply divide by what it
turns out to be, the probability, the
normalizing constant. Is. [sound] So,
let's see whether the same idea applies to
Markov networks. So here's our simple
Markov networks, n, network with four
variables. Let's imagine that our goal is
to compute P of D. And so in order to do
that we need to eliminate A, B, and C from
the unnormalized measures. So we have this
being the unnormalized measure, and we're
summing up over A, B, and C. And the
process works in exactly the same way. So,
if we want to sum out A first, then here
is the factors that involve A, phi 1 of AB, this one. And phi 4 of A D,
multiply them together, we've got a f,
factor whose scope is A B D, and then we
sum out A to get a factor whose scope is B
D. That gives us a new set of factors
where A has been effectively been
eliminated from the graphical model. And
at the end of the process, we get a factor
over the single remaining variable D. So
tau 3 of D and that factor is not the
probability of D. It's proportional to the
probability of D. It's actually equal to
P tilde of D, which is the unnormalized
measure. And so in order to get P of D, we
renormalize. So to summarize this, the
main routine in this algorithm, is
something, is a routine which we call
eliminate variable Z from a set of factors
Phi. And what it does is the following. We
first look within Phi, and we define the
set of factors, Phi prime, which are all
factors that involve Z. And that's what
this mathematical expression says. The
factors Phi I such that Zs in their
scope. We take all those factors and we
multiply them. And then we sum out the
variable Z which is the one that we want
to eliminate. Now, and here is the
important point: we've already used up
these factors, these ones over here have
now been used. We don't want to reuse
them. And so we take them out of the set
of factors and instead we introduce the
one that we just created by multiplying
those factors and summing them up. This
basic operation is what we use in the
context of, the algorithm as a whole. We
begin by reducing all factors by the
evidence. In, which is just eliminating
the rows that don't, that are not
consistent with the observations. And that
is what gets us our set of factors Phi. Now
for each non-query variable we need
to eliminate it. And so we have run one at a
time something that eliminates the
variable Z from the set of factors Phi.
Each such step changes my set of factors.
It adds factors and removes, so actually
it starts by removing factors. Which we have
Phi prime from the previous one, from the
previous line, and it adds, and you factor
tau. And then finally at the very end
when all variables have been eliminated,
there may be one or more factors
remaining. So that point we multiply all
of the remaining factors and then we
normalize to get a distribution. So to
summarize, this is a very simple
algorithm. It works equally well for
Bayes nets and Markov nets. And it
uses, and, a factor product and factor
summation steps. And it does that by
ensuring that when you mult-, that when
you sum out a factor, when you do the
summation step over variable Z, then all
factors involving Z have been multiplied
in, which is the critical piece of the
correctness of this algorithm.