Very important insights about variable
elimination and how to best pick the
elimination ordering is provided by
thinking about the operations the variable
elimination executes as operations on a
graph. So let's see what that does. So
let's consider the initial graph in our
example and let's first view this graph in
terms of the factors that it involves. So
this is the set of factors that we have
in, in our analysis, a viewed as
undirected, viewed as simply factors. So
what is the structure of the graph that
corresponds to this set of factors? Well
first we're going to make all the edges
undirected, but that's not enough because we
see, for example, that we have a factor
here which is a factor over G, I and D,
and so what we need to do is we need to
add an edge between I and D to represent
the fact that they're together in the
factor. Other examples, in that, other
cases where we need to do this correspond
to the other V structures that we have in
this graph. So here, for example, we have
a V structure involving J, so we're going
to need to connect J's two parents and
similarly for H's two parents. This step
by the way is called, not by me,
moralization. Because of the dubious moral
value of marrying the parents of a child no
matter how many of them there are. Umm,
and so I did not invent that name. So
having moralized the graph, we now have
this version of it and this is what we
previously defined to be the induced
Markov Network for the current set of
factors. So, now let's think about a
variable elimination step and what it does
to this graph. So let's begin by
eliminating C and if you remember that
involved this operation. And so first
eliminating C is, changing the set of
factors. It removes these two factors over
here from the set. And introduces a new
factor tau 1 of D. So, the
induced graph is now going to look like
the following. We've taken C out. And this
the remainder is the induced graph over the set of
factors. Okay? Now we are going to
continue. We are going to eliminate D. So
once again we are going to take the two
factors that we have now introduced. ...
Sorry ... These two factors that are
involved here which is tau 1 of D and
phi G of G, I and D. Going to multiply them. And
going to eliminate D. And so the
resulting, and then the resulting graph is
now going to look like this. Where, again,
the, the nodes with the, with the dashed
edges are not really there, they're just
there to remind us that they were there
before. Continuing on, we're going to
eliminate I, and that involves multiplying
in, this term, this term, and this term.
And now something interesting is going to
happen. The factor that we introduced,
which is tau three of S and G Is a factor
that doesn't have an edge in the current
graph. So if we're interested in having
this graph represent our current set of
factors we're going to need to introduce
this edge between G and S. Because that
edge, is necessary because S and G are
together in the same factor. So that edge
is called a fill edge It's an edge that I
had to introduce because of the
elimination ordering. So why don't we just
think about this the way is using the
following example. Imagine every variable
that's eliminated is going off on a trip
around the world And when it's doing that
it is throwing a big goodbye bash and
inviting all of its friends to come and
join it. And when it does that all of its
friends get to meet each other and say, oh
you guys are nice I'm going to be your
friends too. And so all of the friends of
the variable that's eliminated become
friends as a consequence of the
elimination step, okay. So, let me write
that down, all variables connected to in
this case, I, become connected after it's
eliminated, so become connected directly
and that's a general, consequence of the
elimination step process. It's just that the
previous ones didn't happen to introduce
fill edges. Okay, let's continue,
[sound], so now we are going to eliminate
H, H also doesn't introduce any fill edges
[sound], and so we are going to end up
with that, and basically the remaining
steps are pretty mundane, we are going to
eliminate G [sound], L [sound] and S, and
we are going to end up with the following
graph. So this particular variable
elimination process only introduced one fill edge, which is a, a fairly
conservative thing and shows that we, sort
of that we just selected a pretty good
elimination ordering in this case [sound]
so we can now take and put all these edges
that we ended up using together in a
single graph and that graph is called the
induced graph and the induced graph,
which is denoted I, for induced,
Phi comma alpha over a set of factors
Phi and induced by a particular
ordering alpha, because you remember that
we were getting different complexities and
we are going to have different fill edges,
depending on the order in which variables
are eliminated. So this variable, this
induced graph, has the following,
properties. It's an undirected graph where
we connect every pair of variables Xi and
Xj, if they ever appeared in the same
factor when we ran variable elimination
using alpha as the ordering. And so in this
case all of the original, all of the black
edges, were there to begin with and we
ended up introducing just one of those
additional, new or fill edges. So now,
lets... There is some interesting
properties of the induced graphs that
are worth noting. First of all, there are
some properties that relate factors
produced during variable elimination. And
cliques in the induced graph. So first
let's define what a clique is. A clique is
a maximal fully connected sub-graph So,
let's parse that too. So for example, DIG,
here, is a fully connected sub graph,
because all of its three nodes are
connected each other. And it's maximal,
because I can't add any other variable to
this and still have that property hold. So
if I try and add S, for example, then S is
not connected to D. If I try and add C, C
is not connected to I or G. So I can't add
any other variable to this particular
clique, so it's a clique. Here is a clique
that's not maximal So here is, so it's not
[inaudible], so G L J is it's a
fully connected sub graph. But it's
not maximal because I can add S and still
have that hold. Here's another clique in
this graph. You have GID being one clique
and GSL and J being another clique. We're
going to have a third one which is GS and
I another one which is CD. And let's see
if I have enough colors to do this. And a
final one which is G, H and J. And if we
now look at the factors that we produced
in the course of variable elimination, we
see that there is an exact correspondence
between the factors and those cliques
so here for example, the yellow one is CD,
which is this one over here. This one over
here which is GID is the red one, this
one. So that's the red one. This one has S,
I, G, so that's the green one. This one
This one is H, G, J which is the brown
one. Tau 5 induces the big factor, the
one that involves four variables and
that's the blue factor over G, S, L, and
J. And this one doesn't actually introduce
any new cliques which is why it doesn't
have any, cliques associated with it. So
every factor produced during variable
elimination is a clique in the induced
graph. [sound] We can equally well check,
and we saw that in the previous
slide already that every maximal clique in
the induced graph is a factor that's
produced during variable elimination.
We've demonstrated this to ourselves by
inspection but let's actually get proof of
this. So let's consider a maximal clique
in this induced graph. So let's consider for
example GSLJ that's a maximal clique.
And now let's consider the run of variable
elimination, and one of those variables
has to be One of those variables has to be
the one to be eliminated first. So, some
variable in this clique. Some variable is
first to be eliminated. Well, what happens
when a variable is eliminated? Once it's
eliminated it, it doesn't, have any more
edges that get added to it. So once a
variable is eliminated it has no more, no
new neighbors are added to it.
Which means that at the time that it was eliminated
It had all the neighbors that it had in the clique
All the clique members as neighbors.
But if that's the case, then it means that it had factors involving all those other guys.
So it participated in factors with all these other guys.
And that means that when I multiply them all together we're going to end up with a factor over all of them.
And that is a proof that every maximal clique in the
induced graph must correspond to a factor
produced during the variable elimination
algorithm. So now that we, umm, have
constructed a graphical view of variable
elimination we can go ahead and construct
a measure of a complexity variable
elimination and that is a measure known as
the induced width. So first we are going
to define the width of an induced graph.
Is the number of nodes in the largest
clique graph by convention minus one. Why
minus one? No good reason but that's what
people, that's the of definition induced width
The minimal induced width of the graph, is
the minimum over all possible elimination
orderings alpha of the width of the
induced graph. So this is the best
achievable complexity that one can aspire
to with any elimination ordering. You can
think of the minimal induced width of the
graph as a lower bound on the best
performance of variable elimination for
any model that factorizes over the graph.
In summary, we've seen that the variable elimination algorithm can be viewed quite intuitively
as taking a set of steps, each of which corresponds to a graph.
Specifically, a variable elimination step for a variable X takes all of X's neighbours,
that may or may not have been connected before, and connects them to each other.
The result of all this is something
called the induced graph and we've seen
that the induced graph is possibly quite
connected as a result of this variable
elimination process and that the cliques
in this induced graph, that is, the
maximally connected subsets, maximally
fully connected subsets correspond
directly to the complexity of the variable
elimination algorithm. And as we'll see
can therefore help us analyze its
computational properties.