[sound] As we said, there's many different
kinds of queries that one can use a
graphical model to answer. Conditional
probability queries are m-, very commonly
used, but another commonly used type of
inference is what's called MAP inference.
So what is MAP inference? Map stands as a
shorthand for what's c-, for
Maximum a Posteriori and it's defined as follows,
here we have a set of evidence o-,
observations, little e over some variables
E. And we have a query Y, and it turns out
that for computational reasons that we're
not going to discuss for the moment, it's
important that the set of Ys is
everything, all of the variables other
than e. So now, our task is to compute
what's called the map assignment, which is
the Y, the assignment little Y to the
variables Y that maximizes the conditional
probability of, the variables Y given the
evidence. Now, so for those of you who
haven't seen the notation argmax,
argmax is the Y. That provides the maximal
value to this expression over here. Now,
note that, in some cases, this maximizing
value might not be unique. That is, there
might be several different assignments.
Say one, Y1 and Y2 that give the exact
same probability. And so the map is not
necessarily a unique, assignment. This has
many applications, some of which we've
discussed before. So in the context of
message decoding, for example, where we
have a set of noisy bits that are passed
over the channel, over noisy communication
channel, what we often want to get is the
most likely message that was transmitted,
that is as assignment to the transmitted
bits that is the most likely given our
evidence. In the context of image
segmentation, we would like to take the
pixels and figure out the most likely
assignment of pixels to, to semantic
category. So both of these can be
viewed as map assignment problems. Now, an
important thing to understand about map,
is it really is a different problem than
conditional probability queries. So
understand that, let's look at the
following very simple example over just
two random variables. So here we have, a
Bayesian network over the variables A and
B. And if you multiply the two CPDs, it's,
you get the joint distribution shown over
here. And it's not, and it's fairly
immediate to see that the map assignment
is this one, because it has the highest
probability. Can we get at the map
assignment by looking separately at the
variable A and at the variable B? So if we
look at that we see that if we look
separately at the variable A the most
likely assignment to the variable A is A-1
as opposed to, in the map assignment, the
variable A took the value A0. And so, we
can't look separately at the marginal over
A and over B and use that to infer the map
assignment. And the reason is that we're
looking for a single assignment over all
of the variables, that together has, has
the highest probability. Unfortunately,
just like the conditional probability
inference, however, this problem, too, is
NP hard. So, again, let's formalize what,
exact problem is at the heart of this
context. And it, and so here is, again,
one example of an NP hard problem in
the context of map, which is just to find
the joint assignment with the highest
probability. It's not the only NP hard
problem. Here is another one. Figuring out
what for given probabilistic graphical
model and some threshold little P, whether
there exists an assignment little X whose
probability is great than P. That problem,
too, is NP Hard. So, should we give up?
Well, just like in the context of
conditional probability queries the answer
is no. And, there is algorithms that can
solve this problem very efficiently and
fast in an even broader set of problems
than for conditional probability queries.
So let's again look deeper into this
problem, and understand the foundations of
what might make it tractable. So. Going
back to our example of a Bayesian network.
Once again we are going to view CPDs as
factors so here P of C again translates into
a factor over C just like before and whereas
in the case of conditional probability
queries, we wanted to sum out some of the
variables, marginalize them. Now we're
going to, to, what to find the argmax
which is the assignment of these variables
which maximizes the product. So here we
have the max. Of a product which is why
this is often called a max product
problem. Let's break down the max product
problem. So imagine that we in more
general have. In more general case have a
probability over y. Given E equal little e.
And [inaudible] remind ourselves that y is
a. Is the set of all variables. Other than
the ones in e. And so by the definition of
conditional probability. We have this
ratio. Who's what we're trying to find is
the maximal y. The maximize to this
ratio. And notice that the denominator. Is
constant relative to y. Sorry, yes, with
respect to y. Which means that, for the
purpose of finding the maximum y, we don't
really care about the denominator, only
the numerator, which is the probability of
y comma e equals little e, the
unnormalized, an unnormalized measure. The
probabil-, this numerator, in the general
case, is a product of factors normalized
by the partition function, where the
factors here are the reduced factors.
Reduced relative to the evidence. [sound].
Once again we notice, that, this, is the
partition function, and it's constant.
Relative to y. Which means that we can
ignore it. And, so, once again we have
this, the expression is now proportional
to a product of the same reduced factors.
And so what we're trying to do is we're
trying to maximize a product of factors in
this more general case as well. Which
gives us the following as the optimization
problem. There's many algorithms that can
solve the map problem. The first is
analogous to algorithms for sum product.
These algorithms take the maximization
operation, and pushes that into the factor
product. Giving rise to a max product
variable elimination algorithm. We
also have message passing algorithms,
which, again, are a direct analog to
algorithms for sum product. And they give
rise to a class of algorithms called
max product belief propagation.
However, because the map problem is
intrinsically an optimization problem.
One can also call in techniques that are
specific to optimization. And the class of
such methods include methods that are based
on integer programming. Which is a general
class of optimization over discreet
spaces. It turns out that this class of
methods that build on integer programming
techniques is one of the most popular
methods in the last few years. And has
given rise to a whole new range of map algorithms that are considerably better
than in any of the previous algorithms developed up to that point so
especially for the approximate case.
[sound] It also turns out that, for
certain types of networks, that, some of
which we'll discuss, there are specific
algorithms that are very efficient for
that particular class of, of graphical
model. And one of those, perhaps the most
commonly used, but not the only one, is,
methods based on, a class of algorithms
called graph cuts. And. And finally,
because it's a optimization problem one
can also use standard search techniques
over combinatorial search spaces. And
there are problems for which this is also
a very useful and successful solution. So
to summarize, the map problem aims to
find a single coherent assignment of the
highest probability, and that means that
it is not the same as maximizing
individual marginal probabilities as we
saw in the example. One can reformulate
this problem as one of finding the max
over a factor product. And this is a
communitorial optimization problem which
admits a whole range of different
solutions on which are exact and others approximate.