An alternative class of algorithms to the
variable elimination algorithms, is the
class of message passing algorithms. And
as we'll see this is a class that is in
some ways closely related to the variable
elimination, but also offers us additional
flexibility in how we do summation
and factor product steps, so as to
potentially come up with a lower complexity
than would be required by even the minimal
elimination ordering. So let's consider
a simple Markov network of the following
type. And let's assume that I don't want
to go to the cost of eliminating
variables. Although, in this network, it's
not gonna be too expensive. And, instead,
what we're going to do is we're going to
construct what we call a cluster graph.
The cluster graph is something where... it's...
is a data structure in which
we're going to take little bits of
knowledge from this graphical model. And
we're going to place them in things called
clusters. So here we have four clusters.
In this example, cluster one, is a cluster
whose jurisdiction of influence is, the,
the pair of variables AB. Cluster two has
jurisdiction over B and C. Three is over C and
D. And four is over A and D. And these
clusters are going to sit there and
they're going to talk to each other. And
they're going to try and convince each
other that what they think about a
variable that they both consider to be
under their jurisdiction is correct. So
for example, cluster one is going to talk
to cluster two about the variable B and
it's going to tell cluster two what it
thinks about B so that cluster two might
become more informed about the
distribution over B. And so, what we're
going to do is, initially, each cluster is
going to have its own little piece of
information. So Phi 1 is going to go here.
Phi 2 is going to go there. Phi 3 goes there
and Phi 4 goes there. And now the variables
are going to communicate with each other
via these things called messages. So we're
going to call we're going to slightly
rename things. We're going to call the
[inaudible] initial set of beliefs, if you
will, or evidence that a factor that a
cluster has over the variables in its
jurisdiction, we're going to those psi. In
the example were just have psi were just
the phis of the original model but as will
see sometimes it can become a little bit
complicated than that. So now factor...
The cluster one has the factor of psi 1.
And cluster two has psi 2 and so on.
And now lets imagine that psi 1 wants
to send a message. I'm sorry, that psi 2,
that cluster two wants to send a
message to cluster one. So it has to
figure out what it believes. A priori
we're going to assume that its just going
to, we're going to start out by
initializing with a totally uninformed
message. So because initially they haven't
even started talking to each other. So all
messages are initialized to be one. But
now, cluster two can come back and say,
okay. I'm going to take the information,
uninformative as it was, that I got from
cluster two. And notice that I call this
message delta 2,1. Delta, 2 being the
from. And 1 being the to, and so taken
delta 2,1, and now factor one, cluster
one is going to say well I'm going to pick
that and I'm going to multiply it, with my
current, thoughts about the variables A,B
and that's going to give me a more
informed factor and now I'm going to
communicate that information to factor
four, to cluster four. But cluster 4's
doesn't care about a, sorry cluster four
doesn't care about B. And so what I'm
going to communicate to cluster four,
which is this message delta 1,4, from one
to four, is the sum over B, which is the
variable that four doesn't wanna hear
about, of the incoming message. Times my
initial beliefs. For my initial factors.
Now this general process is what keeps the
message passing algorithm going. So each
variable. Each cluster is going to send
messages to its adjacent cluster that
reflect this exact same process. So for
example, just take a different example
here is delta 3-4 so this is the message
that goes from three to four and that
message takes onto consideration the
evidence the two sent to three which is
this guy over here finds whatever three
thought about CD to begin with. Notice,
and this is important, that the message
that three sends to four doesn't take into
consideration, the information that it got
from four. So there isn't in this
expression over here The contribution of
delta 4,3. Because you want to
have, you want to avoid this case of I
repeat back to you a rumor that you just
told me and we all become more convinced
about the truth of this rumor because, oh,
you, I, I thought about this first but now
you're reinforcing me by telling it to me
again and the beliefs are just going to go
up and up. And so what happens here is
that we deliberately only restrict
attention to evidence that comes in from other
sources. So three only uses evidence from
two, when reporting to four. And it only
uses, conversely, evidence from four when
reporting to two. And so now, this is this defines a set a, a communication
protocol by which one factor or one
cluster rather in the graph can
communicate information to its neighbors.
What do we do with this? So how do we
generalize this message passing process?
Let's construct a more general version of
this. So this uses a data structure called
a cluster graph. A cluster graph is an
undirected graph whose nodes are not
variables any more, not as, not in, this
is not a, you know graphical model of the
type that we've seen. The nodes in this
undirected graph are clusters that
correspond to subsets of variables just
like we had before. And we're going to
connect, two adjacent, two clusters, Ci
and Cj. And this, this thing called the
sepset, is the variable that they choose
to talk about. And clearly each one can
only talk about variables that it knows
about which is why the sepset Sij has to
be a subset of both Ci and Cj. So once
again, Ci is the jurisdiction of cluster i,
these are the variables that it
understands, and Sij is the communication
between two adjacent clusters in the
cluster graph. So, now, given a set
of factors Phi, we're going to initialize
the, the model by giving each gra-, each
cluster in the graph a certain amount of
information. So each of my initial
clusters, each of my initial factors phi k,
in my graph, is going to be assigned to
one and only one cluster. And this is
important. It needs to be at least one, so
that the information is taken into account
somewhere. And it shouldn't be more than
one, because if you give it to more than
one person, to more than one cluster,
they're going to, that you're going to
double count the evidence. They're each
going to think it's an independent piece
of evidence, and it's going to be counted
twice. Now where do we put the information
corresponding to factor k? We put this
only in a fact, we can only put it in a
cluster that understands every single
variable in that factor. So if we have a
factor whose scope, has a certain, that
has a certain scope, that scope better be
a subset. Of the variables that the
cluster understands, because otherwise we
can't even talk about those variables. So,
[sound] So once we've done that. See if I
can, erase this. Okay. We can now define
the initial beliefs of a particular
cluster, as the product of all of the
factors that are assigned to it. Now some
variables might, some clusters might be
assigned one factor. In which case psi is
just equal to that phi. Some, because
that, that was the case in the example
that we just saw. Some clusters might have
several factors assigned to them. In which
case we need to multiply them to create a
single factor that is sorta the total
informed beliefs of the cluster. And some
clusters might have no factors assigned to
them. In which case this is a null product
and is equal to one. So now let's look at
an example of the sum of more interesting
cluster graphs than the trivial one that
we showed earlier. Here we have a set of
factors: phi-1 of ABC; phi-2 of BC; phi-3; phi-4;
phi-6 and so on. So initially, we have to
figure out for each of those factors, a
cluster in which to put it. For ABC,
there's really only one choice because
there is only one cluster in this entire
graph that understands about all of A, B
and C, and that is this cluster over here.
BC however, has two choices. It can go
into cluster one, or it can go into
cluster two, because both cluster one and
cluster two understand about B and C. We
are going to put it in cluster two. I mean
you can put it in either one, both are
fine. Phi-3 has again two choices it can go
into cluster two or it can go into cluster
three. We're going to go ahead and make a
decision to put it in cluster two.
Cluster, phi-4, goes, has only, one choice,
because only one cluster has both D and E
in its scope. So it goes here. Phi-5
similarly. Only over here. BD again there
is more that one choice. We could put it
in cluster two or we can put it in cluster
three. Let's, for simplicity, put it in
cluster three, and BDF only one choice.
This is one possible way of assigning the
cluster, the factors to clusters. There is
other alternatives, as I said, that would
work. If we do this we end up, for
example, with psi 2. Being the product
of phi2 times phi3. Where as psi 1 is
simply equal to phi1. And psi3. Is
equal to phi, to phi6 times phi7.
Here is a different assignment of the same
factors to different, to the clusters. And
we can see that it, that it also equally
legitimate. >> Okay this was one cluster
graph for those set of factors. Here's another
cluster graph ... >> So let's compare them
one two one two for different for the
exact same set of factors. Then notice is
that even the clusters have never changed, what
changed is the edges and the sepsets
between them. >> That's in cluster graph. Okay
so now let's think about message passing
in the context of this more richly
structured cluster graph to see what it
looks like here. So here for example if
we're interested in passing a message
from. Cluster one to cluster four. We're
going to take psi 1 which is the factor,
the set of factors that were initially
assigned to cluster four. But we have to
take in the message that this cluster got
from its other neighbor two. We're going
to multiply them together and then we're
going to sum out all of the variables that
one understands but two doesn't. So here
for example, one understands A and C and
two doesn't, so we have to sum out over A
and C. And that is the message delta 1,4. What about Delta 4-1? Delta 4-1 is
the message goes in the other direction.
And here, notice that four gets
messages from all sorts of other
clusters. So in addition to its original
factor of psi 4, it gets a message
from cluster two. It gets a message from
cluster five then it gets a message from
cluster three each over its own scope. All
of these are going to be multiplied
together to give the current, most
informed beliefs about, about the
variables B and E, which are then
marginalizing over E, which cluster one
doesn't understand to produce a message
over B. And once again, we know that the
message from one is not used to inform the
message that four sends back. So that
gives us overall the following expression
for message passing, between cluster i and
cluster j so delta ij, over the scope of
this which is the sepset, Sij and
that has the following general expression.
It takes the factors initially assigned to
cluster i, multiplies in all of the
incoming messages. Other than from j.
Multiply that all together, sums out the
variables that cluster j doesn't know
about. So everything that's in the scope
of Ci, but not in the scope of Cj. And
that gives us a factor over the sepset
that is produced as a message. So putting
that together that gives us an algorithm
which is generally called belief
propagation for the reasons that the
clusters are propagating, if you will,
informed beliefs to each other. And here
is the summary of the algorithm. Each
factor phi is first assigned to a cluster.
That is used to construct our initial
potentials. These psi's that we talked
about. We initialize all of the messages
before anybody starts communicating to be 1.
And then we repeat the following process.
We select some edge in the graph between
adjacent clusters and we pass the message
between cluster i and cluster j over that
edge. Okay? And we repeatedly and this is
the expression for that message. It's the
one that we saw on the previous slide. And
that process is repeated again and again.
At the end of the process, we, now, a
cluster needs to know what to believe
about the variables that it understands.
And so it takes all of the it takes its
own initial beliefs, and all of the
information that it got from all of its
neighbors. Multiplies it all together and
that produces these things which are called
beliefs. Now there's several important,
aspects of this algorithm that are left
undefined. And that we're gonna need to
talk about, later on. The first of these
is repeat until when? When do we decide
that we're done, and that we can stop? And
we'll talk about that in the context of
different variants of this algorithm,
later on. The second thing that's left
undefined is how I select each of the
edges, how do I select the edges, which
edge do I select to pass messages over? So
here there is, you know, the obvious
simple thing, which is just to go in some
prespecified order and that's one option,
is round robin message passing. But it
turns out that there are better strategies
than that and we'll talk about that too.
So, is this algorithm any good? Well, it
turns out that, you know, yes and no. So
first of all, if you pass messages over a
graph like the one that I showed before.
Like, the, you know, little A, B, C, D
loop. Eventually, you see that we achieve
convergence. So this is, here we can see
that, eventually, we do converge to some
probability. But, that probability is a
little bit off. That is, the answer is not
exact. Now in general, with exceptions
that we'll talk about, this is an
approximate algorithm. Which shows that
there's no free lunch. The problem was
NP hard, it's not like I have an easy
way of solving it. So given all these
problems with the belief propagation
algorithm, what makes us think that it's
an effective algorithm to use? When the
algorithm was. [inaudible] discovered in
the 1990s Murphy, Weiss, and Jordan, as
well as others looked at its performance
in the context of real networks and
specifically networks that have a lot of
loops, which is what causes [inaudible] to
misbehave. And so here is an example
network. It's, it's called the pyramid
network. It's a network that is analogous
to one that arises in image analysis. And
what we, what they showed is that when you
compute on the one hand the exact
marginals. On the X axis. And for
different marginals in the network. And on
the Y axis, we see the marginals computed
by loopy belief propagation. We see
that the marginals, by and large, sit
almost exactly on a straight line, with
few exceptions. So you'll see that the
loopy belief propagation is very close to
accurate on this network. Here's another
network, this is a simplified version of a
medical diagnostic network and once again
you can see that the when it compared the
correct marginal on the x axis to the
belief propagation marginals on y axis,
the marginal fit almost exactly on
straight line which shows that again
they're very close... The propagation is
very close to accuracy. So, to summarize,
the belief propagation algorithm passes
messages over a graph of clusters that are
connected to each other via sepsets. The
adjacent clusters pass information to each
other in these messages transmitting
information only about the variables in
the sepset which are the ones that they
have in common. The message that cluster-i
sends to cluster-j, summarizes everything
that a i knows about the variables in the
sepset, except for information that it
obtains from j, so that one avoid direct
double counting of the same piece of
evidence where j gets his own information
back again by i. We've seen that the
algorithm may not converge. And it can have
this oscillatory behavior, And that the
resulting beliefs are pseudo-marginals, in
that they are not necessarily the exact
marginals from a theoretical perspective.
But nevertheless, as we've seen, the
algorithm actually performs quite well in
a range of practical applications, which
is why it's quite commonly used.