We previously defined the map inference
problem, which is that of finding the,
highest probability assignment to a
graphical model. And we talked about
particular classes of models for which the
map problem was tractable. One was a class
that, of models that had sufficiently low
tree width. So that one could use
techniques such as variable elimination or
clique tree methods. And then we also
talked about a variety of other special
purpose classes where one could do
tractable inference. We are going to talk
about now is a general purpose algorithm
that can be used to solve any MAP
problem, keeping in mind of course that
the MAP problem is an NP-hard
problem, so you're not going to get a
fully polynomial time algorithm that, that
one can utilizes in the context of any
problem. So the class of methods that
we're going to talk about is in, is called
Dual Decomposition. And it's derived from
the increasingly prevalent view of the MAP
inference problem as an optimization
problem and building on techniques from
the field of optimization theory. Let's go
ahead and first reformulate the problem in
a way that makes it amenable to this kind
of analysis and this is just a convenience
so here we are going to assume that the
MAP problem that we are trying to optimize
remember we've reformulated this
as a max sum as opposed to a max product
which is a convenient reformulation and we
are going to assume that the data that we
are trying to optimize is comprised of a sum
of two different kinds of factors. The
first is singleton factors. Which are over
the scope of single variable XI and the
second are larger factors that are over
the scope of multiple variables.
And clearly one can fold in the singleton
factors into some larger factor that
contains a variable in its scope but it
turns out to be convenient to keep them in
the model for reasons that will become
clear in a minute. So now our goal is to
find the value for the moment. We're going
to talk about how to find an actual
assignment in a little bit, but imagine
that our goal is to just figure out what
is the value of the highest probability
assignment X. And so we're trying to find
the X that maximizes this total summation.
One thing that we could do, which would be
wrong, but we could do it, is to say,
well, let's forget about the fact that
we're trying to do a single joint
assignment. Rather, we're going to think
about each problem with blinders on. So
we're going to think about, each theta I,
XI, by itself. And we're going to find the
XI that optimizes that, factor. And we're
going to do the same for the larger
factors. Now, that of course is going to
be a very poor solution because the XI
that going to optimize one data I, Is going to be
completely inconsistent with the Xi that is selected by
one of the larger factors that contains XI.
So, you're going to get a completely incoherent joint
assignment. It's not going to be a joint assignment.
It's going to be a bunch of different assignments
that don't that don't agree with each
other. So, what dual decomposition does is
it's going to try and do the same kind of
divide and conquer, but it's going to do
it in a way that tries to force these
local decision-making problems to agree
with each other. And so how are we going
to do that. We are going to do that by
introducing a set of costs. And the costs
are going to be things that are going to
drive each of these local problems to
hopefully, eventually agree with the
decisions made in other local problems. So
going back to this, what we're going to
do, and now this is actually an equality.
Is, we're going to do the following. For
the variable I, we have its own local
potential, theta I. And then we have a
bunch of costs. And these are the costs
that are derived from the [inaudible], and
we have a cost for each factor F that
contains I in its scope. And that cost is
going to try and pull the little I,
decision maker, which is called the slave,
by the way. Each of these decision
problems is called a slave. So this is the
I slave. And here is a little term that's
suppose to pull the i slave, to agree
with the decision made in factor f.
Similarly, we have an F slave. And what
we're trying to do, is we're trying to get
the F slave to agree with the i slaves.
For the variable Xi and its scope. Now, as
written over here, let's convince
ourselves that this expression is, in
fact, equal to the first line. And then
reason is that, here, I add a term, lambda
FI of XI, for I in the scope of F. And
here, I subtract that same expression over
here. So each of these expressions, lambda
FI gets added in at I, and subtracted out
at F. And so they cancel out. So far, I've
had equality. But now, I'm going to really
let each agent make their own decision. So
now, before, there was still the
maximization on the outside. Now I'm going
to let each agent look at its little set
of factors, that, it owns. Including the
sort of penalty terms that it has in, in
order to agree with the other slaves. And
each one is going to make its separate
optimization with all of those terms
together. So, you can think of these,
these penalty terms as messages from, or
between, F and I. Their, their way to
communicate. For F to communicate to I
what it thinks ought to be done and for I
to communicate with F at the same time.
Now one important point that we'll come
back to, in a little bit, is that this,
function here which is called L of Lambda,
notice that this is a function of Lambda.
And only a function of lambda because it's
no longer a function of x because of
maximize over the x. So you're going to
get a different value of this function
depending on the choices of the penalty
parameters. This function is an upper
bound on max theta for any value of
lambda. Now let's understand why that is.
It's, we've seen in this line over here
that this is actually equal to that.
Anyways, we've shown that everything
cancels here. And what I've done here is,
over here, I'm forcing a single X to
maximize this entire expression together.
And here, I'm letting each term be
optimized separately. And that give me
more degrees of freedom, because here I
have to pick the same x across the board,
and here this one gets to pick one x and
this one get to pick another value of x.
And so since, the assignment where they
all agree is a, is one of the assignments
that can be consider in this optimization
problem over here. The overall value that
can be gained is only higher than if I had
to force them all to agree which is a more
constrained optimization problem. In
general, the more constraints I have on
the space that I'm optimizing the lower
the value that I, the lower the value that
I can get. So introducing some notation
which we'll use in a little, which we'll
use in the rest of this presentation,
we're going to call the function that the
I slave is optimizing, theta I lambda. And
the function that is being optimized by
the F slave, theta F lambda. So let's take
an example to make this a little bit more
concrete because this was a little bit
abstract. So let's go back to our to, to
our example of a four way loop where we
have X1, X2, X3, and X4 and we're going to
have these four pairwise potentials
which we're going to denote with letters
this time to disambiguate indices a little
bit. So we have theta F of X1, X2, theta G
of X2, X3, theta H, and theta K. So, now
how is this decomposition going to work
here? Let's assume for the moment that
we're going to decompose this over edges.
So our factors are going to be, for
example, the edge X1, X2. So now what is
the optimization problem that this factor
chooses? Well it has its own potential,
say the f x1, x2, and then it's going to
have these little costs that are going to
try and get it to agree with x1 on the,
with the one slave on x1 and the two slave
on x2. We're similarly going to have, for
x1x4, this is the k, so this is the f
slave. This is the k slave. And it's going
to have its own potential, theta K. And
two penalty terms that are going to try to
make, to make it agree with the one slave
on X1, and the four slaves on X4. And we
similarly have exactly the same form for
the other two, slaves, the G slave and the
H slave. In addition, we have slaves for
the individual variables, the one, two,
three, four slaves. So here is the one
slave. And notice that the one slave has
its own potential theta one, X1. And at
the same time, it has these two terms that
are trying to make it agree on the one
side with F, which is over here. So this
is because of this. And on the other side
with K, because of that. And the same
thing applies to the other slaves, so the
two slave for example, is going to agree
with F. And is going to try to be, is
going to be [inaudible] with F and with G,
so it has a lambda F2 and a lambda G2. Now
I've done this in the context of a very
simple scenario where I've broken up my
model into the factors that existed in the
original specification. So, for example I
had factors that were pair wise
potentials. I had a slave for each such
factor. But that doesn't have to be the
case. [cough] In fact, the only constraint
that I need to satisfy is that I need the
sl, to define a slave to be defined as a
subset of factors that admit a tractable
solution. So that each one can be
optimized. Efficiently, when considered in
isolation. So, for example if we can, if
we'll return to this network, say one
thing we could do is, we can introduce two
larger slaves, instead of the four smaller
FGKH slaves, which one is corresponding to
F and G together so this is the FG slave.
And the other one, representing the k, the
KH slave. And, in this case, if we think
about the agreement, we still have the
one, two, three, four slaves that
represent the individual variables. And so
now we're going to have to require that
theta F agrees with X1, with the one slave
on X1, with a two slave on X2, and with a
three slave on X3. And so we have this
expression, which has a lambda term for
each of those three variables. And we have
a similar term for a similar expression
for the KH slave, where in this case, the
KH slave has to agree with the one slave
on X1, the four slave on X4, and the three
slave on X3. If we now think about the
singleton slaves, for example X1, we see
that X1 has to agree with the FG slave, so
there's a term to encourage that, and with
the KH slave because it's present in both.
On the other hand, the X2 variable only
occurs in the first slave and so it only
has a single agreement term with the FG
slave. And similarly for x3 and x4. So,
how do we then construct the slaves? In
pair wise networks, what we typically do
is we divide the factors into a set of
disjoint trees. And this is in fact what I
showed in the previous slide. We divided
it into one tree that went through the
first wedges, and a second one that went
through the second wedges. And then, and
these, and they are destroying such means
as every edge is assigned to exactly one
tree. And because they're trees we know
how to optimize in efficiency using
[inaudible], [inaudible], [inaudible]
variation or [inaudible] tree. But we also
discuss that there is other classes of
factors that are, that offer tractable
inference. So for example, we talked about
matching, or models that are
associative, or regular, or super modular,
or whatever we call them. And all of these
are tractable classes we can take a whole
bunch of factors that satis, that, that
fit into one of these tractable categories
and optimize them together in one svelte
swoop. We don't need to divide into
separate edges. So let's look at an
example of this. Remember a while ago, we
talked about the problem of 3D cell
reconstruction, where we have a, a cell
over here that we're imaging. And we're
taking various images that are slices, two
dimensional slices through that cell. And
we'd like to reconstruct three dimensional
structure. So here as, as we discussed, we
have the slices and we would like to
correspond the beads, that we see, this
little gold beads that we see and these
different images to each other. So try to
figure out that this bead corresponds to
the bead over there. And from that we can,
then subsequently. Obtain the 3D
reconstruction. Now when we last talked
about this we described this as a matching
problem, where the matching waits between
a point here and the point here. Are
derived from the similarity of both the
location and the 2D slice, and the
appearance of the local neighborhood. But
it turns out that neither of these is
sufficiently distinctive in order to
really make that determination robustly
that one point in an image matches another
point in the other image. And so in order
to do this with a reasonable success we
need to have another set of potentials
which are pair wise potentials. Which
basically preserved distances of these
marker positions. So tell us that if we
had, if we want to correspond this point
over here to this point, and this point to
that point, then the distances between
them. Should also roughly be preserved.
Now, this set of potentials is relatively
sparse and therefore can be solved usually
using exact difference, this set of
potentials is not complicated on its own,
cause it's a matching problem. If you put
them together it turns out to be a
difficult problem to solve. In fact you
could show that a joint set of potentials
like this, with these two different
categories is in general [inaudible] but
using dual decomposition we can solve each
of these separately. And then communicate
information between them. So each of these
would form a tractable slave.