One of the most generally useful class of
sampling methods is one that's very
commonly used in practice, is the class of
Markov chain Monte-Carlo methods. And those are
methods that allow us to design an
iterative sampling process that, through a
sequence of steps, allows us to generate a
sample from a desired target distribution
that might be intractable to sample from
directly. So what are these Markov chains,
and how do you how do you use them? So. A
Markov chain is a, is a method for sampling
from a distribution P That is intractable
to sample from. And so we've seen one
example such a distribution P. If you'd
like to sample from a distri-, from a,
say, a Bayesian network, where we have
some evidence we don't really know-how to
sample from that. If you'd like to sample
from a Markov network, we don't really
know how to sample from that either, in
general. And so, here we have examples of
distributions P, and we'd like to come up
with a way of generating even one example
from the distribution P. So markup chain
gives us a general mechanism for doing
that. And what the markup chain does is,
it defines an iterative process by which
the first sample that you generate is not
going to be from a distribution p, but
ultimately as you move along. You are
going to get closer and closer to
generating a sample from p so. So let's
understand what that Mm-hm, what that
means. Hm, so we have a mark up chain and
the mark up chain is defined over a state
space which we are going to use X's to
denote. And so here's an example of such a
state space. This is a very simple state
space. It starts with the zero point over
here, and you could imagine it has four
negative numbers to the left and four
positive numbers to the right. And a markov
chain defines a probabilistic transition model,
which given that I'm at a given state x, tells me
how likely I am to transition to a different state x prime.
And that is the probability distribution
as indicated in this formula here, so that's for any x, the
probability, the sum over the probability
of states to which you can transition is
exactly one. So, for example, if, in this
case, we have our little grass,
grasshopper who starts out at state zero,
we can see that it has a probability of
0.25 of transitioning to the right. A
probability of 0.25 of transitioning to
the left. And a probability of 0.5 of not
making any progress, and staying exactly
where it is. And, in fact, that
same general probability distribution is
actually, in this example, replicated
across the different states in the chain,
with the exception of the states at the
end, where, if the poor grasshopper tries
to go to the left when it's at - four,
it's going to hit the wall, and it's going
to end up staying where it is, regardless.
And so the probability in this case of
staying is actually 0.75 corresponding to
the two different cases that we just
talked about. But anyway, this is a
Markov chain, and it's, and you can
imagine. Simulating a random process by
which a grasshopper traverses the chain.
And so initially it starts out with, let's
say state zero and then, and then what
happens as it moves, it selects to move
left with probability a quarter, right
with probability a quarter and, and stay
the same place with probability 0.5. Once
the [inaudible] moves it the left, it now
does exactly the same thing. So let's
think about the temporal dynamics of this
type of process. We can ask what is the
probability that a time, that a step P
plus one, this is a step. What is the
probability that at that time step, the
state at time T plus one is equal to some
value X prime? So we can get that by a
recurrence relationship that looks at the
state of time T. So if we had previously
computed the probability distribution over
where the grasshopper might be at time T.
We can sum up over all possible states
where X, where the grasshopper might be
and asked if it was at, at state X at time
T, what is the probability that it ends up
with being, that it ends up going to X
prime. So this, together gives me a
distributional repairs. X comma X prime.
Where this, which, which measure the
probability that at the time T the
grasshopper is at state X and the T+1 is
at X prime. And since I'm only interested
now in asking about T+1, I sum up or
marginalize the time key step state X. So
to go back to our grasshopper example, we
can simulate this process and here is the
first three steps of this. So, at time
zero, the grasshopper is at state zero
with probability one. At time one, it's
going to be if -one with probability a
quarter and if it's +one with probability
a quarter, probability half it's stuck. At
the same state. And now we can simulate
the next step. So it's, at the next time
step the probability that it moves,
manages to move all the way to negative
two is.25 squared because it considers two
successful moves to the left. Here you
have two successful moves to the right. >>
At state zero you have e.g. A sum of
different events which is the probability
that it stayed in the same state twice,
so.5 squared plus the two events that
correspond to moving to left one and back
to the right, one moving to the right and
that the left each of which happens would
probability.25 squared. So this is the
example how you do this. Now it turns out
that for many of these chains, and we'll
describe conditions in a moment
ultimately as the process evolves, the
probability distribution kinda equalizes,
which means that the probability that at
time t, here at state x prime, is
almost the same as the probability that at
time t plus one here at x prime. So,
sorta a kind of distribution over where
you might be past the equalize. And, and
so we can then consider what's called the
limiting process, the limiting
distribution you would get as you simulate
the process for more and more steps. And
that is typically denoted by pi, which is
called the stationary distribution. It
also has a bunch of other names but
stationary is the most common. And if you
plug in. You see basically take out this
approximate equality and you can see that
what we have is a condition on pie, is
that the distribution at one
time step is needs to be the, the
probability of x prime and the stationary
distribution needs to be equal to the
summation over here, where pie now appears
both in the left-hand side and within the
summation on the right-hand side. Now it
turns out that this concept of a
stationary distribution is actually at the
heart of Google's PageRank algorithm. So
what they're actually computing, at least
in the original PageRank, is the
probability that if you take a random walk
on the web that you end up at a particular
website. So this notion of a stationary
distribution is actually quite powerful,
as we've seen. So lets take a simple
example which is this three state
markup chain shown here. So for example note
that from state one there's a probability
of 0.75 we are going to state two and 0.25
we're going to stay in the same state. And
we can now write down a set of equations
that represent, what the fixed, what
properties the fixed-point distribution
needs to satisfy. And if you do that
you're going to get the following
equations. So, for example it tells me
that pi of X1 Has to be equal to 0.25
times 5x1 because soft transition here
plus oops zero. Yes, sorry pi of x1 is
equal to 0.25 times pi of X1 + 0.5 times
pi of X3. Because there, if you were to pi
that you can end up in X one in one of two
ways. Either by starting on X one and
staying there, or by starting out at X
three and moving to X one which happens
with probability 0.5. Similarly, at Pi(x2)
you can end up either by being at X2
and staying there, which is this
transition. Or, by being at X3 and moving
to X2, which happens with probability 0.5.
And, so, this is a set of three
simultaneous equations and three
variables. This by itself is an under
determined system because you can multiply
all of the Pi's by a factor of a 100 and
it would still, be a solution, but we can
add to that the one constraint that says
that all of the Pi's have to be, equal.
The sum of all the Pi's has to be one,
which, is because of the probability
distribution and once you do that, you end
up with a unique solution, to the system
of linear equations and its not difficult
to plug those Pi's into the system and
confirm that indeed this is the stationary
distribution, that satisfies these
equations. By the way, through the
grasshopper example that we showed on the
previous slide the stationary distribution
is the uniform distribution, so this has
to be one of the dumbest ways of
generating a sample from the uniform
distribution. But, it does in fact
generate eventually a sample from
something that is very close to uniform
distribution. So, when does a Markov chain
converge to a stationary distribution? I
said, many of them do but, it turns out
that not all of them. And, so, a condition
that guarantees convergence to a
stationary distribution is something
called regularity. So, a Markov chain is
regular. If the following condition holds,
and notice the order of the quantifiers.
If there exists some number K, integer K,
such that, for every pair of states. So
this is the universal quantifier. The
probability of getting from X to X prime
in exactly K steps is greater than 0.
Now notice what that means. It means that
you pick the k first. And, and only and,
and so you can't have a different k for
different pairs of states. You can pick k
to be 1,000 or a million, it doesn't
matter for this purpose. But you need to
pick it first and then there needs to be a
way of getting from x to x prime in
exactly that number of steps with
probability greater than zero. It turns
out that, that is a sufficient, not a
necessary but a sufficient condition to
guarantee that the Markov Chain converges
to a unique stationary distribution
regardless of its start state. So it
converges and it converges to a single
stationary distribution that's
characterized by the equation that we saw
on the previous slide. Now, what are some
sufficient conditions for regularity
because this one is a little bit hard to
check and so one sufficient condition for
regularity that people often use in
practice, is first that every pair of
states X and X prime need to be connected
with a path of probability greater than
one, sorry with probability greater than
zero. And, for every state there is a
self-transition. So you can always
transition from a state to itself. So if
you think about that, that means that if
you take K to be, the diameter of this
graph, so if you set K to be, the, the
distance, between the furthest. Pair of
states. Then, you can get between every
pair of states using exactly k steps
because you can take less than k and then
just stick around for a while until you
hit k, because of self-transitions. So
this is a way of guaranteeing, that, that
for this value K, you can get from every
state, every state. And that's what
people typically do, they typically add
these self transitions to guarantee
regularity. So to summarize we've
defined the notion of a Markov chain,
which defines a general dynamical system,
or an iterative sampling process from
which we can sample trajectories that
traverse the space of the chain. Under
certain conditions, such as the regularity
condition that we defined, which is
sufficient, although not necessary. This
iterative sampling process is guaranteed
to converge to a stationary distribution
at, at the limit. That is, after we
generate enough samples. And so this
provides us with a general approach to
sample from a distribution indirectly.
Which means that if we have a distribution
from which it's intractable to sample,
this provides us with an alternative.