A very different paradigm to
inference and graphic model, is the use of
whats called sampling or particle based
methods, in those methods rather than
trying to manipulate the exponentially,
even infinitely large probability
distribution as a whole we randomly
sample, instan-, instances from that
distributions and then use those instances
as a sparse representation we can use
those instances then to estimate various
quantities that we care about regarding
the statistics of the overall
distribution, before we show how this is
use in the context of graphical models, let's
go ahead and see how it's
applied in a simple setting. So first of
all, how do we use samples for estimating
quantities that we care about? So, imagine
that. Somehow and we're gonna talk about
how that might happen. Somebody gives us
or we manage to construct a dataset D
which consists of a bunch of samples from
a distribution P. And for the moment we're
going to assume that these samples are
what's called iid, which stands for
independent, and identically distributed.
So that's where the "i.i.d" comes from. And
now let's imagine that we're trying to
compute or estimate and this is all going
to be approximate, approximate some-, a
quantity of the, of the distribution P.
And so for the moment let's focus on
really simple case where we trying to
figure out where these are binary valued
random variables so the distribution P
that were sampling from is. One where the
probability that one equals one is P, and
so think of this as tossing a coin. Now
what is a reasonable estimator for this
parameter, P? That we're trying to
estimate. The probability that X falls
heads. Well this is fairly a intuitive
answer here. This estimator which we are
going to call T -sub- D, Is simply
obtained by looking at all of these
samples that we got and counting the
fraction of one. And if you think about
it, that's a perfectly reasonable
approximation, hm? Now more generally, for
any distribution P, and any function F
whose statistics we're trying to estimate,
we can approximate the expectation of the
function F relative to the distribution P,
in terms of this weighted average of the
value F. On the sample. And this is often
called the empirical expectation. So this
is how we might have, if we had some way,
which we have not yet talked about of
constructing or sampling from
distribution, how we might use those
samples for approximating various
properties, relative to the distribution
p, whether it's a probability of an event
or the expectation of a function and know
by the way that the expectation of the
function subsumes the probability of an
even because you can also take the
expectation for example an indicator
function, and that correspond directly.
With probability. So for example this
probability can be viewed as the
expectation relative to P of the indicator
function representing X equals one. The
function that takes one, when x equals one
and zero otherwise. So, let's think for a
moment, just to be concrete about how one
might go about sampling from a discrete
distribution. So imagine that we have a
discrete random variable X that takes
on K values, X1 up to XK, and let's assume
that each of these has the XI occurs with
probability theta I. And so we have theta
one up to theta K. How might we go about
using computational tools to generate
samples from this distribution? Well, most
computers give us a random-number
generator function that generates samples
uniformly. In the interval zero one. And
so if we wanted to convert that into
something that samples from this discrete
distribution. The simplest way of doing
that is to basically split up the range
and make this point say theta one, this
point theta one plus two. theta-1, plus
theta-2, plus theta-3, and let's leave it
at that. So four values of the random
variable. And now we toss, we use the
random number function to sample from this
space, so let's say it comes out here and
we basically say okay, this was the range
that corresponds to X1, X2, this is X3 and
this is X4 and so since the point fell
here, I'm going to declare that my random
number, that my random value is X3. I
sample again, and I sample in this, this
point over here. I'm gonna say oh, okay,
excellent. So that's how you would use a
random number generator to sample from a
discrete distribution, something that
we're gonna end up using a lot later in
this lecture. [sound]. So, now that we
know how to sample. Let's think about how
you might. What are some properties of
sampling based estimation? And it turns
out that sampling based estimation is, has
some, what appear to be initially some
very compelling performance guarantees.
So, the first that I'll show is something
that is called the Hoeffding bound. And
let's parse this horribly complicated
statement that we see over here. So, first
of all let's go in, let's work from the
inside out. This says my estimator, which
is Td, remember this is my estimator for
p. And this says. Is, epsilon away, is
more than epsilon away, from P. So this
has, I am badly wrong, my estimator is not
close to the true value which is p. Okay. I
am at least Epsilon away in one side or
the other. Now notice that this is a
property, of the data set. The, the set of
samples that I generated. One set of
samples is gonna give me one estimate, and
different set of samples is going to give
me a different estimate. So that brings us
to the next layer out, which is, this data
set is not a fixed quantity. It's sampled
randomly from the distribution. And so, I
might get good data sets. Data sets where
the estimator is close to P. And I might
get data sets where the estimator is far
from P. So this says, what is the
probability. Of a bad data set. For a
sample set. Okay. So what, so that parses
the left hand side. The right hand side is
a bound on this probability of getting a
bad dataset, a dataset where the resulting
estimator is highly inaccurate. So we can
see that, that probability grows
exponentially, shrinks rather
exponentially, in the number of samples M.
On the other hand, it also shrinks with
epsilon. So the higher, the lower the
tolerance that we have for errors, the
higher the probability of making an error
of that magnitude. So if we need really,
really tight bounds, then that we're not
going to get that with very high
probability. Nevertheless, something a
probability that shrinks exponentially
with a number of samples looks really
good, right? The second bound that has a
very similar form is the Chernoff bound.
And the Chernoff bound has exactly that
same composition. So here is our estimator
again. And, here this is epsilon-away from
p. But whereas this was an additive. This
is an additive distance. This is a
multiplicative distance. So this is p
times one minus epsilon and is the lower
bound and p times one plus epsilon is the
upper bound. And once again this is the
probability of getting a sample that, a
bad sample set. And once again, we have an
exponential, we have an, a bound on the
error, which is written over here. And
once again, the number of samples appears
in the exponent, that makes us happy. We
have the same type of epsilon squared
term, that shows the, the dependence on
the tolerance that's required. But here we
have this one other term over here, which
is. The actual value P to which we're
trying, that we're trying to estimate. So,
if we can give you a bound on the error
that you get. The, this bound on, on how
far away you are for P. A bound on the
tolerance epsilon, and that also
bound on the probability with which we get
a bad sample set. We can now say, for
given tolerance that we want. I'm sorry,
for given error probability that we want.
That is, How, if we want to guarantee that
we're within epsilon with probability
that's greater than one minus delta we
need this many samples. And that's fairly
straightforward algebra. You simply say,
this is less than or delta, and then you
just take logs and move things around, and
it all comes out to be exactly this. And
for the Chernoff bound, we have a similar
expression. And, that gives us exactly
that same kind of bound on M as a function
of epsilon and delta. And in this case, P
as well. So that looks great, right? We
can give you, you give me an epsilon,
which is your error tolerance and a delta
which is the probability with which you're
willing to take being wrong and I can say
if you can only sample these many samples
m then I can give you those probabilistic
guarantee. They're not deterministic but
they're a bit, pretty solid. Why is this
not a perfect solution to our inference
problems?'Cause each of these has
significant limitations. So, let's think
about the first, which is our additive
bound. And let's imagine that you're going
into a doctor, and you're saying, you
know. What is the probability that I have
some horrible disease? Well, that
probability, hopefully for you, is still
pretty low. So maybe, if you're unlucky,
it's, I don't know, it's 1%, 2%. Well
an additive error Epsilon on 1%. The
[inaudible], the Epsilon that you need, to
get something that's meaningfully bounded
when the true probability P is 1%. That
case really, really small. You can't do x1
equals 0.01 because that could move you up
from 1% to 2%. And that's the
factor of two increase in your probability
and that something that people really care
about the difference between one percent
and 2%. So you need something more like
0.0001, or may be 00001 depending on you
know, how confident you wanted to feel.
And now this epsilon squared. Over here
we're beginning to look pretty, pretty
scary, in terms of the number of samples
that are required in order to get a
reasonable bound. So you might come and
say well fine, let's use the Chernoff bound,
because that gives me relative errors on
epsilon. Right? so now if epsilon is
sorry, sorry p. So if now p is small then
by all means I can go ahead and just you
know have a it's a multiplicative factor
of p so I can say p plus or minus one
percent of p. Well, unfortunately there's
no free lunch because if p is small notice
that it appears here in the denominator
and so once again we need a number of
samples that could potentially be quite
large when we're dealing with small
probabilities. So the main message from
this, is that sampling-based estimation is a
reasonable thing to do when P is not too
small? When P's not too small, this works
fine. When P begins to get smaller. We,
this, the, the tractability of this is
more in doubt. Now that we understand when
we might expect this to work, let's think
about how we might apply it in the context
of Bayesian networks. So here is our
little baby network that we've used for
the student example. And what we'd like to
do is we'd like to generate samples from
this distribution. So this a distribution
of, remember, P of D, I, G, S, L. And we'd
like to sample from this high dimensional
distribution. Not that high, but still. And
the way in which this is done, is actually
very natural. When you think about the
sort of causal intuitions or forward flow
of a Bayesian network. We start out say,
by sampling the difficulty variable. And,
the difficulty variable sampled from this
distribution over here which is 0.6 versus
0.4. And so, we use the trick we showed a
couple of slides ago. And say it comes out
d0. We then write d0 over here.
Now, I'm going to sample I, and I'm going
to toss a coin with probability 0.7-0.3,
and say it comes out, i1. Now I get the
sample grade. And because I previously
sampled difficulty and intelligence I know
exactly what distribution grade needs to
be sampled from. It's the distribution i1
d0. And, so, I now sample one of the three
values of grade from the distribution in
this row that I've picked out in the cpd
and say it comes out g1. And I proceed to
do the same so S is sampled from this
distribution. And say it comes out say,
s0. And G is, sorry, L is sampled from
this distribution and say it comes out L1.
And that's a sample. And I can do the
whole thing all over again. And, so I can
go ahead and. Erase all of the decision
that I made before, and I can do the exact
same thing so the blue sample might end up
for example, where d1, i1 or I'll use this
distribution and I'm going to end up say
up g2 and I'm using this distribution,
take this one, and I use this distribution
and I get i0. And I can use this
procedure to generate, as many samples as
I want, using a very efficient forward
sampling process where I sample, in what's
called topological order. Topological
means that I start from the roots and I go
down. And I always sample parents before
their children. And so if I want to use
this process, which is very naturally
called forward sampling. Where we say,
want to compute, to estimate the
probability of some assignment, little y,
to some set of query variables Y. Then
what we're going to do is we're going to
generate a bunch of samples from that
bayes net. As many as we think is, is
adequate. And then, if I'm interested in
some particular event, then I simply
compute the fraction of my samples,
fraction of samples. Where Y equals Y. And
I can use that same procedure for
computing other expectations. So whenever,
if, if I have any other function of the
sample, I can compute the sample, function
on that sample and then average it out in
exactly the same way that we showed on the
first slide. And now we can go ahead and
apply the bounds that we showed before. So
for an additive bound we have this many
samples that we need. And for a
multiplicative bound we have this many
samples that we need. And these are just
copying over the two bounds that we showed
before. So, that's great. But that notice
gave me queries without evidence. And what
do we do if we want to now ask a question,
not just about but the probability of Y
but the probability of Y given some
evidence E = e? Well so now, it's not that
easy to sample from a Bayesian network, if
I have evidence that's not at the root. If
I have evidence to the roots, then that's
fine I know the value of that variable and
I just stick that in and ignore it. You
know everything else. But if I have a
variable where that I observed someone in
the middle, on the bottom of the network.
Then what happens when I get there? Do I
sample it, do I ignore it? I mean it seems
a bit unclear. And so the simple solution
that, and we'll talk about others, is an
algorithm that's called rejection
sampling. And what it does, is it does the
most naive thing that you could possibly
imagine. I generate samples from a Bayes
net, and then if they don't agree with my
evidence I throw'em out. And that course.
The remaining samples. So the remaining
sample after I throw out. All of the ones
that are inconsistent with my evidence are
actually sampled from the conditional
distribution. Because this is the same as
basically, reducing the distribution to
sort of ignore the parts that are not
consistent with my evidence. So that's
great, because now I have samples from the
right distribution. And once I have
samples from the right distribution, I can
go ahead and compute the fraction where
Y=little y, or, for that matter, any other
expectation that I care about. Good!
What's the problem with this? Think about
how likely I am to keep a sample. A sample
is going to be consistent with the
evidence with the probability which is the
probability of the evidence. [inaudible]
that's sort of the definition. So the expected
number, the expected fraction of samples
that I keep is exactly P(e). So now let's
go back to, for example, a medical
diagnosis setting, or, or, for that
matter, the, the, the message decoding
example that we talked about previously.
How likely is your average evidence? So
let's think about medical diagnosis. A
person comes in, and they have their age,
and their weight, and their gender, and,
you know, 32 symptoms, and ten test
results. And, you know, the fact that they
were, they went on a trip to Europe last
week. And all of these are pieces of
evidence, and the question is
how likely is that configuration of
evidence? And the answer is vanishingly
small. How likely is your random person
off the street to exhibit this exact
combination? Almost none. And similarly with
a message example. How likely is, are you
to get a particular configuration of noisy
bits? Well, exponentially small also. So,
the number of samples needed grows
(supposed to be grows) exponentially with
the number of observed variables. The more
numbers you observe the lower the
probability of the evidence. And this is
an exponential decay. And so that means
that, if you observe more than a couple of
variables basically this is not a good
algorithm. So to summarize, algorithm
produces very simple procedure. It's very
easy to generate samples for a Bayesian
network and we showed how all these pieces
fit together. And once you've done
that there's really elegant and
theoretically compelling epsilon-delta
bounds as we've shown before. But their
usefulness, unfortunately is limited. The
additive bounds tend to be useless for low
probability events. The multiplicative,
multiplicative bounds are not good either
because the number of samples grows. As a
function of one over the probability of
the event that we're trying to estimate.
And all this is completely irrelevant as
soon as you have evidence because as soon
as you have evidence the number of
required samples grows exponentially with
the number of observed variables. Which
means this is not a feasible solution for
most practical settings. And one final
note that's worth highlighting, this is
the only case in, I think this, the entire
section on inference where I talked about
Bayesian networks specifically and that is
because, because forward sampling unlike
any of the other inference algorithms that
we are going to talk about is just not
feasible for Markov networks because
there's no, you know, there is no notion
of starting at the root. There is no root.
There is no sort of any variable that you
would naturally start with whose
probability you actually know. And so we
don't apply forward sampling to Markov
networks.