So previously we defined the clique tree
algorithm which is just the belief propagation
algorithm run over a graph that happens to
be a tree. As it turns out, we can exploit
the aspects of the tree to greatly improve
the computational behavior of this
algorithm, not just its correctness which
is what we've showed before. So let's go back for [inaudible
message passing in this very simple
tree which has just these four clusters
ab, bc, cd, de, and lets see what the
messages do. So here is the message delta1-2
which is the message that is
passed on this edge. And here's the
message delta2-3 and so on. And these are
the six messages that we have. And now we
can notice one very important property.
Delta 1-2, once computed, never
changes. So you get instant convergence of
Delta 1-2. Once you compute it for
the very first time, there's convergence.
Now what about delta 2-3? Well, that
depends on when delta 2-3 is passed. If
delta 2-3 is passed first, before it gets,
before cluster two gets a message from
cluster one, then, once it gets that
message, things might change. But if
cluster two is clever, it's gonna wait.
And it waits until that message is passed.
And once that message is passed, it
doesn't chance. Delta 2-3 doesn't change
either, ever, if it's smart enough to
wait. What about delta 3-4? Delta 3-4
needs to wait a little bit longer, because
it needs to wait for delta 2-3. But if it
waits for both delta 1-2 to be passed to
cluster two, and delta 2-3 to be passed to
cluster three, then now it's, now that
it's, now that it sends delta 3-4, delta
3-4 doesn't change either. So delta 2-3,
has to wait, for, delta 1-2. And
delta 3-4 has to wait, for, delta 2-3
but assuming it waits then
convergence is achieved in a single
message passing step. Now there is nothing
magical about going left to right. If you
go right to left you get the exact same
behavior. So, here you have this one
converges instantly. This one, you need to
wait. For delta 4-3. And this one
you need to wait. for delta 3-2. But again,
once, assuming you wait, then the messages
converge in a single step. And so we can
compute all of the messages in this entire
tree in one pass in either direction. One
pass from left to right, and one pass from
right to left. In the context of chain
structures like this one, this is
actually, this actually has its own name.
So for chains, you might see this under the
name forward backward algorithm. And is
very commonly used in things like hidden
Markov models and, and other similar chain
structured representations. And so the
point is, the total effort that we had to
compute all of these messages is just one
message passing step in each direction.
One from left to right, and one from right
to left. And. The result of that, remember
that once all messages have been passed,
we have beliefs that are correct beliefs
that represent. That are marginals of
P tilde Phi. And so we've computed all of
the marginals, of all of the clusters in
this graph in one, in, in sorry two,
sweeps over this clus, over this clique
tree. And so more generally as we said,
once Ci received a final message from all
of its neighbors except for Cj. It said,
wait to send, if it waits to send the
message to j until, until I receive the
message from everybody else. Then that
message delta ij is also final. So if
these are final, this is also final. Can
you always find a message passing order,
that will achieve that goal? I mean, maybe
you kind of, everybody ends up waiting for
everybody else, and they all get stuck,
and they never send anybody any messages.
The point is that you could always start.
Because the message from a leaf is always
immediately final. And once the message
from a leaf is finalized, then you can
send the message from the parents of the
leaf, and so on and so forth. And because
this is a tree, it's guaranteed that you
will be able to find a legal message
passing order. And if we pass the messages
in the right order, then we only need to
pass 2K minus one messages, where K is the
total number. Of clusters. And why is
that? Because if you have a tree over k
nodes, in this case k clusters, then
there's k minus one edges and since each
edge has a message in both directions so
we have, we have k minus one messages,
sorry, k minus one edges. And therefore
two k minus one messages, one in each
direction. [sound] Let's look at a couple
of message-passing orders to see which
ones are going to work and which ones
aren't. So, we can start with any leaf.
Any leaf works. So, say, we start with,
oh, I don't know, C2. When C2 has
passed this message. What other, what
other clique can pass its message?
C3 can't pass messages yet. Because
it's still waiting for messages from all
sorts of other guys. So we had to
go to another leaf. For example C1.
C1 can pass the message now. Neither C3
nor C4 are, are candidates for message
passing yet. Because each of them is still
waiting for another message. But C6 can
pass a message, and now we have the option
of activating C4. C4 can now send a
message to C3, because it's got everything
except the message from, from C3 before.
C7 can say, pass a message to C3 and you
notice there is a lot of arbitrary
decisions on how I ordered this. I could
have used C5 next. And now C3 has the
option of passing a message to C5. And notice
at this point everyone has received all of
the messages or all of the messages but
one. And so now we can start passing in
the other direction, so C5 can pass the
message to C3. C3 can pass a message
to any of C2, C7, or C4. And at this point
C4 can pass every, any, can pass the
message to both C6 and C1. What is an
example of an illegal message passing
order? So, for example, if C1 passes a
message to C4, and C4 jumps the gun and
says, yay, I'm gonna send the message to
C3 next, that is an illegal message
passing order, because C4 does not yet
have all of the information that it needs
to pass a message to C3. It's still
waiting for a message from C6. So that's
not a good ordering. Clique trees have
other very elegant computational
properties, that make them a useful data
structure. So let's think about the kinds
of queries that one can answer using,
clique trees. And some of these are fairly
obvious, but others are a little bit more
subtle. So imagine that we wanted to
answer a posterior distribution query on
either a single variable or a set of
variables that appear together in a
clique. So in this case, you could take
any clique that contains all of those
variables. And sum out the variables that
you don't care about from that clique, to
get a posterior over just those variables.
Now remember that, that posterior is P
tilde Phi, it's an unnormalized
measure. So in order to get the normalized
measure, you actually need to renormalize.
Now you could also do something a little
bit more clever. You could, say you wanted
to introduce new evidence regarding, oh,
some variable and query another variable.
So, this is a form of incremental inference.
Where you've already calibrated the
clique tree and now you say, 'Oh,
wait a minute. I made another observation.
Let's see what happens now.' So it turns
out that clique trees are really good for that.
And so we're going to divide this into two
cases, the easy case and the slightly less
easy case. So imagine that we want to
query variable X that appears in the
clique with my new evidence. So here is my
clique and here is Z and here is X and I'm
going to, and I want to figure out what
the posterior of X would be if I further
observe Z. Well, this is actually real
easy. Cuz what I have here is
P tilde phi. Let's assume for the moment to
just Z and X that there's other variables
there, it's not, it doesn't change
anything cuz we can always just get rid of
them. We can now condition or reduce the
clique so this is a clique reduction. By
just restricting attention to the entries
that are consistent with my evidence Z.
And then I end up with P tilde phi. Of
little z, X. And in order to get a
posterior, I can sum out the irrelevant
variables and renormalize. That can be an
incremental inference. That's the easy
case if the two variable are together in a
clique. What about a some of more
elaborate case, where I introduce the new
evidence and I query a variable that
doesn't appear in the same variable, in
the same clique as Z? So using an example,
let's imagine what I did is observe
evidence on A and I want to query
say E [inaudible], actually let's look at
different example let's imagine I want to
query D. [inaudible] In this case, I
can do the following. I can. Multiply wa-,
this indicator function or what we call
this reduction. Of the factor. Into a
cluster that contains the evidence. In
this case we're gonna multiply in the
indicator function of A equals little a,
which corresponds to removing all the
entries in cluster one that are not
consistent with, With a. Our [inaudible]
multiplied into psi one, removing. All
entries that are inconsistent with that.
So now what happens when we change psi 1?
Imagine what we're doing this entire
computations from scratch, that is forget
everything that we did before and think
what would happen to this model in a
hypothetical case that we were passing
messages with the new psi 1 instead of
the old psi 1. Yes some messages would
change. Which messages would change?
Delta 1-2 would change, because psi 1
changed. Delta 2-3 would change because
Delta 1-2 changed. Delta 3-4 would change
but we don't care about Delta 3-4. We're
interested in this belief over here.
What about other messages?
Delta 4-3 doesn't change. Neither does delta 3-2.
Neither, neither does delta of 2-1.
And so only assumption of the
messages in the clique tree change as a
result of this messages of this of this
change, which means that we can review at
least half the messages, if not more, in
computing our beliefs about in this case
cluster three. And the only messages that
we need to recompute are the messages that
are along the path to a clique that
contains the variable X that we want to
query. Which in this case is cluster
three. So to summarize, if we have a
clique tree with k cliques, and we pass
messages in a careful order, which means
that we start at the leaves and propagate
inwards, then we can construct an ordering
such that two k minus one messages suffice
to compute all of the beliefs in, in the,
in the clique tree which means we get a
posterior over every single variable in
the model. Contrast that with the
computational cost of running variable
elimination and times the computed
posterior as end different variable. Here
you get a considerable computational
saving. In fact, computational savings of,
order, order of the number of variables.
And so what we can do is we can compute
all of the marginal at only twice the
cost of variable elimination as opposed to
N times the cost of variable elimination.
And we've also shown that by caching,
restoring the messages, we can use
inference for example in the context of
incremental queries which provides us with
a useful data structure to keep updating
as we obtain additional edivence.