A lot of our thinking so far as gone into
constructing algorithms for the problem of
computing marginals in a graphical model.
But as we previously discussed, a very
different type of inference problem, but
one that has many applications in itself
is that of finding a single coherent joint
assignment that has the highest
probability. And we. Showed already that,
that doesn't have the same, that you can't
just solve the marginals problem, and
pick the highest probability assignment
for each variable, and that gives you the
map assignment. That's not what, that's
not what happens. And so we need to have
an alg-, a different set of algorithms for
solving the map problem. And we're going
to talk now about the first of these,
which is, Effectively following the exact
same lines that we did for exact inference
for computing marginals only it turns out
that one can re purpose them with a small
change to computing the map assignment. So the
first operation that going to do in order
to get this to work, is that we are going to take
products and turn them into summations.
And we are going to be doing that by
observing that p of the our distribution p
of Phi is proportional as we know
to a product of factors. And if we, if we
are trying to find the argmax of that
particular product. It can also be
written, reformulated as the argmax of
summation where each of these theta ks
is the log. Of the potential phi of k. Which is
basically the same as taking the table
that represents the factor and converting
each entry into its logarithm. And that
gives you something that, rather than
being a product of factors, is the sum of
these log factors. And there's really good
reasons for doing that. First, because
summations are easier to handle than, than
products. But also because, if you're
multiplying a whole bunch of very small
numbers, you're going to get numerical
underflows. And converting this into
summations is a much more robust algorithm
numerically, in, in terms of a practical
implementation. And so now we are going to
consider the problem, of that we just
wrote here which is the argmax of an
expression that we are going to call theta
of X1 up to Xn which is defined as the
sum of factors over smaller scopes which
are these theta ks. And this is the
example that I meant to show a moment ago.
So this is taking a factor over scope A
and B, and converting it to its log
factor, by taking log base two. And you'll
notice that the numbers were carefully
selected to give me nice, outputs. But
that doesn't have to be the case. So now
that we've reduced problem to one that
we're taking the max over summation, we're
going to now go back to our simple example
of a chain and we're going to think about
how we can do max sum variable elimination
in chain. And this is going to look.
Almost identical to the max, to the sum
product algorithm that we had before. So
let's understand what we are trying to do
here. So we're trying, assuming what we
are trying to do now is, forget the arg
max, let's assume that we just want to
find the max of this of this. Expression
theta of A, B. C, D and E. And so just
like in the sum product case, we can break
up the maxes into a max over A and then a
max over B and a max over C and a max over
D. And while we might not be quite as used
to doing this kind of operation that I'm
about to show, it's equally valid to point
out, that because none these guys, theta
two, theta three or theta four depend on A
we can. Add them up, the max over this
guy, over theta one and AB, after
completing the max. And so that's going to
give me a factor here. Which, which looks
like max over A, theta one of AB. And I'm
going to call that Lambda one of B.
Because notice that this is not a
constant. It's a function that depends on
B. For different values of B, you're gonna
have different val-, different A's of
maximize, and different values of the max
expression. And so this Lambda one of B is
simply the max over A of theta one, AB.
And that process has effectively now
eliminated A from this expression, and
given me a maximization problem over one
fewer variable, only B, C, D, and E. Just
like in the context of sum product
algorithms, we can view all of these
operations as operations over factors,
rather than just thinking about them in
terms of expression. So whereas before we
defined things like factor product and
factor marginalization, we can now define
analogous operations that correspond to
factor summation and factor maximization.
So factor summation's a very obvious
operation, does exactly what we did here,
so if we want to, in the case of factor
product, if we want to define. In the row
for A1, B1, C1, we're going to add up. The
entry three from A1 B1. And the entry four
from B1C1 and that is going to give me
seven. And I can similarly define all of
the other entries in the factor summation
which we're showing here on the right.
Factor maximization is same way that we
could sum marginalize a factor. This is
something that max marginalizes, is called
the max marginalization. And what it does
is, it looks, if I, so I'm trying to get
rid of B. I have these two rows here. Say,
for example, A1, B1, C1. And A1, B2, C1,
that only differ on B. And my new entry
here, A1, C1, is going to be the max of
these two entries over here. Which, in
this case, is going to be seven. And
similarly for, say, A1-C2. I am going to
end up with a max of 4.5 and two which is
4.5. So this is another form of
marginalization where I remove a variable
B but using an operation other than
summation. So now that we've defined these
two operations, we can go back and define
the max sum variable elimination in
chains, as a set of factor operations.
Where I eliminate A, then B, and so on and
so forth. So, for example, having
eliminated A as in the previous step, I
can now do the exact same operation by
noticing that the only factors that depend
on B are theta two of B, and lambda one of
B. So these other two. I can move outside
of the maximization. And that's going to
give me a max over B of a factor that is
the sum of the two factors Theta 2BC and
Lambda one of B that I got from the
previous elimination step. And that's
going to give me a new factor lambda 2 of C
and the process continues. In exactly the
same way as variable elimination did for
the case of sum product. And that's basically
the algorithm. So now let's think about
what we get at the end of this execution,
for the final factor. What is Lambda four,
having gone through Lambda two and Lambda
three, and now we get Lambda four of e.
What is Lambda four for a given value,
little e? Lambda four of little e is what
we got by maximizing. Over A, B, C and D
of theta A, B, C and D. So this is, the
best possible assignment. The best value.
That I can get, that I can possibly get.
If, we mandate that E equals little e.
Okay. And so, this is a factor, and it
gives me that value, for each one of the,
value score, the, effectively, for each
value little e of E. This is called a max
marginal. In the same way that we took
variable elimination for sum product and
we used that to define a clique tree
algorithm, we can do exactly the same
thing for max product, for er, max sum,
using the exact same type of data
structure. So here we def, we're going to
use the exact same clique tree, and we
have cliques over AB, BC, CD, and DE. And
we're going to as, as usual, assign the
potentials. To the appropriate, cliques
using. The family preservation property.
And now let's go ahead and see how
messages are passed, in this, clique tree
architecture So initially, the AB clique
is going to define the message lambda 1-2,
which is obtained by maximizing out A over
theta one. And the resulting message over
B gets passed to clique two. Clique two
can take that message; multiply it with
its own, factor, theta two. And add that,
this is max sum, remember? I'm going to
add that to lambda 1-2, and that gives me
the message lambda 2-3. And the same thing
can happen when clique three passes a
message to clique four in this case over
the scope of E. So exactly the same
message passing process except using max
and sum instead of sum and product. We can
equally well pass messages in the other
direction. So four to three over scope D
three to two and two to one. And all the
properties that we said hold in the
context of sum product clique trees hold
here as well. First notice for example,
that once this message lambda one two is
sent, it never changes again. It's, it's
defined once and for all. Lambda two
three, once it receives the message lambda
one two, it too has stabilized and will
never change, and similarly for lambda
three four. So we can do one pass. From
left to right to compute all of the left
to right messages. And a similar pass
right to left to compute all of the right
to left messages. And as soon as we do
that, they've all converged. The second
thing to notice is what is the value of
this clique over here. So, if we look at
this, we can see that when I've compute,
when I finally get all of the messages
from both sides, I have integrated in
theta one. Theta two, theta three which is
stored in the clique itself, and
theta four coming in from the message on
the right, and maximize out all of the
variables A, B, and E so that what I have
left is a factor over the clique three
which is the max over A, B, and E of the
sum of all of the factors in this network.
So, just to summarize, once the clique I
receives the final message from all of its
neighbors except c j, then that message is
also final, will never change, and the
messages from all leaves are immediately
final. And so what we have is an algorithm
that at convergence, that converges after
two passes and gives us correct max
marginals at every single one of the
cliques. So. Let's take a simple example
just to convince ourselves that this is
doing the right thing. So, I'm looking now
at a much simpler [inaudible] that only
has a, b, and c. So, there's is two
factors one over theta one of ab and theta
two of BC. And first we are going to
construct the overall math theta which is
the sum of theta one and theta two. So this
is a factor summation [inaudible] this
expression. And let's look at it and see
what is the map assignment in this
example. And if we just look at the
numbers that we computed, we see that the
map assignment is A1 B1 C1 with a value of
seven. Now let's look at the message
passings, process that you will have, on
this, very simple clique tree with two
cliques. So, this is theta one, it's
assigned to clique one. Theta two is
assigned to clique two. And let's look at
the two messages that are passed. So, here
was my a one so a b passes a message to b
c, and that message is the max marginal.
Max marginalization over the variable a.
And so we can see here we have a max
between three and, and -one so we get
three, because this is the max over the
two values of a that are consistent with b
one. And for b two we have the max over
zero and one so we get one. >> And exactly
the same process gives us, for this
message, where I'm max marginalizing C, I
get this message. This path from left to
right. Now each of these two cliques takes
its message, and note this is, I've gotten
immediate convergence here because there
was only one message to pass in each
direction. And, so what I get here is the
sum of this factor plus the incoming
message. I've added these two together and
so I have for example, for the first row
A1, for A1B1, I have three from here and
four from here. So I get three + four
which is equal to seven. For a1, b2, I get
a zero from here, and a2 from there, zero
+ two = two. And I can do exactly the same
operation to get this, to get this, set,
to get this factor on the right. I get
that by summing up this, with that, and I
get this factor over here. And you'll
notice that miraculously. The map, the map
had each of these factors separately. Is
a1 b1 on the left and b1 c1 on the right?
So sure enough what I got here was the
most likely assignment consistent with a1
b1 and over here the most likely
assignment consistent with b1c2. And
you'll notice, if you go back and check,
and I'm not going to do that right now.
But if you go back and check this, big
table over here, you can convince
yourselves that this doesn't only hold
true for A1-B1. If you look, for example,
at A2-B1, you'll see that what you get
here, the value three, is the value of the
most likely assignments that are
consistent, that is consistent with A2-B1.
So actually, let's go back and check that.
So here is A2-B1. We have two assignments
consistent with A two B one, one is 0.5
and one is three. Three is the best one,
and sure enough the value that we get here
is three. So, it all works. So what can we
say about this algorithm once it
converges? The important thing is that we
can compute beliefs at each clique that
represent exactly the max marginals of
that clique. So how do we compute these
beliefs? Analogously to what we had in the
context of sum product, we look at the
factor assigned to the clique, which is
the theta I. And we add to it the incoming
messages. Before you remember we had the
factor assigned to the clique multiplied
by the incoming message because we were
doing products instead of summations. What
does this belief, what does this belief
encode? This belief the max marginal. So
specifically, it, we can consider for any
given assignment to the clique Ci we can
look at the best possible, the score of
the best possible completion to the clique
Ci and that is the value of the belief at
that clique. So it's the max over all of
the variables, WI, that are not assigned
to the clique. One important
consequence of the fact that we have max
marginals is that we get a, a calibration
property here as well. So, f, the cliques
must agree on the variables that they
share. So to understand this let, let's
look at these two cliques that we have in
the simple 2-clique example. And here are
the beliefs that we had for clique one,
and for clique two. It's the sum of theta
one plus the incoming message over here.
And theta two plus nine over two. And,
let's look at what the calibration
property tells us. It tells us that, for
example, if we look at. The implications
of this clique regarding the variable b.
We would have that, that the, this clique
tells us that the best possible completion
for b one has a score of seven, and the
best possible completion for b two has a
score of three. This clique, if we look at
it, tells us that the best possible
completion for b1 also has a score of
seven, and the best possible completion
for b two also has a score of three. So
these two cliques agree regarding their
regarding the variable in their
shared scope, which is the variable
B. So to summarize, we can apply, in the
context of max sum, exactly the same
clique tree algorithm used for sum
product. Messages are passed in the same
way. The clique trees is constructed in
the same way. The only difference is that
the message passing operations use max and
sum as opposed to sum and product. At
exactly, as in sum product, convergence is
[inaudible], achieved after a single up
and down pass. And the result of that is a
set of beliefs that represent max
marginals at each of those cliques.
Where, as a reminder, the max marginals
tells for each assignment, what is the
score of the best possible completion to
that assignment.