We've argued that table CPDs are
problematic because of their exponential
growth in the number of parents. One of
the classes of structured CPDs that is
most useful are classes, is the class of
CPDs that encodes a dependence of a child
on the parent. But a dependence that is
only happening in certain contexts. One
method for encoding that is using the
class of what's called tree-structured
CPDs. So to understand what
tree-structured CPDs are let's look at
this simple example. Imagine that we have
a student, and the student is applying for
a job. And the job, that the prospects of
the student to get the job depend on three
variables. Depend on the quality of the
recommendation letter that they get from a
faculty member, of their SAT scores, and
whether the student chooses to apply for
the job in the first place. So let's think
about one possible CPD for this, for this
model. So here we have a tree structure.
And you can think about it as a set of, as
a branching process where the distribution
over a job looks at some variables and
then decides what the distribution might
look like. So for example, initially the,
The dependence is on whether the student
chooses to apply for the job or not. What
happens if the student doesn't apply for
the job? Well, you might say in that case
the student doesn't get the job, but it
turns out to be not the case. In the
heydays of Silicon Valley, for example, we
have the different Internet bubbles.
Students were getting job offers without
ever applying for jobs. And so it might
actually happen that the student's
probability of getting a job is not zero
even in this case. And notice that the
student not having applied for the job
didn't submit either recommendation letter
or the SAT scores which means that the
student's job prospects don't depend in
this scenario on either of these two
variables. And so, in all possible
configurations of the s and l variable,
the s and l variables, the probability of
the student getting a job is 0.2. What if
the student did choose to apply for the
job? Well, in this case we can imagine a
recruiter whose primary interest is in the
student's SAT scores. They don't really
believe recommendation letters all that
much. And so the next, and so the
recruiter first looks at the student's SAT
score. And if the student got a good score
on the SAT, s1, then regardless of the
recommendation letter, which the recruiter
doesn't even choose to look at, the
student's probability of getting a job is
0.9. Only in the case where the student's
SAT scores are not as strong does the
recruiter go back and look at the letter,
in which case there is a certain
probability, say 60%, of getting a job if
the letter is strong. And ten percent if
the letter is weak. So we can see that we
have a CPD that in this case depends on
three binary variables and so really we
would need to represent in principle eight
different probability distributions over
the j variable. But we've only represented
four because in certain contexts some of
the variables don't matter. So in fact
this notion of a variable not mattering is
related to the notion of context-specific
independence, which we've defined
previously. So one can formalize this in
fact as a context-specific independence.
So let's look at this tree and think about
which context-specific independencies
arise in the context of this
tree-structured CPD. So, let's Looking at
the first one, does j, the variable that
we care about, depend on l? In the context
A1. S1 Well, we can see that in the
context A1S1, the recruiter never looks at
the letter. So in fact, j is independent
of l in this context. So the answer to
this one is yes. Okay, what about the next
one. J is independent of l given A1 alone.
Well, in this case, we have, we're going
down here and now there's two scenarios.
One in which S = S1 and the other, S = S0
and in this case, the recruiter does look
at the letter and so this one in fact is
not true. What about the next one? J is
independent of l and s given A0. So let's
look at the A0 case. And sure enough, in
the A0 case there's no dependence on
either l or s, so this one is also true.
The last one is a little bit interesting,
because it's a mix of context-specific and
non-context-specific independence. So
we're asking whether j is independent of l
in the context S1. For both values of the
variable a. And so now let's, and so to
answer this question we actually need to
do a case analysis because this reduces to
two different independent statements. J is
independent of l given S1 and A1 and j is
independent of l given S1 and A0. So let's
evaluate each of these two separately. J
is independent of l given S1A1 is exactly
this assertion, so this one's true. J is
independent of l given S1 and A0 is
represents this. Which, in fact, is a
special case of this scenario. And so both
of these in fact are true independent
statements, and so since both cases hold
we have another conditional independent
statement that holds here. Let's look at
another example that turns out to be
representative of a large class of
examples in this context. So here the
student, when applying for the job, needs
to submit a recommendation letter but has
a choice between the two letters that they
might, that they might elect to provide.
One from one course and another from a
second course. So letter one and letter
two. Now the student's job prospects
depend on the quality of the letter that's
actually provided because, of course, the
recruiter doesn't have access to the
letter that was not provided. So if we
look at this in the context of the
[inaudible], they don't even like this.
The first variable at the top corresponds
the student choice and it has two branches
c1 and c2, and in the c1 case, there is
dependence only on the quality of letter
one and then the c2 case, there is
two So this is an example of what
[inaudible] Related to something called a
multiplexer CPD, because effectively the
choice variable determines the dependence
on one set of circumstances or another set
of circumstances. Now it turns out that
this example has some interesting
ramifications. Because not only do we have
[inaudible] specific independence's that
arise because of this restructure, it
turns out that this, also implies non
[inaudible] specific independence's that
are quite useful as we'll see later on in
the course. Specifically we have that
letter one is independent of letter two
given J and C Now, if you think about this
from purely the proc-, the perspective of
the, the separation structure, the flow of
influence in this graph, we can see that
the job actually activates the V
structure, between letter one and letter
two. So you wouldn't actually expect
letter one and letter two to be
conditionally independent. That is, we
have a flow of influence because of
inter-causal reasoning. But now let's
think about this in more detail. And let's
do a case analysis just like we did
before. So we're now going to ask if
letter one is independent of letter two,
given j and C1. But what happens in the
context C=C1? Well in this case, there's
no longer a dependence between job and
letter two, because the recruiter is never
given the second letter. And so, in the
context C1, the graph really looks like
this, where there's no edge from l to the
j. Conversely, looking at the other case
analysis where C=C2, in this case this
other edge is going to disappear and once
again there's no V structure and so
there's no active trail between these two
variables L1 and L2. So effectively, in
both of these cases, the active trail
disappears and so that implies the
independence assumption. That I mention
this example is related to more general
class of models called the multiplexer
CPD. The multiplexer CPD in this case
actually has the following structure. We
have a set of random variables, zero on up
to ZK all of which take on some value in
some particular space. And the variable Y
is a copy of one of the ZIs. The variable
A, over here, is the multiplexer, the
selector variable. And the selector
variable takes on values in the space one
to K and it selects which of the ZIs the Y
copies. And notice that the Y here is
deterministic, as we can see by the fact
that we have these two lines surrounding
it, which is our way of indicating
deterministic dependencies. And so what is
the CPD of the variable Y, given the
selector A and the parent Z1 up to ZK? We
can think about this as, remember we need
to specify a probability distribution so
this probability distribution is one, if Y
is equal to Z sub A. So what does that
mean? It means that, and zero otherwise.
So what does that mean? It means that if
A, say, is equal to little A, then
deterministically Y is equal to sub little
A, with probability one. That's just a
formal way of saying that. So A tells us
which of the variable Z Y needs to copy.
This turns out to be an extremely useful
concept in a variety of applications. So
for example when we have perceptual
uncertainty, when you have noisy sensors
where we observe say What we have, say, a
sensor observation of one of several
airplanes, but we don't know which
airplane it is that we're observing. And
so the position of the observation is the,
represents the position of the airplane
that we're observing but the variable A
here is the one that tells us which
airplane it is, which we might also be
uncertain about. And this gives rise to a
whole set of problems known as
registration, or correspondence, or data
association problems which are very common
in many applications. Different type of
application for this, type of structured
CPD, comes up in physical hardware
configuration settings. So this is an
actual example from a trouble-shooter, for
printers used at Microsoft. And it turns
out that all of the trouble-shooters that
are part of the Microsoft operating system
are, built on top of [inaudible] network
technology. So here the task is to try and
figure out why a printer isn't printing.
So we have a variable here that tells us
whether a printer is producing output. And
that depends on a variety of factors, but
one of the factors that it depends on is
where the printer input is coming from. Is
it coming from a local transport? We're
not [inaudible] And depending on which of
those it's coming from, there's a
different set of failures that might
occur. So, the variable here that serves
the goal of the selector variable, is this
variable Print Data Out. And that's the
root of the tree that's used here. And,
and depending on whether the print
location is local or not, then you depend
either on properties of the local
transport or on properties of the network
transport. And it turns out that even in
this very, very simple network the use of
tree CPDs reduces the number of parameters
from 145 to about 55 and make the
elicitation process much easier. So to
summarize [inaudible] provide us with a
compact representation that captures
effectively this motion of dependence in a
[inaudible] specific way. And as we've
mentioned as relevant in a broad range of
applications of which we're only given
some examples, hardware configuration,
medical settings, we're depending on the
kind of situation that your in you might
depend on one set of predisposing factors
say or another Dependence on an agent
action, as we've seen for example in the
student's decision on whether to apply for
a job or not or which letter to submit.
And we've also discussed perceptual
ambiguity where the value of the
particular sensed observation depends on
which real world object that observation
comes from.