That exploit additional forms of local
structures some kind of pro matrix form
are extremely valuable in context of
general, in the general context of
graphical models because they allow us to
provide a much sparse representation. But
they are absolutely essential when we have
in networks that involves continuous
variables because their tables are simply
not an option. So let's look at some
examples of networks that involve
continous variables, and see what kind of
representations we might want to
incorporate here. So now, let's imagine
that we have a continous temperature
variable. Say the temperature in a room.
And we have a sensor, a thermos-, a
thermometer that mentions, that measures
the, the temperature. Now, thermometers
aren't perfect, and so, what we would
expect, then, is the sensor is around the
right temperature, but not quite. And so.
One way to capture that is by saying that
the sensor S is a normal distribution. And
here's an all distribution. Around the
true temperature, T, with some standard
deviation, Sigma S. So this defines for
every value of T a distribution over S. In
a very compact parametric form that has
just really the parameter of sigma S, and
if we just say that S is a Gausian around
the variable, around the value of the
variable T. Now let's make the situation a
little bit more interesting. This is the
temperature now. And this is a
[inaudible]. So we have P. And P. Prime.
Now, P. Prime now depend, the, the
temperature soon depends on the current
temperature, as well as the outside
temperature, because of some equalization
of temperatures from the inside to the
outside. So, what model what, we, might we
have for T prime as the function of it's
two parents? Temperature the current
temperature and the outside temperature.
Well, so one model might be just some kind
of diffusion model that says that T is
equal to some weighted combination. Sorry,
T prime is a Gaussian around,
a mean that's defined as a combination of
the current temperature and the outside
temperature. So you kind of combine the
two, and because there is stochasticity in
the process, we're going to say that T
prime isn't exactly equal to this, but
rather is a Gaussian around this mean.
With some standard deviation stigmatic. To
be distinguished from the standard
deviation stigma x which is the center of
deviance. Let's make life even more
interesting. Let's imagine that there is a
door in the room. The door can be opened
or closed so it's a discreet variable,
takes two values and clearly the extent of
the diffusion is going to depend upon
whether the door is open and we would
expect different parameters to this
system. In the case of two values of the
discreet variable and so if we write the
model now we're going to have that the
temperature time, the temperature soon T
prime, is going to be a Gaussian
who's parameters, alpha and sigma depend
on the value of a door variable. So, if b
equals zero. We're going to have
parameters alpha zero and sigma zero T.
And if b equals one, we have
a different set of parameters that equal
to different diffusion process. So just to
give all these things name this model that
we had over here was called a linear
Gaussian. We will define that more formally in the
next slide. And this model is called the
conditional linear Gaussian. Because
the linear Gaussian whose parameters are
conditioned on the discrete variable
Door. So to generalize these models
to a broader setting where, where we have
a general variable Y and Y has parents X1
up to XK the linear Gaussian model has the
following form. It says that Y is a
Gaussian, so that's what the N stands for,
who's mean, is a linear function, and
that's why it's called a linear
Gaussian. Is a linear function of the
parents Xi. And importantly whose
variance doesn't depend at all. On the
parents So the variance is fixed. That's
the definition of a liner Gaussian CPD,
and obviously, it's restricted. It doesn't
capture every situation, but it's a useful
model and a useful first approximation in
many cases. Conditional linear Gaussian
introduces into the mix, the possibility
of one or more discrete parents. In this
case, we just drew one more simplicity,
but you could have more than one. And this
is just a linear Gaussian whose
parameters depend on the value of A. So,
writing it down it looks exactly like
this. We now have, for every one of the
parameters, we have the ability for the
parameters to depend on A. And this case,
the variants, can depend on the continue
on the discreet parent. But not on the
continuous ones. And this is the
conditional in your Gaussian model. And
again, similarly it is a restricted model,
and one can certainly generalize beyond
that, as we'll show in a moment. But it's
a very useful model that's used in a large
number of applications. One example
application that we've seen that involves
continuous variables is the task of robot
localization. I'm not going to show this
video again now. We're going to see it
again when we talk about temporal models.
But, just as a reminder, what we have here
is a robot whose location is a continuous
quantity. So are the sensor observations
that give a noisy version of how far away
the robot is from an obstacle looking in
each one of the different directions. Okay
and so we have both the continuous state
variable as well as the continuous
observation that the robot needs to deal
with. So what kind of observation model
makes sense in this study. So here lets
imagine that this line over here
represents the true distance. From the
robot's current location, from a given
location to obstacle. So if the robot
is looking in, if we're conditioning on
the robots current location and we're
asking, if I look in this diresction how
far is it before I hit an obstacle. In
this case that distance is, 200 and, I
don't know, twenty centimeters. And what
this tells us is that a sonar is a
Gaussian. You can see this is the sonar.
The red is the sonar. Is a Gaussian around,
the true distance. Now, the laser, which
is a different sensing modality for the
same robot is also a Gaussian around that
true distance. But because the laser is a
more accurate sensor the standard
deviation is lower for the laser than for
the sonar. And that reflects the accuracy
of these two different sensor modalities.
Now, this is an idealized version. But
surprisingly corresponds in useful ways to
the real model. So let's actually look at
some of the, Let's look first at the model
that was used in the system. And then, at,
which is the red line. And then we can
look at the blue line. The red line
actually involves three different
components. So this is the actual center
model. Used by the robots and we can see
that it has three components. It has this
peak Which is the Gaussian around the
true distance. The next most obvious
phenomenon is this ridiculous peak over
here. This corresponds to a max range
reading. This is what you get if there
isn't an obstacle in that direction within
a reasonable distance for the laser or the
sonar to return any signal. And so that's
why there's a very large peak, at, at,
beyond a certain distance. That's the
entire rest of the probability mass. The
final most more subtle aspect of this
probability distribution is that you see
that this is higher than that. So, the,
there's more probability mass, for the
density, before the obstacle than after
the obstacle. And why is that? Because
once you get to the obstacle. The beam
returns. But before you get to the
obstacle there might be some other like,
transient things, like a person walking in
front of the obstacle. And that's going to
return the beam in a way that doesn't
represent the actual structure of the map.
And so that's why we have a certain
probability. Of having the ob, of having
the, the beam return sooner than the
obstacle, and that probability doesn't
exist on the downside once the obstacle's
been reached. So the actual probability
distribution is an aggregation of these
three signals. The sensor model around the
obstacle in a given direction. This
uniform distribution, before
the obstacle would [inaudible]
distribution return and the max range
reading at the end. The red line is the
model that was used and the blue
line is, the actual measured distances in
different settings to sort of show whether this
really does, the model that was used
really represents reality. And the answer
is that, it does to a surprising extent.
So this, this is an example of how
continuous sensor, continuous
distributions are going to be used in a
real world application. The next example,
of that, is actually the robot motion
model. So here are the robots. And the
robot is heading in a given direction
alpha. Heading sorry, heading in this
direction that's what it thinks it's going
and the question is if it moves a certain
distance it thinks it's moving a certain
distance in a given direction. What is the
Actual distribution over it's next
location. And the answer is it's a little
bit tricky because robots actually have
heading and there's certain uncertainty
alpha, over which is the difference
between where they think they are going
and where they are actually going. And
then there is also noise. On the distant
delta, that they think they moved, and,
so, when you put all these together, the
actual cloud, on, the distribution, on
where the robots going to be, falling,
[inaudible] move, is this weird, banana
shaped distribution, which is centered
around. This area where the robot thinks
it is. But is, but has a sort of banana
shape that's, where the banana shape is
induced by the uncertainty about the
angular trajectory. And if you actually
run this for a while, you can see that the
banana shape gets more and more and more
diffuse. So here is the first banana
shape, and now the robot turns, and
there's more uncertainty over the heading.
And so, you get. A larger and larger
banana shaped distribution, on the robots
position, assuming there's no evidence to
correct, the position based on say sonar
or laser readings.