We have previously shown that a graph
structure encodes a set of independencies
and that, that set of independencies then
necessarily holds for every distribution
that can be encoded as a Bayesian network
over that graph. What we're going to talk
about now is the question of how to take a
distribution that has a certain set of
independencies that, that it satisfies, and
encode it within a graph structure. How
well can we take that distribution and
capture its independencies in the context
of the graphical model. So first, let's
understand what the independencies of a
distribution are. So we're going define this notion of I(P) for distribution P,
as the set of all independence statements.
X is independent of Y, given Z. That
hold for the distribution P. So one
can write down, potentially, an
exponentially large set of independence statements. Each of those is going to be
either true in a given distribution P,
or not. And what we're going to do is
we're going to define I(P) to be the ones
that are true in that distribution. Ok, so these
are independencies that hold in P.
And we've already seen that if P
factorizes over a particular graph
G, then, G is an I map for P, which means
that every independence that holds in G,
that is, is implied by the D separation
statements, or the D separation properties in
G, every such independence also holds in P.
But that doesn't mean that the converse
holds. That is, there can be
independencies that hold in P that are
members of I(P) . But are not
encoded by the graph structure. So. Why
does that matter? Because, if we have a
graph that doesn't capture, some of the
Independencies in P, then, it's
unnecessarily complicated. And conversely
the sparser the graph the more
independencies it encodes then the sparser it is and therefore it has fewer
parameters that we need to elicit or
learn. Fewer edges also means that
inference is more efficient and finally it
means that the graph is intrinsically more
informative about the properties of P. So
we would like graphs that capture as much
of the properties, independence properties of P as possible. So what do we want in
terms of sparsity? Something that is
fairly basic that we might choose to
require is what's called a minimal
IMAP. That is, we want an IMAP for the
distribution P that at least doesn't have
redundant edges. So for example, if we
have a graph X. Y, where Y really doesn't
depend on X in the sense that P of Y
given, say, X zero in the CPD is equal to
P of Y given X one, then we could remove
this edge and still have something that
was an iMAP for this distribution. And so
this edge is now redundant, and so from
our definition that would mean that this
iMAP is not minimal because you can have
an iMAP from which edges can be removed.
So that might seem to be a reasonable
strategy but it turns out that it's not
sufficient in terms of insuring that our graph is as sparse as it might be. So to
understand why that's the case let's look
at a distribution such as that corresponds
to this example that we've seen before where the student's grade G depends on these two
variables I and D. So that in fact is a
minimal iMAP for a distribution where D
and I are independent and G depends on
both of them. But it turns out that this is
not the only minimal iMAP for
distribution. A different minimal iMAP is
this one. Where we have an edge that goes from D to I, from D to G, and from G to I.
Let's convince ourselves that in fact this
is a minimal iMAP. Let's try and remove
any one of those edges and see if we still
get an iMAP for the original distribution.
So if for example we try and remove this
edge, that would correspond to
a statement that D is independent of G
which is certainly not the case in our
original distribution. So that one doesn't
work. What about the second one. If we try
and remove the second edge from G to I
that would correspond to a statement that
D, sorry, that G is independent of I,
given D, which is also not the case in our
original distribution. What about the
final edge, the one that doesn't
correspond to an edge in our original
network. This one. Can we remove that one?
That one seems most promising of the
lot but if you remove that one it would
correspond to the assumption that D is
independent of I, given G. And that is
exactly the dependence that is induced by
inter-causal reasoning that we've seen
before. So in fact, this is a minimal I
Map. None of the edges can be reduced.
There is a better minimal I Map, but this
is a minimal I Map. So minimal I Maps are
not necessarily the best tool for
capturing structure in the distribution.
What we'd really like is a perfect map. A
perfect map is one where the independencies
in G exactly corresponds to the
independencies in P. So the G perfectly
captures the independencies in P. And
sure enough if we could get that, that
would be ideal. Unfortunately perfect maps
are often hard to come by. So here's an
example of one scenario that doesn't have a perfect map. This is a distribution P
that is actually represented by this pairwise Markov network that
we've seen before. So, one where we have pairwise interactions ab bc cd and ad.
So we know that this distribution
satisfies certain independencies, because
of the Markov network property.
Specifically we know that, a is
independent of c, given b and d, because b
and d separate a and c in the graph, and
at the same time we know that b is
independent of d, given a and c. So now
that we, let's imagine that we have a
distribution P that satisfies these
independencies, so P satisfies this
pair of independencies, and now
let's try and code those independencies
using a Bayesian network as a perfect
map. Let's try. One possible attempt
would be to just try and direct the edges say
this way. Is that an iMap for this
distribution? Well, among other things one
of the independencies implied by this
graph would be that B is independent of D
given A. And that's certainly not
supported by the original distribution. So
this in fact is not an iMap. So try a
different way of organizing the edges.
So, for example. Here we have, sure
enough, and this is good, that B
and D are independent given A and C.
And that's one of our independencies that
we had before so it captures correctly
that one. But, if, but, not all, but, it
doesn't capture the but it also makes
other independent assumptions that are not
true in the original distribution. For example, that A and C, are marginally independent.
And, that's certainly not true in the
original distribution. So once again, this
is not, an I-map. What is an I-map for
this distribution as a directed graph?
Well, one possible iMAP for this
distribution as directed graph. Here's
several. Is this one? And, you can confirm that this distribution satisfies, that
this graph implies that A is independent
of C. Given B and D. And that's it in
terms of independencies. And so this in
fact is an iMap for the distribution
because in this case I of D is a subset of
I of P, which is this set over here. But
it doesn't capture all of the
independencies. It only captures one out
of the two. So this is the distribution
that does have a perfect map as a Bayesian
network. Let's come up, let's provide
another example of an imperfect map. And
in fact this is a distribution
that doesn't have a perfect map as
either a Bayesian network or a
Markov network. And this is the
famous example of the XOR which is
as we'll see a counter example to many, many
things. Here we have two random variables X1 and X2 which were assuming are binary
valued and say... Each of them takes the
value 0,1 with probability 50-50. Y on the
other hand is the Exclusive Or of X1 and
X2, which means that Y is equal to one
if and only if exactly one of X1 or X2,
is equal to one. Okay, so let's talk
about, this probability distribution P,
looks like, here it is, we have that,
there's four possible configurations, that
have nonzero probability, and, each of
them, has equal probability of 0.25, so
X1, X2, can be, either, zero, or, one,
with probability 50-50, and, here is the
value of Y over here. But now
let's think about other, so let's see some
independent statements are true for this
distribution. So most obviously looking
at this graph we see that X1 is marginally
independent of X2. But if you close your
eyes, on this part of the image
And just look at the right hand
side. You'll see that really X1, X2,
and Y are all symmetrical in terms of
their structure. So it's not difficult to
verify that we also have that X1 in fact
is independent  of Y and X2 is
independent of Y. And all three of these
pairwise independencies hold in this
distribution. And, so this is not in fact
the, the, the graph on the left is not a
perfect map for this distribution because
there are  independencies that hold in P
that are not visible in the graph. And in
fact you can organize the nodes in this
graph any which way and, but you cannot
get all three of these independencies
captured at the same time. Because the
only way to do that would be to have X1,
X2, and Y be separate variables. And of
course that wouldn't be an IMAP for the
distribution. So we've talked about Bayes nets as a
perfect map. What about Markov networks
as a perfect map? The definition here is
the same except that we've replaced G by
H, so a Markov network H is a
perfect map if the independencies
encoded by H exactly correspond
to the independencies in P, and can we capture
all possible distributions in terms of
a Markov network as a perfect map?
So I'm sure you're all expecting, expecting your answer
to be no, and sure enough that's true.
So here is an example of a distribution that has a perfect map, in this
case is as a Bayesian network, but not as a Markov network. So this is the famous
V-structure example, in this case the
Difficulty, Intelligence, Grade
V-structure and let's think about what in
the, what we need to encode as in terms of
edges for being an I-map of this distribution. So clearly we need
to introduce an edge between D and G and
between I and G. Because it's certainly
not the case that we can make D and G
independent given I or vice versa. And so
this would be the obvious I map for this
distribution but this example if we choose
this as, as a candidate I map it would
imply among other things that D is
independent of I given G. And that of
course is exactly wrong because we know
that when we condition on G,
D and I become dependent and
so the only iMAP. For this distribution is
one that has all three edges, and that
loses the independence we had over
here, which is D is marginally independent
of I. So
once again, there's no perfect map for
this distribution as Markov network. The
final question that we might ask ourselves
is, the extent to which a representation
of a distribution is, in fact, unique. And
so say that we could represent the
distribution using some graph, say, as a
perfect map. Is that a unique
representation? So, to understand that
let's look first at the simplest example.
One where we have two variables X and Y.
And here we have one graph that captures
in this case no independence assumptions so
I of G is equal to the empty set. G1 and
here's G2. It looks the same except that
the edges are inverted, the one edge is
inverted. And, once again, this is a
different graph that has exactly the same
vacuous set of independencies. So we can
see that here we have two distinct graphs
that have the exact same of independent
assumptions and because of that they can
represent exactly the same set.of distributions.
Which in this case
is all distributions over the variables X,
Y. Now, one might think that this is a degenerate example,
because, it's a fully connected graph.
But it turns out to be not the case,
there are many other situations, where,
two distinct graphs, with edges going in
different directions, represent the
exact same set of independence
assumptions. So, for example, when we look
at graphs over three random variables, it
turns out, that, of these four scenarios,
one of those represents adifferent
set of independent assumptions than all
the others, but, all the others are the
same. So, which is the odd man out? Which
of these following graphs does not encode
the same independence assumptions as the
others? As I'm sure most of you realize,
the answer here is the V-structure, which
is one that we've seen before. So this one
has the independence assumption X is
independent of Z marginally, whereas
these other three. Have the independent
assumption that X is independent of  Z.,
given Y. So these three graphs, again,
represent the same set of independence
assumptions, which is this set over here.
And as such, they also can take
any probability distribution that can be
represented by one of these graphs, can
also be represented by another, by the
other. So the formal notion for this, the
formal term for this notion is what's
called I-equivalence. Where two graphs
G1 and G2 over the same space are said to
be I-equivalent if they make the exact
same set of independence assumptions. And
in the previous example we saw for example
that X, Y, Z is I-equivalent to say. Y
being a parent of both X and Z, and. This
third one over here, whereas the
V-structure is not I-equivalent.
Now, why is I-equivalence an important
notion? It's important because it tells us
that there are certain aspects of the
graphical model that are unidentifiable.
Which means that if we end up, for
whatever reason, thinking that, say, this
is the graph that represents our
probability distribution, it could just as
easily be this one, or that one. So
without prior knowledge of some kind or
another, for example that we prefer X to
be a parent of Y, there's no way for us to
select among these different
choices. And it turns out that this is not
an exception, rather it's the rule. Most
graphs have a large number of
I-equivalent variants. And
that turns out to be a complicating
factor, especially when we get to learning
models from data. So in summary, we prefer
to have graphs that capture as much of the
structure in I(P) as possible, because they
are more compact. Therefore easier to
learn and easier to inference with, and
also provide us with more insight about
the distribution. We talked about minimal I-maps,
as one option for sparse
graphs and we showed that, that's not a
particularly good option because it might fail
to capture structure even if
it's present in the distribution and even
if it is representable, as a Bayes net, or as
a graphical model. A better notion is a perfect
map, which is great, but there are many
cases where a perfect map might not exist.
And we've also seen that when we take a
distribution that was naturally
represented as a Bayes net, and tried to
represent it as a Markov net, as a, we
generally do not get a perfect map, we
lose independencies and vice versa.
Something that was naturally represented
as a Markov net, you try and encode it as a
Bayes net once again, you lose
independencies. Specifically, when we go
from a Bayes net to a Markov
network, we lose the independencies in
V-structures. And when you go from a
Markov network to a Bayesian network, we
need to add edges that inside, loops like
the, A, B, C, D Loop. We had to add this
edge in the middle. An edge typically
called a triangulating edge, because it
turns the loop into a pair of triangles.