Shared structure and shared parameters
comes up in directed models, but it comes
up as much or perhaps even more in
undirected models. And that is because for
reasons we've already discussed and will
continue to discuss, eliciting parameters
in an undirected model is much more
difficult because they don't represent
[inaudible] probabilities or probabilities
and so it's a lot easier to represent them
as, sort of templates that, are comprised
of smaller building blocks. So let's talk
about log-linear models and how we, why
and how we might share parameters in
log-linear models. And it turns out to be
quite easy once you think about life in
terms of log-linear models. So, let's go
to the, one of the simplest examples that
we've discussed, which is that of icing
models. So icing models, as you recall, is
a model that was first invented in the
context of statistical physics where we
have a bunch of binary random variables,
each, which in this case, in the original
application, represent the spin of atoms
in a certain grid. So here is, one here's
a spin going one way and here's a spin
going, the orang-, the pink one is a spin
going in the opposite direction. And we
have correlations between the spins of the
adj-, of the electrons in the adjacent
atoms. And what we have as our energy
model in an icing model, is a sum over all
of the edges in the icing model. So in
this example the edges are organized in a
grid of the weight. That represents the
connection of the spin of the two adjacent
atoms times this feature over here. So F
of XIXJ, which is the product of XI and XJ
and it just, as a reminder XI are all in
the inter, are all either minus one or
plus one. So the product is always either
negative one or positive one. Negative if
the two have different spin and positive
one if they have the same spin. Now, this
doesn't have any shared parameters because
we have a separate parameter WIJ for every
pair of atoms. I and J. But clearly we're
not going to have, in general, a separate
model for every, for every number of atoms
in, of the material that we're trying to
model. So usually, what's going to happen
is that we're going to just have a single
parameter W that represents the
interconnectivity between or the, the
extent of the influence. Extent and type
of the influence of two adjacent atoms on
each other. And so this is now a model
that has the same feature And the same
weight. So same feature. And same weight.
Reused across different sets of, different
pairs of random variables in the model.
Okay? In, the natural language processing
example that we have used previously, so
we have, again, parameter sharing where we
have in this case, these are the, just as
a reminder we have these being the actual
words. These being the labels for the
words, this is the name that's a
[inaudible] recognition problem. But the
same thing happens in other examples. So
here we have, we've talked previously
about the kinds of features that
represen-, that relate, for example, the
label of the word and the word itself. For
example if it's capitalized it's more
likely to be a person, if the previous
word is Mrs. It's more likely to be a
person too. And so, And so here again we
have features, which are the ones we just
talked about, feature of for example, is
why I a person An XI is capitalized. And
we would have a term that uses this
feature repeated for every position in the
sequence. That is the same feature which
talks about the connection between the
label of the word and the word itself
would recur in every position in the
sequence. Because you wouldn't want that
same, to represent different
parameterizations for different positions
in the sequence. And similarly, we have
the same energy terms, for example, that
relate adjacent words also being repeated
across different pairs, in this case, of
adjacent words. [inaudible] in, in this
example. Once again we have no potentials
that represent in this case the connection
between the image features And the label
And once again we're going to use the
exact same potentials for all pixels and
we're going to have a difference in this
case sudden potentials that are going to
be re-used for all [inaudible],
[inaudible] pixels or super pixels. So how
do we do this? It turns out to be really
simple. What we basically need to specify
for a given feature that we want to reuse,
we're going to specify for it a set of
scopes. That is a set of scopes for which
we would like it to be applied. And, so if
we have a set of scopes, and let's assume
that DK is one of the scopes that to which
we would like apply the feature K, so our
energy function now is going to include a
term WKFKDK in the energy function. So for
example, if FK is We have we want to have
SKB applied to Adjacent to adjacent
super-pixels in the image. So the scopes
of feature FK will be the label YIYJ such
that I, J are adjacent. And that's going
to be the set of scopes to which we apply
that feature. And every time that we have
that apply we're going to have a term that
multiplies in the value of that feature
times the weight which is shared. The
weight depends on the feature, so WK
depends on K [inaudible] So this is just a
way of replicating the feature with its
weight across different, different subsets
of random variables in the image. Or in
the, in the, in the model. So, said
otherwise and I wrote all over this so
let's see if I can erase this. Yes. We
will have a term in the energy function.
Which has W K times the sum of the
features across all the scopes to which it
applies. Which is just the way of
aggregating like terms that all have W K
in them. So to summarize, in log-linear
models it's very common to use the exact
same feature and weight for multiple
subsets of variables. We've given multiple
examples of that. And this allows us, just
as in the other examples that we've seen
in the direct case to provide a single
template for multiple [inaudible]
networks. Whether it's different, the
[inaudible] network for different images
or for different sentences. And, the
parameter M structure are then allow-, are
then reused both within and across Markov
networks. And the only thing we need to do
in order to apply this is to specify a set
of scopes to which particular feature is
it going to be applied.