We talked about the problem of, learning
models with missing variables, missing
data. And discussed some of the
complexities of that learning problem. So,
now we're going to basically bite the
bullet and try and understand how one
might go about doing, say, parameter
estimation in the context of missing data
nevertheless. So let's remind ourselves of
one of the more important, difficulties in
learning. Parameters for the missing data.
So let's draw here the likelihood function
that we might have. So the x-axis here is
the param-, is a pictorial description of
the parameter vector theta. And it's a
one-dimensional depiction, but usually, of
course, it'll be multidimensional. And
what we see here on the y-axis is the
likelihood function. In the context of
complete data as, as we might remember the
likely function had this really nice form.
It was nice log concave function and in
the context of daisy networks it could
actually be optimized in closed form
using, using a simply formula. In the
context of missing data, however, the
situation became considerably more
complicated now like the assumption looks
more like this. It's this nasty
complicated multi model function, which is
really impossible to optimism in closed
form. So how do we go about optimizing a
function that looks like this. There is it
turns out two general classes of
strategies. The first is a generic
optimization method such as gradient
ascent. So here for example, we have a
pictorial depiction of gradient ascent. We
might start out with a particular point in
the parameter space. And we compute the
gradient of that point. And we go in the
direction of steepest ascent, which might
take us to the next point. At which point
we compute the gradient, and we continue
until we reach what is going to be a. In
generally local optimum of the function
that we're trying to optimize. Now what I
describe right now is a very simple
radiant assent over parameter space but in
general there are more efficient methods
for improving the convergence, the rate of
convergence of these algorithms, methods
such as line search or [inaudible] radiant
methods that basically are going to get us
faster to whatever [inaudible] whatever
[inaudible] we're gonna end up at So key
question when applying [inaudible] such as
this is how difficult it is to compute the
gradient in this high dimensional space,
fortunately the context of [inaudible]
networks we can actually come up with a
[inaudible] formed solution for that
gradient, and that solution takes the
following form. So the gradient of our log
[inaudible] function relative to a
particular parameter, theta of xi given
UI. So this is in the context of, a
standard say multinomial Bayesian network
and little xi's of particular assignment
to big XY and little UI and some
assignment to its parents. That gradient
has the following form: it's one over the
value of the parameter at the point that
which we are computing the gradient, times
the summation over data instances. M. I of
the probability of that particular
assignment x I n u I to the node and its
parent, that particular joint assignment,
given all of the evidence in the nth
instance. At the current value of
parameter. So, we basically look at each
and every one of the data instances,
compute the probability of this event, xi,
UI given whatever observations I happen to
have seen. Whether x i or u i are observed
or not, and then I compute that
probability add this all up and divide by
the values of parameter. So that's a nice
sort of usable formula except that we have
to understand some of the repercussions of
that, specifically this requires that we
compute this probability over a
[inaudible] that is a [inaudible] , given
the [inaudible] m , and we need to compute
that for all variables i and for all data
instances m So this effectively means that
we have to run inference for every
instance. And furthermore we need to
compute the probability for every family
in the Bayesian network. Now. Fortunately
we can at least reduce the second part of
this computational cost which is the fact
of, that we need to run this for all i. By
remembering the fact that we have, if we,
say calibrate a clique tree or even a
cluster graph then when we're done with
the calibration because of the family
preservation property a node and its
parents are all going to be in the same
clique or in the same cluster. So a single
calibration process is going to give us
all of these probabilities. At once but
that's only true for given data instance
m, which means that effectively what we
end up with is the following computational
cost which is that we need to run
inference for each and every data instance
at every iteration of the gradient process
which is a very costly computation Now
what are the pros of gradient ascent as a,
as an optimization algorithm. It's a very
flexible strategy, so whereas I, we just
show how the formula applies to table
CPS's. It can also be extended to long
table CPD's via the chain rule for
derivative. Which is not the same as the
[inaudible]. However it also has some
significant cons. First its, it turned out
to be a little bit tricky. Not horrible,
but a little bit tricky to ensure that the
parameters define legal CPDs. So this
gives rise to a constrained optimization
problem where we need to make sure that
the entries in the CPD are all graded and
equal to zero and sum to one, and that
imposes some additional burden on the
optimization problem. And then it turns
out that if you want to get any kind of
reasonable convergence, you can't just do
straight gradient accent. One needs to do
something more clever like [inaudible]
gradient or a line surge, which again
tends to increase the computational cost.
The second strategy, the one typically
uses for optimizing the likelihood
function, is, is a strategy that is
specifically geared for, for likelihood
functions. So it's a special-purpose
algorithm that doesn't optimize any old
function, but rather just specifically for
likelihood functions. What?s the intuition
behind this algorithm called expectation
maximization or '''em for short, the
intuition that you have a chicken and an
egg problem here, if we had complete data
then parameter estimation would be easy
because we know how to do [inaudible]
parameter estimation and [inaudible]
networks in fact its a closed form
problem. Conversely if we had Those full
set of parameters, then computing the
probability of the missing data would also
be easy. Easy in the sense that it
requires making [inaudible] using straight
probabilistic inference which merely may
not be computationally easy but
conceptually computing the probability of
missing data is an easy well-defined
problem. So, we have two, sets of, of
things that we need to infer or estimate.
One is the parameters. And the other is
the values of the missing variables.
Missing data. And each of those is easy,
given the other. And so what the EML
rhythm does is effectively an iteration
process, or, in fact, one can formally
show a coordinate ascent process. Where we
start out with some set of parameters use
that to estimate the values of the missing
data and then use that completion to
re-estimate the parameters, and so on and
so forth, until we reach convergence. So
more formally we pick some starting point
for the parameters. In fact, one can also
initialize on, on the missing var-, on the
values of the missing data. It's more
standard to, to in many applications, to
initialize with the parameters, but both
are completely legitimate. So, say we pick
a starting point for the parameters, and
then we iterate these two steps. The first
is what's called the "E" step, "E" step
stands for expectation, in which we
complete the data using the current
parameters, and the second is the "M"
step. Standing for maximization, and that.
Estimates the parameters relative to data
completion and maximization comes from,
basically something like maximum
likelihood. That's. That's where the M in
maximization comes from. And it turns out
that this iterative process is guaranteed
to improve the likelihood function at each
iteration. That is, at each iteration the
likelihood function is going to be better
than it was before the previous one. And
so this process is an iterative improving
process. Let's make this process more
precise. So, let's consider each of those
e steps and n steps separately. So, the
expectation or estep. Remember this going
from the parameters to the missing,
variables. For each beta case D, and each
family x, u, we are going to compute the
probability of x, u. Given the observed
values in, in that data instance, and
given the current parameter setting, theta
T. With that completion, which, note, is a
soft completion. Because its a probability
distribution over the parameters, over the
missing variables not a single assignment
to x and u. With that soft completion we
are going to compute what is called the
expected sufficient statistics, the
expected sufficient statistics is very
similar to the sufficient statistics that
we had before, when we were computing
sufficient statistics we were counting the
number of times that we saw a particular
combination x comma u, remember we had m
Of X, U as being our sufficient
statistics. Now we have a soft completion
and so we have expected a soft sufficient
statistics, which we are going to denote
with an M hat. Sub-scripted by the
parameter vector that gave rise to the
completion. And, and had sub-theta T for a
particular assignment X comma, U is going
to be simply the sum. Over all the data
instances of the probability that we just
computed. The probability of X, U given
the assignment D sub M and the parameter
state of D. And that is a notion of
expected counts or expected sufficient
statistics which are now in the context of
the m step going to use as if they were
real sufficient statistics and so we're
going to take these expected sufficient
statistics and use them to perform maximum
[inaudible] using the exact same formula
that we would have used had these been
real sufficient statistics so specifically
for example in the context of multinomial
[inaudible] we would have the next value
of the parameters [inaudible] E plus one
given X U, is M. Hat and bar of beta T Xu
divided by m bar theta t of u. Which is,
in using the soft count, the fraction of
xu's among the u's. Let's consider, a
concrete very simple example, which is
that of, Bayesian clustering. So what we
see here is your standard naive
[inaudible] model, where we have a single
class variable. And, a bunch of observed
features. And the assumption here is that
the class variable is, is missing. That
is, it's. Sometimes are never, in most
cases, never observed in the data, and so
effectively, we're trying to identify what
are the categories or classes of instances
in this data under the assumption that
within each class the feature values are,
are, are independent. That is the features
are conditionally independent in the
class, as in the [inaudible] phase model.
So instantiating our formula from the
'''em algorithm for this setting, we get
the following very natural formula. So the
sufficient statistics for, for the class
variable is simply the sum over all of the
data instances of the probability of the
class variable given the observed features
for that data instances, for, for that
data instance. And. The and the val-,
current value of the parameters. That is,
it's the soft counts of how many instances
fall into each category when each instance
is allowed to divide itself up of cross
multiple categories so to use a soft
assignment. The second set of sufficient
statistics which represents the
dependencies between one of the features
and the class variable is [inaudible] had
sub theta of x i [inaudible] and that once
again sums up over all the data instances
and simply looks at the probability of a
particular class variable and a particular
feature, variable and particular feature
given the observed instance, the observed
feature at that particular instance now
with these expected counts we can now go
ahead and do maximum [inaudible]
destination and that gives rise to the
following [inaudible] very simple
equations which is that the theta
[inaudible] is equal to [inaudible] sub
theta [inaudible] divided by m which is a
total number of [inaudible] instances and
theta of [inaudible] given [inaudible] is
going to be a sign N half, feta x I comma
c. Divided by n half feta of c. Which
again is the standard formula. But using
soft rather than the hard counts.
2012022923-01-32-532c1979a83-046d-47e7-b4cd-af0448a5141e.mp3
So, to summarize the '''em algorithm, if
we have in this case, the exact same
problem that we had in the context of the
gradient ascent algorithm, which is that
we need to run inference, the probability
of (xI, c) for each data inference of
each generation. As for, the gradient
ascent algorithm, this only requires a
single calibration, because of the same
family preservation property that was
useful there applies equally here. What
are the pros of [inaudible] its very easy
to implement on top of an existing
[inaudible] destination procedure that one
might have for complete data so having
implemented an mle procedure one can
easily build on top of that by adding a
separate e step for computing the
[inaudible] expected sufficient statistics
... >> Empirically, it turns out that the
'''em also makes very rapid process,
progress, in terms of converging, to a
better and better set of parameters.
Especially in early iterations. And we'll
see some empirical results for that in a
bit. The cons of the '''em algorithm is
that the convergence generally slows down
at later iterations, and so it requires
sometimes that later iterations might use
say some kind of conjugate gradient
algorithm because it turns out that that's
more effective there.