Until now we've tackled the problem of
learning a model, structure, or parameters
from the case of complete data. We're now
going to move to what turns out to be a
much harder situation, where we're trying
to learn when we have only partially
observed data. This arises in a variety
of settings. It arises when we have a
scenario where we, where some variables
are just never observed. They are hidden
or latent. It also occurs when some
variables are just missing because some
measurements weren't taken. It turns out
as will see that these settings provide
significant challenges both in terms of
the foundations defining the learning
tasks in a reasonable way and from a
computational perspective where as we see
the computational issues that arise in
this incomplete data setting or
considerably more challenging. I mention
latent variables. Let's try to argue why
we might care about latent variables. So,
one reason is latent variables can often
give rise to sparser and therefore easier
to learn models. So let's imagine that
this is my true network. G star, where we
have three variables leading into this
variable, H, and then the three variables
at the bottom. And if all variables are
binary, then this is a network that can
be parameterized with seventeen
independent parameters. But now, let's
imagine that I've decided that h is
latent. And I'm just going to learn the
network over the observable variables which
are the x's and the y's. And, so what is
the network that correctly captures the
structure of the distribution p over x
one, x two, x three, y one, y two and y
three. And it turns out that this network,
if you think about this, has first because
H is not there, an edge from every X to
every Y. And furthermore. Because the Ys
are no longer conditionally independent,
given the X's, because they're only
conditionally independent, given the H
that I don't observe. Then I have also
edges between the Ys directly. So the
spaghetti actually turns out to look like
this, with a total of 59 parameters in the
network. So by dropping this one latent
variable, I've created a model which is
much harder to learn. Now, of course,
learning a model with the latent variables
is, by itself, a, A problematic situation
but it may well be worth the tradeoff. So
the other reason why we might care about
learning latent variables is because they
might be interesting. They might provide
us with an interesting characterization of
structure in the data, and I'll give
examples of that in a later module. But
for the moment, just as a teaser, imagine
that we have a data set corresponding to
3D point clouds, that are scanned of a
human body. And we would like to discover
from that, what are the, what is the limb
structure of the person, that, to which
the scans correspond? That is, we want to
identify clusters in the data, cluster in
the point cloud, that correspond
to body parts. And so we want to basically
end up with an output where each point has
a latent variable representing which body
part it belongs to. So having motivated
why we might care about missing data,
let's think about some of the complexities
that arise. So let's imagine that somebody
gives us this sequence over here and says,
you know, here's these question marks,
marks that correspond to missing data. How
do we treat this? And the answer is, if
you don't know why these data are missing,
you have no idea how to proceed. And so to
understand that, let's consider two
different scenarios. The first one is an
experimenter is asked to toss the coin.
And occasionally, the, the coin misses the
table, and drops on the floor, and the
experimenter is, you know, too tired to go
crawl under the table to see what
happened. And so they don't record the
value of the coin in the cases where it
fell on the floor. Case two is the coin is
tossed but the experimenter doesn't like
tails. For some reason tails are, are you
know, give him the heebie jeebies and so
tails are not reported sometimes. Note in
these two cases really should give rise to
very different estimation procedures if we
are trying to learn from this dataset.
Specifically, in the first case, we should
probably just ignore the question marks and
just learn from the sequence of observed
instances, HTHH. Because the other one,
beside from being missing it doesn't help
anything about the point. In case two on
the other hand, we can't really ignore the
missing measurements. We need to learn
from the sequence H T, T, T H T H, because
ignoring the missing values is effectively
ignoring something that is, predominantly or
entirely tails. And so, we can get
incorrect estimates if we just ignore
them. So in order to correctly learn the
missing data we need to actually consider
the, the mechanism by which the data was
made to be missing. And so how do we model
the notion of missing data? So, let's
imagine that we have a set of random
variables that, that define our model,
and, in some instances, we may observe
some, but not others. And so we're going
to define a set of observability variables
which are always observed. And basically,
O sub I tells us, is one if XI is
observed. And zero otherwise. And so we
always know whether we observe the
variable or not, and so OI is always
observed. And now we're going to add a new
set of random variables, which are also
always observed. These are the variables
that we're going to call yi which have the
same value as xi. So each one has the same
value space as xi. Except that there is
also the, I didn't get to observe it
value. And so in the real data case, we,
in the real scenario, we basically get to
observe the y and we get to observe the
o's and the x's are not observed. Now, the Y's are a deterministic function of the X's
and the O's. So Y is equal, YI is equal to
XI when O is observed. And is equal to
question mark when O is not observed. So
in the cases wh-, where the val-, where I
have OI is equal to one, I can reconstruct
the value of XI. But for the cases where I
don't have the observation, I can't. And
so this is a way of just defining the, the
observability, pattern that I have. With
this set of variables, I can now model the
two, the two different scenarios that we
had before. In this scenario. This
corresponds to the coin falling on the
ground every once in awhile. We have a
separate model over here that represents
our, our observability pattern and we see
that a variable is sometimes observed by
chance. And that the target and observed
value Y depends on X and on O, but there
is no interaction between the value of the
coin and whether I end up observing it or
not. By comparison, in the case where the,
experimenter doesn't like tails, we see
that the X, that the true value of the X
variable affects whether it's observed or
not. And so, we have an edge from X to O.
So when can, in which of those cases can
we ignore the missing data mechanisms, and
focus only on the likelihood of the stuff
that I get to observe? And the answer is,
one can define a notion called "missing at
random." Missing at random is a way for me
to say I can ignore the mechanism. With
the observability and focus only on this
piece over here. Personal famous
[inaudible]. So one can show that it
suffices for this question, for focusing
only on the likelihood, that this
distribution over X and Y and O have the
following characteristics. That the
observation variables, O. [inaudible] are
independent of the unobserved X's. Which
we're going to denote h, given the
observed values. Y, which are my data
instances. Which means that if, you tell
me the values that you observe, then the
fact that something may or may not been
observed doesn't carry any additional
information. Now this is a little bit of a
tricky notion, so let's try and give an
example. Imagine that a doctor, a patient
come, comes into the doctor's office, and
the doctor chooses what set of tests to
perform. For example, the doctor chooses
to perform or not perform say, a chest
x-ray. The fact that the doctor didn't
chose to perform a chest x-ray. Probably
indicates that the person didn't come in
with a deep cough or some other symptom,
or some other symptom that suggested
tuberculosis or pneumonia. And therefore
the test wasn't performed. So, the
observation or lack thereof, of a chest
x-ray, the fact that a chest x-ray doesn't
exist in my patient?s record, is probably
an indication that the patient didn't have
tuberculosis or pneumonia. So, these are
not independent. So, in that model. We do
not have the missing at random. Assumption
holding because the observability pattern
tells me something about the disease which
is the unobserved valuable that I care
about. On the other hand, if I have in my
medical record. Things like the primary
complaint, that the patient came in. For
example, a broken leg. Then at that point,
given that the primary complaint was a
broken leg I already know that the patient
is likely didn't have tuberculosis or
pneumonia. And therefore given that
observed feature, observed variable which
is the primary complaint, the
observability pattern no longer gives me
any information about the variables that I
didn't observe. And so that is the
difference between a scenario that is
missing at random and a scenario that
isn't missing at random. For the perspe-,
for the, for the purposes of our
discussion, we're going to make the
missing random assumption from here on.
What's the next complication with the case
of incomplete data? It turns out that the
likelihood can have multiple, global
maximum. So, intuitively, that's almost,
almost obvious. Because, if you have a
hidden variable. That has two values, zero
and one. The values of zero and one don't
mean anything. We could rename the one and
zero. And just invert everything. And it
would basically give us an exact the
equivalent model to the one with zero and
one. Because the names don't mean
anything. So that immediately means, that
I have a reflection of my likelihood
function that occurs when I rename the
variables. And, it turns out that this is
not something that happens just in this
case. When I have multiple hidden
variables the problem only becomes worse
because the number of local, the number of
global maxima becomes exponentially
large in the number of hidden variables.
And so now we have a function with
exponentially many reflections of itself
and it turns out that this can also occur
when you have missing data not just with hidden
variables. So even if I already have a
data where, where only some occurrences of
a variable are missing its value, even that
can give me multiple local in global
maximum. So to understand that a little
bit in more depth, let's go back to the
comparisons between the likelihood in the
complete data case and the likelihood in
the incomplete data case. So, here is a
simple model where I have two variables x
and y with x being a parent of y. And I
have three instances and if we just go
ahead and write down the complete data
likelihood. It turns out to have the
following beautiful form which we've
already seen before. Where we have, the
product of probability is for the three
instances. And, each of these can be,
we've omitted writing the parameters for
clarity, and that's going to be equal to,
here is. The, probability for theta X0, Y0
given the parameters, the second instance,
and the third instance. And the point is
this ends up being a nice decomposable
function of the parameters. As, in terms
of, of a product, which, when we take the
log, ends up being a sum. So the
likelihood decomposes. It decomposes by
variables and it decomposes within the
CPD. What about the incomplete data case?
Let's make our life a little bit more
complicated, and, whereas before we had
these complete instances, now notice that
these, both of these instances have an
incomplete observation regarding the
variable, X. And now let's write down the
likelihood function in this case. Well,
the likelihood function is now the
probability of Y0, which is the first data
instance, times the probability of X0 Y1,
which is the second data instance, times
another probability of Y0. So, since Pi P
of Y zero appears twice of we've squared
this term over here and the probability of
Y zero is the sum over X of the
probability of X comma Y zero. That is you
have to consider both possible ways of
completing the data X for the different
values of X. X zero and X one. And so if
we unravel this expression inside the
parentheses, it ends up looking like this:
Theta X0 times Theta Y0X0 plus Theta X1,
Theta Y0 given X1. And the important
observation about this expression, is that
it is not a product of parameters in the
model. Which means we cannot take its log
and have it decompose over parameters of
this summation. Because a log of a
summation doesn't, doesn't decompose. And
so that means that our nicely
compositioned properties of the likelihood
function have disappeared in the case of
incomplete data. It does not decompose by
variables. Notice we have a theta. For the
X variable sitting in the same expression
as an entry from the P of Y given
X CPD. It does not decompose within
CPD and even computing this likelihood
function actually requires that we do a
sum product computation. So it requires
effectively a form of probabilistic
inference. So what does that imply both of
these properties that we talked about in
previous slide? What does that imply
about the likelihood function? Before, our
likelihood function had the form of these
gray lines over here. So for example like
this. This is a likelihood function of the
complete data scenario. Then, when we have
a multi, when we have a case of incomplete
data we're effectively summing up the
probability of all possible completions of
the unobserved variables and so the
overall likelihood function ends up being
a product of Ends up being a summation,
sorry. A summation of likelihood functions
that corresponds to the different ways
that I have to complete the data. So this
end up being, where this is one summation.
So the likelihood function ends up being a
sum of. Like, some of these nice concave
likelihood functions. Well [inaudible]
concave likelihood functions. But the
point is, when you add them all up it doesn't look so nice at all. It ends up having multiple
modes and it's very much harder to deal
with. The second problem that we have, in
addition to multi modality, is the fact
that the parameters start being correlated
with each other. So if you remember when
we were doing the case of complete data,
we had the likelihood function being
composed as a product of little
likelihoods for the different parameters.
What happens when we have an incomplete,
data scenario? So, when you look at this,
you can see, for example, that when X is
not observed, that when X is not observed.
You have an active V structure that goes
from theta YX through Y all the way to
theta X. And so intuitively that suggests
to us that there is a correlation, an
interaction, between the values that I
chose for theta Y given X and for theta X.
And when you think about the intuition for
that, it makes perfect sense. Because, for
example, if theta X chooses to make XO
very, very likely, then most of the
instances where X is unobserved will be
assigned to the XO case, and that's going
to basically, have me, you can assign the
data instances to the x0 and that's going
to change the estimates of theta y given x0
relative to theta y given x1 because most
of the instances now correspond to x0
rather than x1. In absence of correlation
between sum and to see that correlation
manifesting. Let's look at some graphs.
And so what we're seeing here is actually
the correlation between two entries in the
CPD theta y given x. So, over here we see
theta y given x0 and here is theta one
given x1. What you see here is the contour
plot of the likelihood function, a data
points and zero missing measurements and
you can see that this is a nice product
likelihood function with a nice peak in
the middle and there's no interaction
between two parameters. But as we start to
gain more, more missing measurements, you
can see that the curves starts, that the
counter flocks start to deform and even
with three missing measurements see there
is significant interaction between the
value that I end up picking for theta
of y given x1 and the value will be end up
theta y given x0. So to summarize
incomplete data, is actually something
that arises very often in practice, and it
raises multiple challenges and issues. How
are the, how are the missing values
generated? What makes them missing, turns
out to be very important. The fact that
there are certain components of the model
that are just unidentifiable because there
is several equally good solutions. So, if
you pick the best one, you better realize
that there are others that are equally
good out there. And finally the complexity
of the likelihood function is another
significant complication when doing this
kind of when trying to deal with
incomplete data.