One simple yet extraordinarily useful
class of probabilistic temporal models is
the class of hidden [inaudible] models.
Although these models can be viewed as a
subclass of [inaudible] networks, we'll
see that they have their own type of
structure that makes them particularly
useful for a broad range of applications.
So, a hidden mark up model in its simplest
form can be viewed as a probabilistic
model that has a single state variable S
and a single observation variable O. And
so the model really has only two
probabilistic pieces, there is the
transition model. That tells us the
transition from one state to the next over
time, and then there is the observation
model, that tells us, in a given state,
how likely we are to see different
observations. Now, you can unroll this
simple 2TBMs. So if this is our 2TBM, you
can unroll that to produce an unrolled
network, which has the same repeated
structure of, you started this state at
time zero, move to the state of time one,
and so on. And in each state, we make an
appropriate observation. But what's
interesting about hidden Markov models is
that they often have a lot of internal
structure that manifests most notably here
in the transition model. But sometimes
also in the observation model. So here is
an example of what the, of what a
structure transition model would look
like. And this entire model is actually an
un-, is peering into the CPD of the
probability of. The state at time of the
next state given the current state. So
each of these nodes in here is not a
random variable rather it is particular
assignment to the state variable
[inaudible], the state that the model
might be in and what you see here is the
structure of transition matrix that tells
us that from S1 for example the model is
likely to transition to S2 with
probability 0.7 or stay in S1 with
probability 0.3. And so the. These two
outgoing probabilities have to sum to one,
because it's a probability distribution
over the next state, given that, in the
current time point, the model is in state
S1. And we similarly have that for all
other states. So here, from S4, for
example, there is a probability of 0.9 of
going to S2, and 0.1 of staying at S4. So
here the structure is actually a sparsity
in the transition model as opposed to
something that manifests at the level of
the two TDN structure which is actually
fairly simple. [sound] It turns out that
this kind of structure is useful for a
broad range of applications. Robot
localization, speech recognition, where
[inaudible] are really the method of
choice for all current speech recognition
systems, biological sequence analysis,
[inaudible], for example, annotating in
DNA sequence with elements that are
functionally important and other elements
that are not of importance, and similarly
annotating a text sequence with a
particular, annotating words with the role
in the sentence, for example. All of these
are methods where hidden Markov models
have been used with. Great success. So
let's look for example what the HMM would
look like for robot localization. This
might not look exactly like an HM to begin
with because it has some additional
variables. So, let's talk about what each
of these variables means. Here what we
have here is a state variable that
represents the robot pose, that is the
position and potential orientation of the
robot within a map at each point in time.
We also have an external control signal,
you, which is the guidance that the robot
is told to move left, move right, turn
around. Since these variables are.
Observed and externally imposed, they're
not really [inaudible] random variables.
They're just, inputs to the system, if you
will. And then we have, in addition, the
observation variables, which is what the
robot observes at each point in the
process. Which depends on both their
position and, of course, on. The math.
Position, so that the robot's observations
depend on the overall architecture of the
space that they're in and the state of the
building. Now since, in many of the
applications that we'll be considering the
map is observed, which is why I just
graded out then you can effectively think
of this as something where the basic
structure. Over which where reasoning is
just the set of variables that represent
the s's and the o's which is why this is
really a slight elaboration of the
standard h m model. And here also we're
going to have sparsity in the transition
wall because the robot can jump around
from one state to the other within a
single step and so there's only going to
be a limited set of positions at time
tables one given where the robot is
[inaudible]. Speech recognition, as I
mentioned, is perhaps the prototypical
HMM, success story, because it's so, it's
so much in common use. The speech
recognition problem is to take a sentence,
such as Dorothy lived in, whatever. And
imagine somebody is saying that. And what
is given is input to the probabilistic
reasoning system, is this very noisy
acoustic signal that represents the, the
values of the different, frequencies of
speech in a different fre-, acoustic
frequencies at each point in time. And
what we would like to do is we would like
to Take that input, and put it into a
decoder, that, is going to evaluate
different possible sentences, and
hopefully guess what the source sentence
is, and maybe able to predict it with
reasonable accuracy. So how does speech
recognition work. So this is what an
acoustic signal looks like. We can see
that over here, where at each point and
time we have these frequencies and we can
convert that to the frequency spectrum. By
using Fourier transforms. And what we
would like to do is we would like to break
up this continuous signal into. These
pieces that correspond to words and
recognize for each piece that, which word
it corresponds to. So this is a two-fold
problem because in general in continuous
speech we have to build, identify the
boundaries between words as we are also
trying to identify the words. And it turns
out that the way to do this is not to
think about words as the basic units but
rather think about the smaller entities
that are called phones or phonemes as the
basic units from which words are comprised
and then as we recognize phones we can.
Put them together to figure out what the
words mean. So here is a phonetic alphabet
one of several that break the is used to
define how words are broken up into these
little pieces. And so you can see that
these don't line up exactly with, with
characters in the alphabet. Because the
same character can actually be pronounced
in different way, giving rise to different
phones and vice versa. Sometimes the same
phones can come from different letters.
And so what we see here are the, for
example, the phone called. Er we call it
ur and is pronounced in the same way as
the ur in hurt. And so this is a phonetic
alphabet, and as I said there is many of
those that one can consider. [sound] So,
Once we have the phonetic alphabet, we can
look at a word, in this case this is the.
Phonetic alphabet for the phonetic
breakdown of the word nine. N-, Nine. And,
so you can see that this is an HMM
structure. This is not the DBN, this is
the HMM of, that tells us, at each point
in time, whether you're within the phone
N, I, or [noise]. And so there is a
self-transition loop, because you can stay
in the same phone for more than time unit.
And then eventually, you transition to the
next phone and the next phone. And this is
a typical HMM for a word. Now within a
phone, a phone also lasts a certain unit
of time, and so what we have here is the,
within the phone for a given, within a
given phone, there is a transition model.
In this case the aa phone and it has. In
this case, three states. The beginning, B,
the middle and the final. And this is a
fairly standard breakdown for most phones
that have the beginning of the phone, the
middle and the end. And each of these,
typically corresponds to a different
distribution over the acoustic signal that
you see at that stage in the phone.
[sound] So if you put all these together
if you're trying to do speech recognition
then, and this is for the moment speech
recognition for isolated words, so there
is a start state. And then there is a
transition model from the start state,
that tells us how likely we are, in the
current state to go into one of many
words, and that would be a language model
that tells us how likely different words
are to occur, at this point, and then
assuming, and then given that the model
has transitioned to say the one. Word, the
word one. And we can see that we now have,
across different points in time, that the
model transitions to the [inaudible], and
then ultimately to the [inaudible]. And
then, finally to the [inaudible]. And
then, at the end of it, it transitions to
the end of the word, at which point, the
process circles back, and we move on to
the next word. And the self, and the
transition back to the start is what
allows us to do continued speech
recognition. So this is a probabilistic
model that tells us how speech might be
constructed of first words, then phones
within words and then finally pieces,
little bits of the phone, that we see in
this, in the phone HMM that we saw
previously. And this is a generative model
of speech but what happens is that as you
feed in evidence about the observed
acoustic signal over here and you run
publicist inference over this model what
you get out is the most likely set of
words that gave rise to the observed
speech signal. So, to summarize. Hmms in
some simplistic way can be viewed as a
subclass of the framework from [inaudible]
Bayesian networks. And while they seem
unstructured when we observe them at that
level. When we think of structure at the
level of random variable, there is a lot
of structure that manifests in the
sparsity structure of the, of the
conditional probabilities and also in
terms of repeated elements as we saw in
the previous slides, the phoning, the
phone model can occur in multiple words
and we re, replicate that structure across
the different places where the same.
[inaudible] can be used in, in the
language. And so that gives a lot of
structure in the transition model that
really doesn't manifest in any way at the
level of random variables. And we've seen
that HMMs are used in a wide variety of
applications for sequence modeling and
they're probably one of the most used
forms of probabilistic graphical models
out there.